<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A consolation for our grammar schooles: or, a faithfull and most comfortable incouragement, for laying of a sure foundation of all good learning in our schooles, and for prosperous building thereupon More specially for all those of the inferiour sort, and all ruder countries and places; namely, for Ireland, Wales, Virginia, with the Sommer Ilands, and for their more speedie attaining of our English tongue by the same labour, that all may speake one and the same language. ...</TITLE><AUTHOR>Brinsley, John, fl. 1581-1624.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 187 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 51 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2004-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A16864</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">STC 3767</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC S106549</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99842263</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99842263</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">6904</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A16864)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6904)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1058:9)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A consolation for our grammar schooles: or, a faithfull and most comfortable incouragement, for laying of a sure foundation of all good learning in our schooles, and for prosperous building thereupon More specially for all those of the inferiour sort, and all ruder countries and places; namely, for Ireland, Wales, Virginia, with the Sommer Ilands, and for their more speedie attaining of our English tongue by the same labour, that all may speake one and the same language. ...</TITLE><AUTHOR>Brinsley, John, fl. 1581-1624.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[16], 84, [2] p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed by Richard Field for Thomas Man, dwelling in Pater noster Row, at the signe of the Talbot,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1622.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Dedication signed: Iohn Brinsley.</NOTE><NOTE>The first leaf is blank.</NOTE><NOTE>With a final imprimatur leaf.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Education, Elementary --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2003-10</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-10</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Aptara</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Rina Kor</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Rina Kor</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A16864">
<STC T="S">3767</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99842263</BIBNO>
<VID>6904</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>A
CONSOLATION
FOR OVR GRAMMAR
SCHOOLES:
<HI>OR,</HI>
A faithfull and most comfortable <HI>in∣couragement,
for laying of a sure foundation</HI>
of all good Learning in our Schooles, and
<HI>for prosperous building thereupon.</HI></P>
<P><HI>More specially for all those of the inferiour</HI>
sort, and all ruder countries and places; namely,
for <HI>Ireland, Wales, Virginia,</HI> with the <HI>Sommer</HI>
Ilands, and for their more speedie attaining of our
<HI>English tongue by the same labour, that all</HI>
may speake one and the same
<HI>Language.</HI></P>
<P>And withall, for the helping of all such as are <HI>d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣sirous
speedilie to recouer that which they had formerlie</HI>
got in the Grammar Schooles; and to proceed aright
<HI>therein, for the perpetuall benefit of these our</HI>
Nations, and of the Churches
<HI>of Christ.</HI></P>
<P>LONDON,
Printed by RICHARD FIELD for THOMAS MAN▪
<HI>dwelling in Pater noster Row, at the Signe</HI>
of the Talbot. 1622.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>¶To the Right Honourable his
Maiesties Lord Deputy of Ireland,
and to the right Honourable the Lord Pre∣sident
and Lord Lieutenant of WALES, and the
Principalitie thereof, the Gouernours of the Iles
of GERNSEY and IERNSEY; and to the right
Honourable and right Worshipfull, the Treasurer,
Councell and Company for VIRGINIA, and of
the Sommer Ilands; and to all other Gouernours
within his Maiesties dominions, to whom the
charge and care of Schooles; namely, those of the
inferiour sort, are assigned: with all true fauourers of
good Learning, who vnfainedly wish the perpetu∣all
flourishing of the Church of God, and of their
natiue Countrey, I. B. wisheth all happinesse in
Christ eternally.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">A</SEG>Fter many thoughts to whom I
should more particularly dedicate
this my hoped Consolation, (right
Honourable able and right Worship∣full,)
the Lord in his wisedome
and mercie (I trust) directed me
vnto your selues, as those whom it doth in a peculiar
manner concerne. That like as he hath appointed you
<PB REF="3"/>
to these places, so ye may euer haue before your eies, the
speciall ends for which he hath assigned them to your
trust, &amp; for which you must be answerable to his hea∣uenly
Maiesty. The first and chiefe whereof (as I con∣ceiue)
is this, That his pure religion, honour, and true
worship, may be set vp, and aduaunced in them;
the next, that the wealth and sauing of all his poore
people in those places, both of their soules and bodies,
may be by you procured, so farre as in your power
shall lie. And these things to be effected principally,
by a learned, holie, and faithfull Ministerie, protected
and assisted by a godlie Magistracie, and by propaga∣ting
and spreading all good learning and knowledge
amongst them. To this purpose God hauing ordained
schooles of learning to be a principall meanes to re∣duce
a barbarous people to ciuilitie, and thereby to
prepare them the better to receiue the glorious Go∣spel
of Iesus Christ; as also for the breeding and
nourishing of such a holie Ministerie, with a wife and
godlie Magistracie, and people to be perpetuallie pre∣serued;
your care as I take it, in the next place (that
I may speak with all reuerence and submission) ought
to be for prouision of meete schooles and Seminaries
for them, according to the natures and conditions of
the places, and as God shall raise vp meanes thereto.
And for those which are alreadie so prouided and e∣stablished,
<PB REF="3"/>
that the best orders may be knowne and
receiued, for the speediest aduancement of the best
learning in them, and for accomplishing all the good
thereby desired; and withall for supply of what pri∣uate
helpes Gods goodnes shall vouchsafe, for bree∣ding,
and nourishing, and also preseruing all true pie∣tie
and grace amongst them.</P>
<P>The benefit therefore and comfort of such small
mites, as his heauenlie bountie hath vouchsafed me,
which may be helpefull hereunto, I do most thanke∣fully
and cheerefully, as from his goodnesse, tender
vnto you to this end; And more specially to you, right
Honour able and right Worshipfull the Gouernour,
Councell and Companie for <HI>Virginia,</HI> and of the
<HI>Sommer Ilands;</HI> that planting in a right order,
beginning with the Lord, and the carefull planting
and watering of his sacred Religion, you may finde
a more happie growth, and increase, and euermore
sound and lasting ioy to your owne soules. First, the
mite of my Schoole-labours trauelled in, now manie
yeares for all inferiour and ruder places, whereunto
what blessing his heauenlie bountie hath giuen, I
leaue to the iudgement of all true harted wel-willers
vnto good learning. Secondly, I desire to commend
vnto you, for them, and that vpon vndoubted ex∣perience,
the helpe, and benefit of another poore la∣bour,
<PB REF="4"/>
which he of his goodnes hath likewise granted
vnto me, namelie of a little Treatise called, <HI>The true
Watch, and Rule of Life:</HI> which hauing receiued
the witnesse of sundrie godlie learned, (of whom I
haue for manie yeares intreated the examining; and
censuring of it, after the publique authorizing there∣of)
to be that waie of godlines, wherein we all who
truelie professe Christs Gospel do agree, and that
narrow path, in which all that walke conscionablie,
and carefullie, shall certainely finde eternall Life: I
dare be the more bold in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>tie to make tender of, for
the furtherance of their perpetuall comfort and feli∣citie.
And vnto the same adioyned the <HI>Rule of true
Prayer,</HI> the second part of the same <HI>True Watch;</HI>
wherein I haue followed, (so neare as I haue beene
able) the perfect patterne of our blessed Sauiour:
which two so conioyned, may be for directing pri∣uately
euerie soule (which hath grace to vse them,
and to put them so in practise) as their Sea-card and
Compasse, to keepe them in the right course to their
intended Point; that they may not be carried ouer
farre, nor fall too short of their desired hauen; Yea
to performe that for them, which neither Card nor
Compasse can; to wit, that they may not onelie be k<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pt
from splitting; or dashing vpon the Rockes or Sands,
but that they may saile securelie amongst the most
<PB REF="4"/>
dangerous rockes and perillous tempests. That ar∣riuing
happily, they may likewise euer after be kep<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
safe, in the midst of all sauage and cruell enemies.</P>
<P>And finally, what straits or miseries soeuer they
shall come into, either by Sea or land; that but onely
crying vnto the Lord, they may be graciously heard;
and mercifully deliuered in due time, according to that
which shalbe most for the glorie of his Maiestie
and their owne saluation, with the good of his people.</P>
<P>Though the dedication and patronage of my
Schoole-labours belong vnto our most hopefull and
illustrious Prince, and so in like maner of my <HI>Watch</HI>
vnto most Honourable personages (to whom I am
euer bound) yet I know that the tender of the assured
benefit thereof, after so long triall in the right vse
and practise of them, euen vnto your Honours and
Worships, for these poore soules, and for your more
happie execution of your charge, will be most plea∣sing
vnto them, as who desire the wealth of all.
Yea (giue me leaue to speake iointlie and freelie, yet
in all humble duty vnto you all before mentioned, both
right Honourable and right Worshipfull) euen yee
are they to whom the charge of these poore Countries
and places are committed in speciall manner, and the
prouiding for them. If therefore you should not vse
all holie meanes for the honour of our God, with the
<PB REF="5"/>
sauing and preseruing of all those soules, and their
posteritie, and gaining the verie sauage amongst
them vnto Iesus Christ, whether <HI>Irish</HI> or <HI>Indian,</HI>
but onelie respect your owne ends and proiects, you
could neuer stand before his heauenlie Maiestie, to
answere his Highnesse for it; especiallie, if hee most
graciouslie offering you helpes thereto, you should not
embrace them accordinglie, and to your vtmost abi∣litie
see them put in execution. You cannot be igno∣rant
of the wofull estate of all sorts, so long as they
remaine in ignorance and blindnesse, without the sa∣uing
knowledge of our Lord Iesus Christ, and much
more of all such, as haue bene nourished long in feare∣full
superstition and Idolatrie: and aboue all other,
those who haue bene bred in a manifest, and most
palpable, and euen a visible adoring of Sathan; nor,
how the Holie Ghost hath told vs plainelie,<NOTE PLACE="marg">2. Thes. 1. 8, 9</NOTE> <HI>That our
Lord Iesus will come, in flaming fire to render
vengeance to all who know not God, and
which obey not his heauenly Gospell.</HI> Who
must then be punished with euerlasting perdition,
when he shall come to be glorified in his Saints, and to
be made maruellous in all them that beleeue. Oh set
before your faces the miserable condition of the dam∣ned,
and so the danger of all liuing in blindnesse, whilst
they so remaine. If we beleeue the word of the Lord,
<PB REF="5"/>
and looke stedfastlie with the eies of Faith, vpon
the wretched estate and wofull torment of that rich
Glutton in Hell (by whom our Sauiour fore-warneth
all sorts for euer) it will surely cause vs to looke vnto
our selues.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Luke 16. 24. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></NOTE> Or if we set before our eies the Lake pre∣pared
for all the vngodlie,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></NOTE> and where the bloud of
those soules must be required, if they perish for lacke
of warning or instruction. And finallie, if we consider
aright, <HI>That the righteous can scarcely be sa∣ued,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">1 Pet. 4. 18</NOTE>
as the Holie Ghost witnesseth most plainelie,
and we may see it by d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ilie experience, (when as m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣nie
a good soule, which hath bene carefull to walke
with God, yet in distresse of conscience, and a little
left to Sathans buffe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tings, for their humbling, en∣dure
such miserie, and is so hardly rescued from
him and from vtter destruction) it will surely awake
vs all to looke more carefully to all committed to our
charges. Yee are those whom our blessed God hath
appointed; vnder our dread and gracious Soueraigne
to be as foster-fathers vnto them, and therefore it
concernes you neerelie, to thinke seriouslie hereof;
for if that way of godlinesse, which we professe accor∣ding
to the word of the Lord and our good Lawes
(which I haue long endeuoured to set plainely before,
our faces, in that little Tr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>atise, the vse and benefit
whereof I desire to commend vnto you for them) be
<PB REF="6"/>
that narrow way of life, as wee are assured from
the mouth of the Lord it is; then their contrary cour∣ses
must needes be the way of death and hell. Though
therefore, wee should haue no commiseration of the
poore soules themselues, yet remember the things
that may concerne your owne blessed estate and po∣steritie,
and your ioyfull appearing before the high
Tribunall of our Lord and Sauiour, and then there
will be no more need to mooue you therein, nor anie
other whom the charge of soules concernes, who shall
consider hereof aright, to do your vtmost endeuour
for their saluation. There will be no more need to call
on you to see the gospel of Christ planted among them,
or to prouide them of faithfull Ministers, and to pro∣cure
by all possible meanes all other helps, or that, that
which hath bene most charitablie giuen, and former∣lie
collected to these ends, may be rightlie employed,
and whatsoeuer else the Lord shall hereafter affoord
for their benefit, chieflie to bring them into and keep
them in this narrow path. Wofull is the case of all
those, amongst whom Sathan reignes, and who wor∣ship
him instead of Christ, as all such do, who know
him not, and much more those poore <HI>Indians,</HI> among
whom he (as is reported) is visibly adored &amp; sacri∣ficed
vnto, as their God. Maruell not if honest and
vnderstanding Christians be so hardly drawne ouer
<PB REF="6"/>
to these places, as namely into <HI>Virginia,</HI> or so much
as to perswade their friends to such a voyage, when
as there are in the same so manifold perils, and espe∣cially
of falling away from God to Sathan, and that
themselues, or their posterity should become vtterly
sauage, as they are. This holy care being first had,
for their soules and eternall happinesse; and withall,
that there be no wrong offered to the poore sauage
there, nor scand all giuen to them, there may be a
greater hope of a happy Plantation, and that he will
in mercy afford a plentifull supply of all good things,
and raise vp many to be benefactors and furtherers,
and giue a prosperous successe to all your holy ende∣uours,
with assurance of his fauour present, and for
euermore. But if thorough the wickednes or offensiue
carriage ef Ministers or people, minding nothing
but for their owne aduantage, these poore soules shall
take occasion to conceiue euill of the Lord, and his re∣ligion,
all this hope is vtterly ouerthrowne, in the
very hauen.</P>
<P>Here upon in my desire of their conuersion and sal∣uation,
with the sauing and preseruation of our owne
countrie-men there alreadie, and which hereafter
shall go to them, and of all other in these ruder coun∣tries
and places, I haue bene bold to tender these my
poore trauels, vpon much hope and confidence: That
<PB REF="7"/>
first euen this course of instruction, to be presented
vnto you, being embraced and rightly put in practise,
a most speedy and sure foundation, may be layd for all
future good learning, in their schooles, without any
difference at all from our courses receiued here at
home; and whereby both Maisters and Scholars, may
proceed speedily, and cheerefully, and with certaine
assurance of a blessing; and that so from vs may be
sent continu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll supplies of teachers to proceed in the
same order. The triall whereof I dare (through Gods
goodnesse) tender to any by your selu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s appointed to
m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke full demonstration of it to them, like as I haue
formerly done to the most learned and fit that I could
chuse to this purpose, as appeareth in the Exami∣ners
ce<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sure, in the closing vp of this little Treatise.
And withal, to help that we may haue by the same, not
onely the puritie of our owne language preserued a∣mongst
all our owne people th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re, but also that it may
be readily learned in the Schooles, together with the
Latin, and other tongues, and so more propagated to
the rudest <HI>Welch</HI> and <HI>Irish,</HI> yea to the very heathen
&amp; sauage, brought vp amongst them, the more easily
thereby to reduce them all (as was said) to a louing
ciuility, with loyall and faithfull obedience to our So∣ueraigne,
and good Lawes, and to prepare a way to
pull them from the power and seruice of Sathan, that
<PB REF="7"/>
they may ioyntly submit themselues to Iesus Christ.</P>
<P>And for the <HI>Watch,</HI> being agreeable to the word
of the Lord, as I trust euery one that tries aright shal
find it, I dare boldly a vow, that euery soule that shall
truely put in practise, first that <HI>Rule and Way of
life</HI> to walke in it, shall find more true comfort by it,
then by all the commodities in <HI>Virginia,</HI> yea more
true ioy, with all heauenly riches and felicity, then
all the golden mines of the <HI>Indians</HI> can possibly pro∣mise
vnto them. Secondly, for that <HI>Rule of Praier</HI>
in the same, that euery one who shall learne to exer∣cise
it, as the Lord Iesus hath taught him, shall ob∣taine
whatsoeuer good thing his soule shall desire:
and finally, that so watching and praying, he shall be
kept safe, euen in the midst of Diuels and ten thou∣sand
other perils, and haue the Lord to be vnto him,
as he was to <HI>Abraham,</HI> God all-sufficient, whither
soeuer he calleth him, to be seene of him in the Mount,
and the inheritance of <HI>Abraham,</HI> to him and his, so
walking, for an euer lasting possession.</P>
<P>Thus haue I presumed to tender vnto you (right
Honourable and right Worshipfull) whatsoeuer the
Lord hath vouchsafed me, whereof I haue had hope,
that it might help you in your gouernments and char∣ges,
for the good of those poore people committed to
you, and specially which might further the happy suc∣cesse
<PB REF="8"/>
of that so much desired Plantation, for the con∣uersion
of the heathen, and training them vp in good
learning, and the feare of the Lord, and that so from
the children, it may please God more easily to deriue
the same vnto their fathers, from the younger to the
ancients; and so in time, by some of themselues so trai∣ned
vp, to propagate it to all their posterity: which
(if after further triall made by you) it shal be as cur∣teously
accepted, as it is heartily and cheerefully of∣fered,
according to that which I haue receiued from
the Lord, I shall not onely haue more cause to blesse
his heauenly Maiestie, but also be encouraged still to
prosecute these poore trauels, and to study the fur∣ther
good of them all during life, especially for draw∣ing
the poore natiues in <HI>Virginia,</HI> and all other of
the rest of the rude and barbarous from Sathan to
God, and so rest,</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Yours in all humble obseruance
and hearty prayer to God
for you,
IOHN BRINSLEY.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB N="1" REF="8"/>
<HEAD>A CONSOLATION FOR
OVR GRAMMAR SCHOOLES.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>HE vncomfortable and fruitlesse
toyles,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Occasion of this worke.</NOTE> which the Lord hath left vn∣to
men, to humble them thereby,
haue euer caused many to bēd their
wits and beate their braines, to find
out more plaine and profitable
wayes, both to rel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eue themselues,
and to make their burdens more light. Amongst others,
my selfe hauing first had long experience of the mani∣fold
euils which grow from the ignorance of a right or∣der
of teaching, and afterwards some gracious tast of the
sweetnesse that is to be found in the better courses truly
knowne and practised, I haue betaken me almost
wholly, for manie yeares, vnto this weightie worke, and
that not without much comfort, through the goodnesse
of our blessed God. And thence the more earnestly haue
I pursued this same, for that I haue bene fully perswaded
vpon happie experience (I trust) that I could neuer em∣ploy
my thoughts and trauels more acceptably in anie
earthly thing, or whereby a greater benefite might re∣dound
both to Church and Commonwealth, and in
some sort to euery soule, then in searching out, and set∣ting
forth to the view of all, the shortest, surest, and most
easie entrance to all good learning, and how with cer∣taine
hope of good successe all may proceed therein.</P>
<P>Who knowes not the grieuous complaints, which
<PB N="2" REF="9"/>
(to the disgrace of learning) are made almost in euerie
place,<NOTE PLACE="marg">The vsuall complaints against non∣proficiencie in schooles.</NOTE> for the iniuries done to countries, townes, pa∣rents
and children; because in so manie schooles, the
children, which are the chiefe hope of parents and poste∣ritie,
are either spoiled altogether, or else do profite so
verie litle?<NOTE PLACE="marg">Where good is done, how hardly it is ef∣fected com∣monly.</NOTE> And for the most part, wherein any good is
done, that it is ordinarily effected by the endlesse vexa∣tion
of the painfull Maisters, the extreme labour and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er∣rour
of the poore scholars, with enduring far ouermuch
and long seueritie. Now whence proceedeth all this, but
because so few of those who vndertake this function,<NOTE PLACE="marg">A chief cause hereof, want of knowledge of a right course of tea∣ching.</NOTE> are
acquainted with anie good method, or right order of
instruction, fit for a Grammer schoole? This therefore
hath bene in my heart, to shew my loue and dutie to all
sorts, in seeking for my part to deliuer the poore, pain∣full
&amp; honest minded Schoolemaister from this reproch
and griefe,<NOTE PLACE="marg">The authors desire to help all this.</NOTE> and to helpe withall to supply this so great a
want. And in stead hereof my earnest desire hath bene to
procure a perpetuall benefite to all estates and degrees,<NOTE PLACE="marg">And to pro∣cure a perpe∣tuall benefite to all posteri∣tie.</NOTE>
euen to euery man for his children and posteritie; by en∣deuoring
to make the path to all good learning more e∣uen
and pleasing in the first entrance, then former ages
haue knowne; and thereby also in the continuall procee∣ding
afterwards, so farre as the Lord shall vouchsafe me
his mercifull assistance in this great attempt. That chil∣dren
being so entred in a plaine manner, may striue to∣wards
the goale with vndoubted certaintie of obtaining
their desire, with pleasant delight and chearefulnesse
throughout all their time.</P>
<P>Concerning the singular benefits and blessings which
come by good learning,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Of the rare benefits of learning no good man euer doubted</NOTE> like as to euery particular soule,
and so to whole nations, no man truly wise did euer yet
make doubt. No not anie one who hath knowne aright
<PB N="3" REF="9"/>
what learning meant; or who vnfainedly loued his coū∣trey,
the soules of Gods people, or the Gospel of Christ.
For what maketh a nation to be a glorious nation, but
that the people are a wise and an vnderstanding people?
What is it whereby we come so neare vnto the Highest,
or to that blessed estate from which by our first parents
we are so fallen, and to which we must be renewed and
restored, if euer we shall inherit againe the tree of life, as
by true vnderstanding and knowledge, especially if the
same be sanctified vnto vs? Yea, what is it else whereby
we excell the beastes, but by this diuine reason, with
which the more we are enlightened by the spirit of the
Lord, through the meanes of learning, the more we dif∣fer,
the more we do excell? Or who is he that can giue
God that glorie for which he was created, and redee∣med
from hell, or can in anie measure honour him as he
ought to do, to his owne saluation, but onely he who is
endued with right knowledge and vnderstanding? Con∣trarily,
whence is that inhumanitie, as amongst manie
of the Irish, the Virgineans, and all other barbarous na∣tions,
but frō their extreme ignorance of our holy God,
and of all true and good learning?</P>
<P>If anie man should dislike of learning,<NOTE PLACE="marg">The licenci∣ousnesse of some learned or abusers of learning, ought not to cause vs to thinke the worse therof.</NOTE> or thinke that
there is ouer-much of it, for the strange licentiousnesse
and outragious courses of sundrie learned ones, or for
that so manie do abuse their learning, euen to their own
perdition, without vnfained repentance; why doth not
the same man dislike also of the light, yea of riches, ho∣nours,
and pleasures, all which are abused commonly by
the selfe same men, as they haue occasion, as much as
learning is? Good learning is indeed the heauenly light,
the truest honour, the best riches, the sweetest pleasure.
Learning is all, and all in all, if we beleeue that wise <HI>Sa∣lomon,</HI>
<PB N="4" REF="10"/>
or anie of the graue Sages who haue euer liued
since the beginning of the world. Neither is the lear∣ning
of these men the cause of their licentiousnesse, but
this is it in truth; either that being left vnto themselues,
to humble them thereby, they haue put out that light of
learning which checked and controlled them, and haue
chosen, in their courses, to liue in darknesse rather then
in the light; or for that God hath therfore in his heauie
displeausre and most iust iudgement (as we are to feare
of manie of them) giuen them vp to such palpable blind∣nesse
in the midst of the shining light of this last age, be∣cause
<HI>they loued darknesse rather then the light,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Iob. 3. 19. 2. Thes. 2. 10.</NOTE> or at least
for that they <HI>receiued not the loue of the truth, that they
might be saued.</HI></P>
<P>But wholly to conuince all sorts,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Learning is the glorie of man, in the verie naturall mans account</NOTE> that learning is the
true light, and that principall part of mans glorie; let any
naturall man aske of his owne heart, whether if he would
haue his child brought vp to make a worthie man, he
would not haue him trained vp in the most excellent
learning, notwithstanding all the abuses of it, and what∣soeuer
can be deuised against it. And why should anie
one who knoweth but the law of nature, much more the
diuine law of our holy God, <HI>(that whatsoeuer we would
that men should do to vs euen so we should do to them)</HI> once
grudge or disdaine that vnto others, which of all other
things he most desireth for himselfe &amp; his? Why should
he not as well repine against them for the vse of light,
seeing the Lord in his rich bountie, in like maner gran∣teth
the light of true learning to be communicated to e∣uerie
one, chiefly for his soule, as he shall be capable, as
well as he hath the light of the day for the bodie; and also
hath charged all most strictly, to seeke after it aboue all
other things. According to that of <HI>Salomon: Wisedome is
<PB N="5" REF="10"/>
the principall thing,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Prou. 4. 7.</NOTE> therefore <HI>get wisedome, and with all
thy getting get vnderstanding. Exalt her, a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d she shall pro∣mote
thee, she shall bring thee to honour when thou doest em∣brace
her.</HI> Wisedome is that one thing without which a
man is not in truth a man, nor can euer honour his Crea∣tor
as he ought.</P>
<P>Yet to passe ouer this point, as not so needfull (I hope)
amongst vs, especially the true professors of Christs glo∣rious
Gospell; whereof neuer anie one was a sound fa∣uourer,
who was not likewise an earnest furtherer of the
best learning: &amp; contrarily, they onely who haue sought
the ruine of the Church, as <HI>Iulian,</HI> haue sought (cun∣ningly
at least, and vnder other faire pretences) the shut∣ting
vp of the schoole dores, and the bringing of all good
learning into open contempt or base esteeme. And the
rather do I represse my selfe herein, for that this point
hath bene so worthily handled and cleared by some of
high place now sundrie yeares agoe, and all obiectours
put to silence.</P>
<P>To ret<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rne therefore towards our proposed marke,<NOTE PLACE="marg">The first and principall meanes of good lear∣ning, the schooles of learning.</NOTE>
&amp; to consider of the meanes whereby the Lord bestowes
this heauenly gift of all true knowledge and good lear∣ning;
is not the first and principall the right education
of children in the Grammer schooles, which God hath
ordained to be his nurseries of all learning and vertue?
In verie many of which schooles abroad the contrarie
rudenesse is notwithstanding verie much to be pitied
and layed to heart of all; like as it hath bene long, and is
at this day too generally complained of, and that to be
feared not without iust cause.<NOTE PLACE="marg">In what schooles the best learning &amp; nurture are to be found.</NOTE> Of which sort are all those
wherein the schollers are so brought vp, as that they are
made more vnfit for anie calling, or so much as to take
paines in anie profitable employment. But these true
<PB N="6" REF="11"/>
nurseries are onely such, wherein learned Maisters and
Vshers, being incouraged with meete maintenance and
due rewards, do follow the best &amp; most approued cour∣ses,<NOTE PLACE="marg">A wonderfull differēce be∣tweene those scholes wher∣in the best or∣ders are ob∣serued, &amp; the rest.</NOTE>
labouring constantly to put the same in vre. For in
these a wonderfull difference will appeare, when they are
compared with those other, in which the right meanes
and orders are litle knowne, and lesse regarded to be put
in practise.</P>
<P>And first to begin with the matter of learning,<NOTE PLACE="marg">1. The matter of learning easie in such schooles.</NOTE> which
ordinarily and in it selfe, through our naturall blindnesse
and dulnesse is so hard and vnpleasant; it is made in these
schooles most easie, and replenished with all sweete de∣light.</P>
<P>Secondly for the manner of proceeding,<NOTE PLACE="marg">2. The maner of procee¦ding in a sin∣gular order without con∣fusion.</NOTE> it is in these
schooles so direct and orderly, to the verie highest top
of all perfection in the same, that the things taught be∣fore
do euer giue light to those that follow after; and the
later do so hang vpon the former, as that they haue a
continuall dependance, and also the scholars haue a con∣tinuall
helpe and vse of all those things which they haue
learned before. There is moreouer in them a very come∣ly
array, as in a well gouerned armie, each knowing his
owne ranke and office,<NOTE PLACE="marg">The painefull schoolmaster may there ex∣pect a rich blessing.</NOTE> without the least disorder or con∣fusion.
Whereupon the painfull Schoolemaister may,
through Gods blessing, as certainly expect much com∣fortable
fruit of his labours, as anie other man in all the
world. That euen as the best husbandrie bringeth forth
vsually the greatest increase, the shortest and safest cut
in nauigation, doth fetch in soonest the double gaine; so
the shortest and fairest way of teaching, shall bring in
speedily double learning without anie losse or danger.
So as it must needs be great follie to go further about
with more trouble and perill, where a shorter and more
<PB N="7" REF="11"/>
sure line is plainly directed and pointed out vpon infal∣lible
experience.</P>
<P>But for the fruits hereof they will be found such,<NOTE PLACE="marg">The fruite hereof able to encourage each Maister to take the vttermost paines to fol∣low the best manner.</NOTE> as are
able to allure and encourage euerie one, to take the vt∣termost
paines to seek out &amp; to practise the best meanes
which euer God shall afford. For in the meaner schooles
will soone appeare such a change, from raw and rude be∣hauiour,
vnto all commendable qualities, as if they had
bene cast in a new mould.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Hence wil en∣sue a maruel∣lous chāge in schooles.</NOTE> So that verie children will be∣gin
to vnderstand, write, speake, oppose and answer, and
in all thinges so to demeane themselues, as to gaine
the hearts of all who shall rightly make triall, and
compare them with most others.<NOTE PLACE="marg">The bringing learning into esteeme, and to make it to be desired, &amp; honored of al▪</NOTE> Whence it must needs
follow, that whereas learning is now commonly so
basely reputed of, and so few in the countries abroad
regard to set their children to it; yet if the best courses
were in vse, euerie one would desire to haue his brought
vp in some learning and nurture,<NOTE PLACE="marg">The stirring vp many be∣nefactors to learning.</NOTE> and all of the better sort
and qualitie should be prouoked to become benefactors
to schooles, to augment their maintenance and encou∣ragements
for the nourishing &amp; increasing of the same.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Things ac∣companying a right course in procee∣ding.</NOTE></P>
<P>These things likewise will certainly accompanie such
a right order of proceeding; both a maruellous free∣dome
of the Maisters from their wearinesse and discon∣tent,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Deliuery of the maisters from much vexation and ouermuch se∣ueritie. Of scholars from terrour.</NOTE>
and from that ouer-great seueritie which they are
enforced to exercise, or else to do litle good; and withall
a ioyfull deliuering of the poore children from that con∣tinuall
feare, whereby in manie schooles, the greatest
part haue bene wont to be exceedingly dulled and to be
made most vnwilling to their bookes.<NOTE PLACE="marg">That all things in schooles may be done with delight and comfort.</NOTE> That now contra∣rily
Maisters may teach with much delight and comfort,
and scholars learne with an ingenuous emulation, like
as they recreate themselues in their ordinarie sports. And
<PB N="8" REF="12"/>
for the time spent in getting learning,<NOTE PLACE="marg">More substan¦tiall learning in such at 7. yeares▪ then in others atten.</NOTE> assuredly more
true, sound, and substantiall learning will be found to be
gotten in such places in seuen yeares, then is in others
commonly in seuen and halfe seuen. For this is a thing
notorious,<NOTE PLACE="marg">State of most schooles and scholars of 15. yeares of age.</NOTE> that in the greatest part of our common
schooles abroad, (some few of principall note excep∣ted)
the scholars at fifteene or sixteene yeares of age,
haue not commonly so much as anie sense of the mea∣ning
and true vse of learning, for vnderstanding, resol∣uing,
writing, or speaking, but onely to construe and to
parse a little, to steale an exercise, and to write such La∣tine
as anie of iudgement will disdaine to reade.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Vnfit for the Vniuersities.</NOTE> That in
respect of being fit to be sent to the Vniuersities with
credit, that they may proceed with delight and vnder∣standing,
when they come there, they are commonly so
senslesse, as that they are much meeter to be sent home
againe. And if they be admitted into the Vniuersities, it
is not without the griefe of all who respect the credite
thereof.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Euils in their entrance and continuance in the Vni∣uersities.</NOTE> So as that they enter commonly with fowle dis∣grace,
and continue with much contempt, to spend their
friends monie &amp; their owne precious time, which might
haue bene farre better employed. That they become
there a great deale more readie to anie kinde of exercise
then vnto the studie of good learning, the ignorance
whereof proues such a reproach vnto them. Hence also
after sundrie yeares so euilly spent, manie of them return
home againe, almost as rude as they went thither, or are
sent abroad to be vnprofitable burdens, both of the
Church and Common-wealth perpetually. Or if such
do light into the hands of painfull and conscionable Tu∣tors,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Tutors must playe the schoolmasters if euer they shall do good.</NOTE>
and fall to their studies, yet their Tutors must then
act for them the School-maisters part, which must needs
be verie harsh and vnpleasing, yea rare to be found
<PB N="9" REF="12"/>
amongst them. So that in stead of their Academicall
readings, they must be enforced to supplie that which
was wanting in the Grammar schoole.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Such scholars must vse ex∣traordinarie paines.</NOTE> Such schollars
must likewise vse extraordinarie paines and industrie, and
be of most happie capacities, if euer they shall come to
that pitch and height of good learning, which being
trained vp rightly from the beginning, they might verie
easily and in shorter time haue attained vnto.</P>
<P>Hereof the complaints of the worthiest and most care∣full
Tutors in the Vniuersities giue too sufficient testi∣monie.<NOTE PLACE="marg">And doing best, shall yet euer feele the want of the Grammar schoole.</NOTE>
And though such scholars proue neuer so well,
yet shall they feele the want of the Grammar schoole all
their life long. But to leaue the Vniuersitie a litle, and
to returne to our schooles againe for the gracing of thē.
Whereas now in sundrie of them, yea some which are
of good maintenance, there are to be found some few
like vnprofitable drones, not by the vnaptnesse of na∣ture,
but for lacke of better guidance and education;
then contrarily should we haue all such schooles gene∣rally,
as the litle bee-hiues,<NOTE PLACE="marg">If the best or∣ders were had the schooles should be as the bee-hiues</NOTE> euerie one in his owne cell,
and each knowing his owne taske, and all gathering
iointly to fill the hiues with the most excellent life ho∣nie.
So that tast wheresoeuer you pleased, you might e∣uer
find most sweete contentment; if thus the best cour∣ses
were alike made known to all, and care had that they
might be constantly put in practise euerie where. Yea
then it would come to passe, that whereas now there is
litle or nothing in verie manie of them, wherein the eye
or eare can take delight, but rather those who come to
make triall haue enough at the first, and euer take iust
cause of griefe, that there should be such lamentable
spoiling of so manie toward youths, so wretchlesse mis∣spending
of their golden age, with such inualuable and
<PB N="10" REF="13"/>
irrecouerable losse and iniurie to all,<NOTE PLACE="marg">As the good∣ly gardens &amp; sweet singing birds.</NOTE> yet in short time we
should see the same as the goodly gardens, &amp; as amongst
the litle singing birds, in the flourishing Spring; where
we still looke and hearken after more sweete varietie of
pleasant flowers,<NOTE PLACE="marg">And general∣ly excell thē∣selues.</NOTE> and of melodious tunes. Then should
we find by ioyfull experience, that each meane schoole
would <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ot onely excell it selfe, but be equall to manie of
chiefer note. And as much as the goodliest garden doth
excell the place ouer growne with briars and nettles, the
litle bee-hiues the nests of drones, so much should these
each way surpasse those same which now they are.<NOTE PLACE="marg">That wee should as much reioice in these, as e∣uer we grie∣ued for the other.</NOTE> That
as we haue bene grieued formerly for the one, we should
be rapt with admiration of the other, and thinke all our
paines and cost farre too litle to be bestowed vpon them.
Maisters should be much more encouraged to go on
with cheerefulnesse, in seeing Gods blessing vpon their
labours, and by hearing the due commendations giuen
to their scholars, then by anie other rewards whatsoeuer.
The children should euer likewise haue their emulation
increased,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Maisters and schollars should pro∣ceed with all alacritie.</NOTE> which of them all should most excell. And to
conclude this point, hence it should come to passe, that
although all could not be expected to excell in learning,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Though all should not excell, yet all should be fit∣ted to some good emploi¦ment, for the benefit of the whole.</NOTE>
(for then should we be left destitute of husbandmen to
till the ground, and much more of meete supplies to fur∣nish
all other callings; neither is it possible, by all the
meanes or paines in the world, to make such to be scho∣lars,
to whom God in their naturall co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>stitution seemeth
to haue denied it; chiefly where parents or teachers thē∣selues
are too indulgent or remisse: so that their children
are disobedient, much absent from schoole, come and
go at their pleasures, neglect their exercises or the like, or
haue bene spoiled by ill entrance at the first,) yet these
things would follow through a right and carefull gouern∣ment.
<PB N="11" REF="13"/>
That a good part would be found in euerie forme
to credit the schoole: some to store the Vniuersities, o∣thers
to adorne all other places and conditions of life;
that thereby might be had men expert in each kinde as
necessitie should require, for the common benefite and
good of all.<NOTE PLACE="marg">All these ve∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ied in some few schooles.</NOTE> All these things we may see verified in some
few and rare schooles, by comparing of which with most
others, and so by considering what a difference there is
(onely through the better courses practised constantly
in them,) we may fully iudge of the truth of all that hath
bene said, and most necessarily be enforced to subscribe
thereto.</P>
<P>Vpon the due consideration hereof,<NOTE PLACE="marg">This endeuor to di<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>charge a debt to all, by making all sorts par∣takers of the blessings, which he hath vouch∣safed.</NOTE> and vpon much
and loug experience of diuerse places, together with the
certaine assurance of these and the like vndoubted bene∣fites,
which must needes ensue generally vpon the best
courses of learning and good education, first diligently
sought out amongst all, and then diuulged for the pub∣like
good, to be put in practise, I haue presumed to en∣deuour
to my poore abilitie, as the Lord hath vouchsa∣fed
me mercie, to make all sorts partakers of this blessing,
and thus to be paying my debts to all, in communica∣ting
the same vnto them.</P>
<P>This trauell therefore hath bene,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Dutie to all in high place for their chil∣dren and po∣steritie.</NOTE> and is my dutie and
seruice, first vnto you all (ye worthies of the chiefest
ranke) who are vnfained fauourers of good learning, and
more especially to you to whom the Lord hath engaged
me and mine; yea my heartie wish (with all thankfull ac∣knowledgement)
towards you, in your children, and
posteritie, in whom you are to remaine after your de∣parting
hence, &amp; by whom you would haue your names
and dignities still preserued euen in the earth. That they
may with sporting, in a pleasant kind of recreation, at∣taine
<PB N="12" REF="14"/>
vnto that heauenly gift of learning, and excell all
others therein, according to their places and degrees.
And that hereby they may adorne your houses, increase
their owne honour in euerie kinde, to become principall
lights, and pillars of their countrey, and not to liue to
the ouerthrow, or the dishonour of your houses, and
names, much lesse to the euil example, or to the spoiling
of the poore people amongst whom they dwell, as those
who leaue their names for a curse behind them.</P>
<P>It hath bene and is my debt,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Desire to all parents.</NOTE> and true desire to all pa∣rents,
to further their comfort in their beloued children,
that they may see before their eyes their childrens for∣wardnesse
in learning and vertue, which may be vnto
them some recompence, of all their loue, care, and cost.
And also that being hereby encouraged to bring them
vp vertuously, they may alwayes haue the testimonie of
a good conscience, to cause them to reioice, in that they
haue had this first care to prouide them this portion.
Hereby they may depart hence with gladnesse, when
they may leaue those in their places, in whom they may
see iust hope, that they shall liue still in the earth with
worthie reputation.</P>
<P>And in more especiall manner hath it bene my studie
for all such who in their naturall and tender affection,<NOTE PLACE="marg">To all more tender hear∣ted parents.</NOTE>
would haue their children brought vp in the most lo∣uing
and gentle manner, as it were in playing, and with
ingenuous strife and emulation, without that sharpnesse
which they cannot endure, so much as once to heare of.</P>
<P>Yea to all likewise of the meaner sort,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Wel-wishing to the poorer sort.</NOTE> that euen their
children may the more easily attaine vnto learning, that
so some of them being aduanced thereby, may become
a stay to their parents, a comfort to their kinsfolkes, a
credit to their countrey which brought them vp.</P>
<P><PB N="13" REF="14"/>
And to come vnto our Schooles,<NOTE PLACE="marg">To the schooles thē∣selues.</NOTE> for whose comfort
I haue chiefly spent my strength, it is my loue vnto you
all, that you may be such fertile Seminaries, of the best
instruction and nurture, as to replenish all places and cal∣lings.
Such as from which all crueltie and terrour may be
driuen farre away; that you may be <HI>Ludi literarij,</HI> truly
so termed; when the Maisters may teach with delight,
and scholars learne with delight: yea when the greatest
delight and comfort may follow in the end, in reaping,
and enioying the fruit of all your trauels. When as the
meaner schooles may be either equall, or at least come
neare to those of greater name, &amp; the chiefe may seeme
as litle Colledges, euerie yeare sending forth their new
supplies, vnto our renowned Vniuersities, our Innes of
Court, and to all other places of principall note; not
onely to match our aduersaries herein, but also to sur∣passe
them in that, wherein they haue sought to gaine
the chiefest credit, &amp; to giue our Church the sorest blow.</P>
<P>It is the debt of my loue,<NOTE PLACE="marg">To the Vni∣uersities.</NOTE> and token likewise of my
thankfulnesse to you, famous Vniuersities, by endeuou∣ring
that ye may be replenished with the choisest plants,
when Tutors may be wholly employed as Tutors ought
to be, that so you likewise proceeding in the best courses
after, may euer flourish more and more, in all the liberall
and worthie Arts, adorned with the sweetest <HI>Rhetorici∣ans,</HI>
the sharpest <HI>Logicians,</HI> most acute and wise <HI>Philoso∣phers,</HI>
skilfull <HI>Physitians,</HI> holy and great learned <HI>Diuines;</HI>
for beautifying and fully furnishing the sacred Ministe∣rie,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Loue to all who haue lost their learning to repaire it, and recouer them selues.</NOTE>
to your eternall praise and commendation, and to
the euerlasting glorie of Christ.</P>
<P>My loue to you who haue mis-spent your time, and
estate in vnprofitable courses, which will be bitter vnto
you in the end, and who know not how to employ your
<PB N="14" REF="15"/>
selues or your talents. That hereby you may retire your
selues in time, and not onely recouer in a few moneths,
that which you haue formerly got in schooles, and now
haue lost, (as experience warrenteth you may in good
sort) but that you may moreouer grow on forward in
the konwledge of good learning, to become at length
some way profitable to the Church of God, and your
countrey which bred you. That at least you may betake
your selues, if not to the more fruitfull reading of the
sacred story with other learned works helping thereun∣to,
to your eternall saluation; yet to the diligent studie
of the famous and ancient Grecian or Roman history, &amp;
their noble warres; to helpe the better to preserue, and
defend your natiue countrey; or for the succour of the
distressed parts of Gods true Church, and the poore
members of Christ against that Roman Antichrist, as
you now see the Lord to neede your helpe, and call you
forth thereto. That thus you may receiue comfort to
your owne soules, of the pardon of your former courses,
and of the Lords fauour, when you shall walke with him
in some profitable calling: which otherwise I can neuer
see how you can attaine vnto, but that you shall find the
flashing of h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll within you, when your consciences shall
be once thoroughly awakened, to consider seriously
how vnprofitable you haue bene; and of that fearefull
doome denounced against the vnprofitable seruant: <HI>Cast
that vnprofitable seruant into vtter darknesse,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Matth. 25.</NOTE> <HI>where shall
be weeping and gnashing of teeth.</HI> This will surely be exe∣cuted
vpon you without your vnfained repentance, and
laying liuely hold on the Lord Iesus Christ.</P>
<P>Finally it hath bene,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Desi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e to all functions.</NOTE> and is mine vnfained desire to all
functions and places, and more particularly to euerie
ruder place, as to the ignorant countrie of Wales, and
<PB N="15" REF="15"/>
more especially that poore Irish nation,<NOTE PLACE="marg">To all ruder places, as to Wales, to the Irish, Virgi∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ia the Som∣merlland<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</NOTE> with our louing
countrie-men of <HI>Virginia,</HI> or where euer else, if it might
please the Lord to cause the light to breake forth vpon
them, which now fit in such palpable darknesse, and in
the shadow of death, and wholy vnder the slauerie of
Satan. To the end to make the way of knowledge more
easie vnto them, not onely to the attaining of the Latine
tongue, but also that hereby they may much more easily
learne our English tongue, to helpe to reduce the bar∣barous
to more ciuilitie, and so to plant Gods true reli∣gion
there, that Iesus Christ may reigne amongst them,
Sathans kingdome fall, and they saued eternally, if the
Lord vouchsafe them that mercie.</P>
<P>To this purpose I cannot but oft thinke of the speech
of a worthy learned man whom Cambridge in his time
much reuerenced,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Maister Iohn Ireton of Legworth in Leicester∣shire.</NOTE> who hauing laboured many yeares
with little fruite, amongst a blinde, and superstitious
people, was wont much to lament, that he was enforced
to labour in a barren soyle where salt had bene sowen:
whence he vsed to affirme that the chiefe hope of Gods
church for all such pleaces so nuzled vp in rudenesse and
superstition, was to come out of our Grammar schooles.
And indeede for bringing men vnto ciuility, the very
heathens saw this to be the onely way, according to these
verses of the Poet, which are familiar to euery child.</P>
<Q><L>Adde quod ingenuas didicisse fideliter artes</L>
<L>Emollit mores,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ouid.</NOTE> nec sinit esse feros.</L></Q>
<Q><L>Right learning of ingenuous Arts,</L>
<L>The sauage frames to ciuill parts.</L></Q>
<P>This was one chiefe cause that all the wisest among them
did so much prefer, and euer so aduance learning, and
learned men.</P>
<P>To shut vp this point;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Discharge of debt to all.</NOTE> this (I trust) shall bring a
<PB N="16" REF="16"/>
blessing in due time to euerie one, when this way of at∣taining
to learning, shall become so plaine and direct,
as that each poore mans child may with a litle cost and
labour get some vnderstanding, to know how to serue
the high God, and his owne necessary occasions: and
that the children, and posteritie of those, may come
to the knowledge of the truth, who themselues haue li∣ued
in most grosse ignorance, and extreame blindnesse.
By the meanes hereof euery one shall be the better ena∣bled
to pay that debt,<NOTE PLACE="marg">That euerie one may pay the debt of his birth.</NOTE> which by his very birth he oweth
vnto the Lord, and to his natiue countrey.</P>
<P>For we are none of vs borne vnto our selues,<NOTE PLACE="marg">For that none of vs are born to our selues.</NOTE> but as the
heathen Oratour could say, <HI>Our countrey doth challenge
a part</HI> (of our life &amp; seruice,) <HI>our parents a part, our freinds
a part, &amp;c.</HI> So that all the course of the life of euery one
of vs should be bent, to the faithfull discharge of this our
debt: so to leaue to posterity a thankfull remembrance
of our well deseruing of them. If the heathens professed
this, how much more should we Christians oft bethinke
our selues, how much we owe not onely to our coun∣trey,
&amp; to the Church of God in generall, but euen to e∣uery
particular soule, and more specially to those whom
he hath linked vs to by nearer bonds. And to this end
ought each of vs to seeke, as he offereth opportunity, to
be alwayes paying this debt of ours; which none are
likely to discharge, so well as they, who haue bene best
instructed in their youth.</P>
<P>Hereupon there shall neuer be wanting many cheere∣full
aduancers of all good learning,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Learning be∣ing in reputa∣tion, shall ne∣uer want mul∣titudes of be∣nefactors.</NOTE> from which so ma∣ny
blessings do proceed, especially when learning shall
come into the right estimation. This also shall be the
chiefest glorie of all such in the earth, to haue bene bene∣factours
and furtherers vnto the best learning and true
<PB N="17" REF="16"/>
pietie, and likewise a notable euidence of the eternall
happinesse prepared for them.</P>
<P>To this purpose if that heathen Orator could likewise
say further,<NOTE PLACE="marg">The chiefest glory in earth to be aduan∣cers o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> lear∣ning &amp; piety.</NOTE> euen by the light of nature: <HI>That to all
who haue preserued, helped, or any way augmented
the happinesse of their countrey, there is a most certaine
place ordained in the heauens, where they shall enioy
eternall happinesse;</HI> how much more boldly may we
Christians auouch the same, vpon certaine grounds out
of the word of God: That there is indeed a place of euer∣lasting
happinesse, and glorie prepared for all those, who
in witnesse of their loue &amp; thankfulnesse to Iesus Christ,
and to their countries, shall employ their studies, and
their wealth, to the greatest aduancement of all heauen∣ly
learning, and vnto the vertuous education of youth,
the hope of the succeeding ages?</P>
<P>Finally,<NOTE PLACE="marg">The glorie of our nation shalbe increa∣sed as learning increaseth.</NOTE> from all these shall the glorie of our nation
be enlarged continually, when men of true wisedome &amp;
godlinesse, do both rule and obey euerie where. A state
most certaine to endure long. A Prince ten times hap∣pie,
and renowmed to be the head of a people so excel∣ling
in all true wisedome and vnderstanding.</P>
<P>Being thus vndoubtedly perswaded of so manie and
rich blessings to ensue,<NOTE PLACE="marg">A part of our happinesse to shew our loue in furthering so great a good.</NOTE> vpon the right finding out, and
making knowne the best courses of teaching in the Grā∣mar
schoole, without the least euill that I can surmise, I
haue thought, that this shall be a speciall part of my com∣fort,
and a mercie aboue all other outward fauors, which
the Lord hath euer vouchsafed me, if I may but do the
least seruice herein, or but shew my desire to further so
great a good. Hereupon haue I bene encouraged (as I
said) not onely to trauell thus farre in it, but also to ten∣der
this my poore seruice vnto all, presuming vpon the
<PB N="18" REF="17"/>
kind acceptance of it amongst all sorts; which the Lord
hath hitherto vouchsafed, so far forth as I know. Because
my confidence hath bene, from my first entrance into
this trauel, according to the desire of my heart, that these
small beginnings might soone receiue such plentifull
augmentations, as in time to accomplish all the good
which hath bene mentioned; and as the Lord hauing ve∣rified
amongst verie manie, will I trust euerie day more
manifest vnto all.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Why this work was the more hastned to the publike view.</NOTE> I also at the first edition of it, hastened
it the more, because, as we are borne for all, (as before
was said) and receiue all our talents for the benefite of e∣uerie
one, to whom they may do good, and are thereby
each so deeply indebted vnto them, so I haue endeuored
since to increase my former experiments, and to make
them vndoubted, by full, and most certaine triall (as I
trust and heartily pray:) that all sorts for whom they haue
bene written,<NOTE PLACE="marg">The vncer∣taintie of our liues ought to make vs to do all the good we can whiles we may.</NOTE> may reape some benefit by them, so long
as schooles or learning shall remaine. And what is my
life but a vapou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, so that I might haue bene taken away
before the work<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> had euer come to light, like as some of
my fellow labou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ers in this kind haue bene, (of whom I
receiued some of these directions,<NOTE PLACE="marg">M. To<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ey. M. Coote. M. Richardson</NOTE> and those not of the
smallest moment) who had bene able to haue done farre
greater seruice in this kind;<NOTE PLACE="marg">We cannot appeare be∣fore our <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>od, if we haue not done our vt∣termost ende∣uour to pay our debts, and to employ our talents to bring most aduantage to our maister.</NOTE> most of whose worthie ex∣periments
in this behalfe, were buried with them? Or
how could I haue euer stood before the Lord, if (being
so fully resolued &amp; assured of the good that might come
by this labour, and for that likewise, by the bond of the
Communion of Saints, all to whom this benefite of it
might redound, had interest in it; the Lord also hauing
offered me so fit oportunitie,) I should not haue sought
the discharge of this my debt to the vttermost farthing?
Might I not iustly haue feared, that he would haue bene
<PB N="19" REF="17"/>
displeased for my negligence and loitering in so necessa∣rie
a worke? Why should I not then still communicate
from time to time, what he hath further vouchsafed me
in my continuall trauell? Yea why should I not stirre vp
all my louing brethren, to the full perfecting of that,
which hath bene by his goodnesse brought thus far for∣ward
towards the same?</P>
<P>Why should we suffer the industrie of the enemies to
be a condemnation to vs,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Considering well the indu∣strie of our enemie.</NOTE> for omitting our opportuni∣ties
of accomplishing any seruice, which may concerne
the glory of our God, the welfare of this people, and the
perpetuall benefit of this our deare nation: when they
watch all occasions not onely to hinder whatsoeuer
good they can amongst vs, but to put out for euer the
candle of Israell.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Witnesse for euer the pow∣der fornace.</NOTE> When as they will toyle day and night
with the perill of their liues, to vndermine, and blow
vp our royall King, and Prince, our Nobles, and wor∣thies,
with all our glorie at once; thereby to make an ea∣sier
passage to their most bloudie and accursed massa∣kers,
to murder all who beare anie loue to Christs Gos∣pell,
yea to destroy vtterly all the people of the Lord, e∣uen
through the whole world, if it were possible, as their
furious rage doth at this day proclaime, though with
the endlesse destruction of themselues both soules and
bodies, and euen of their natiue countrey their mother
which bred them.</P>
<P>Notwithstanding,<NOTE PLACE="marg">This worke hath not bene set vpō rashly, but vndertakē by an holy &amp; warrantable calling.</NOTE> I haue not rashly attempted to en∣ter
into this so great a worke, but, I hope, that I may tru∣ly
say, that the Lord our louing God, who hath holpen
me hitherto, hath called me vnto it. And this hath he
done, partly enforcing me by necessitie, to seeke out the
easiest, speediest, and best meanes to manage this my
calling, and wherby I might do most good in my place,
<PB N="20" REF="18"/>
to be thereby in some sort answerable to the same. Partly
by giuing me a confident assurance, euen from the be∣ginning
of this my trauell, what a benefite might come
to all sorts, by the read<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>est courses once found out; and
more also in this, that I haue seemed to my selfe, by his
goodnesse, to haue from time to time gained euer some∣what
by my search: &amp; haue withall obserued how much
some few schooles haue excelled others, chiefly through
the better courses which they haue followed. Partly by
vouchsafing me strength, and cheerfulnesse to proceed
thus farre, still adding vnto me some new experiments.
More specially by causing me to haue an earnest desire,
and an hope by this meanes to answer the loue of cer∣taine
worthie friends, in seeking that good to theirs,
which I was not able to performe vnto themselues. But
aboue all, hath he called me hereunto, by the encou∣ragement
which I haue receiued from some principall
benefactors to schooles,<NOTE PLACE="marg">By special be∣nefactors to schooles such who had au∣thor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>y to cō∣mand <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y ser∣uice.</NOTE> &amp; good learning; who though
they might by their authoritie and fauours haue com∣manded
all my seruice, yet knowing my endeuour here∣in,
haue both most louingly cheared me, and withall
somewhat supported me to goe through with this so
weightie a businesse:<NOTE PLACE="marg">The <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ight Hon. E of H. M. Iohnson Archdeacon of Leicester∣shire.</NOTE> for the good of their own schooles
and places, and of all others. Who haue not thought it
enough to found or bestow the places, and to endow
them with meete maintenance, vnlesse they shall also do
what may be to leaue in them the best meanes of all
good instruction and education. To whom not onely
my selfe, but the Church of God (as I trust) shall euer
be beholden.<NOTE PLACE="marg">From his So∣ueraigne Ma∣iesties desire for all his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hooles.</NOTE></P>
<P>But to passe ouer this point. That worthie desire of
our royall Soueraigne (whom the Lord long preserue
to his glory and the good of all his people) namely to
<PB N="21" REF="18"/>
haue all good learning to florish in these his dominions,
declared so many wayes, &amp; specially in that his gracious
incitement to all Schoolemaisters (in the conclusion of
his Maiesties letters, set before our common Grammar
(ought not onely to prouoke, but to binde vs all, who
haue this function and charge, to indeuour our selues to
the vttermost, to search out still the best meanes for the
most fruitfull training vp of our Scholars, in all good
literature and vertuous conditions, where he so royally
assureth vs, that as we shall receiue reward of Almightie
God for the same, so of his Maiestie worthy commenda∣tions.
And therefore whatsoe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er comfort we shall finde
by our trauels therein, to make the same fully knowne
for the generall good of all, as God shall vouchsafe vs fit
occasions thereunto.</P>
<P>For the manner which I haue vsed in all this procee∣ding;<NOTE PLACE="marg">For the man∣ner of pro∣ceeding in this worke, the Preface to our common Grammar doth direct it.</NOTE>
the Preface to the Reader in the same our com∣mon
Grammar hath directed me; where hauing affir∣med
that the varietie of teaching is diuerse, and alwayes
will be, for that euerie Schoolemaister liketh that which
he knoweth, &amp; seeth not the vse of that which he know∣eth
not, and therefore iudgeth that to be the most suffi∣cient
way, which he seeth to be the readiest meane to
bring a learner to haue knowledge therein; it directeth vs
thus: <HI>Wherefore it is not amisse (saith it) if one seeing by
triall an easier and a readier way then the common sort of
Teachers do, would say that he hath proued, and for the
commoditie allowed it, that others not knnwing the same,
might by experience proue the like, &amp; then by proofe reaso∣nably
iudge thereof: not hereby excluding the better way
when it is found, but in the meane season forbidding the
worse.</HI> This course haue I followed in all directions
which I haue here obserued, &amp; set them downe accor∣dingly.
<PB N="22" REF="19"/>
Whereas it may be obiected and said,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Though ma∣ny haue writ∣ten hereof, yet none haue proceeded in this particular manner for the helpe of he meanest.</NOTE> that sun∣dry
haue written very learned treatises, concerning the
trayning vp of youth: I answer, that it is so indeede; yet
(that I may speake in modesty as the truth is) all the lear∣ned
do well know, that they are such, as do onely set
downe the same in a generall maner; or do write of some
one piece or two alone, or at most of some few parts of
Grammar learning and matters appertaining thereunto;
and the principall of them vnknowne to the common
sort of teachers: or else they are beyond the capacity and
reach of the meaner sort (for whom this is cheifly in∣tended;)
or at least, they haue specially fitted their course,
for the instruction of two or three alone, to be trained
vp in priuate houses, as our renowned <HI>Maister A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>kam.</HI>
But none whom I know, or haue heard of, haue in this
kind of search and triall, gone through the seuerall parts
of our Grammarschoole learning, applying themselues
for the weakest, &amp; for the common countrey Schooles,
thus leading them as by the hand, thorow all the whole
courses thereof, onely according to our common Gram∣mar
and most approued classicall Authors.</P>
<P>Neither haue I in this,<NOTE PLACE="marg">This worke hath not bene proceeded in by priuate conceit.</NOTE> followed mine owne priuate
conceit, but besides searching by reading, triall and ob∣seruation,
I haue first for many yeares inquired further
(as I said) the best courses, from the most experienced,
who haue proued them: euen of such as haue sent most
excellent scholars vnto the Vniuersities; as I haue bene
assured from some of the chiefe in the same. Secondly I
haue made triall to see a demonstration of euery thing.
Thirdly I haue had (so much as I could) the iudgement
of all the learned, with whom I could confer or commu∣nicate.
Fourthly, so far as I haue bene able, I haue procu∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed
yearely trials to be made by some of the best autho∣ritie,
<PB N="23" REF="19"/>
learning, and iudgement that I could obtaine this
fauour of, &amp; haue intreated them to censure all things
frankely, and to direct vs wherein they found or thought
vs defectiue, to confirme and encourage vs wherein we
proceeded in a right course.</P>
<P>Neither haue I conferred with any louing friend
hereof (so farre as I remember) who hath not approued
of the course, and wished all good successe to this my
trauell.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Nor posted on, but haste∣ned slowly.</NOTE> So that I haue not posted it forward, but hasted
slowly; and vsed so farre as God hath granted me oppor∣tuniy,
all meanes of due preparation, and of mature de∣liberation:
thus enquiring of (as I said) and conferring
with so many of the best experienced, as either my cal∣ling,
or greatnesse of the charges in trauell would per∣mit.
And moreouer before I published any thing hereof
in print, I sent some draughts, vnto sundry learned, for
their helpe and direction, though not to the hundredth
man to whom I desired. For that I was neither able to
get copies enow written, nor to procure them written
truly, much lesse to be at the charge to send thē abroad
into all parts, to many, who I know would willingly haue
laid to their hands, and added their experiments. There∣fore
herein also, in steed of sending any moe written co∣pies
abroad, I after a time, by the coūsell of some faithfull
and iudicious welwillers to this worke, thought it best
to follow that worthy President of most happy labours,
<HI>Maister Perkins;</HI> who when he was in hand with his
Probleme, being aduised to send some copies first to his
learned freinds, answered that he could not get copies
enow written, &amp; though he procured some writtē forth,
and by good scholars, yet they were so defectiue, as that
he could not well send thē. And for that cause he would
print some few of them first, which might go forth to
<PB N="24" REF="20"/>
the view of the world, and so he might heare the com∣mon
censure of all, and receiue the helpe of his freinds,
and then reforme accordingly. Thus did I aduenture
to send forth the former draught of my Grāmar Schoole,
with some other parts belonging to the same to the pub∣lique
view of all, that I might the sooner heare and re∣ceiue
the free censures and better directions of all louing
freinds, and welwillers vnto this worke, so to be forth∣with
trying, reforming and supplying, like as I haue
continued vntill this day.</P>
<P>In the whole worke,<NOTE PLACE="marg">The Author assumeth to himselfe one∣ly the wants &amp; errors.</NOTE> as I promised not any thing but
my trauell, which I haue striuen to performe with all
the poore ability which the Lord hath vouchsafed me,
so I take nothing to my selfe, but onely the wants and
errours. The rest is his who hath giuen this desire, and
prolonged my life, granted me vnderstanding, strength,
and opportunitie to bring it thus farre forward. What
directions or experiences herein, I haue receiued from
others, as yet, or lately liuing, I would haue set downe
with their names adioyned, like as I haue done of some
(which I know might haue brought much credit to the
worke, for the authority of sundry of them; and thereby
euerie one of them haue had their due) but that they did
not thinke it meete, desiring to be concealed. What I
haue gathered out of the writings of the chiefe learned
who haue reuiued learning in this last age, as <HI>Sturmius,
Melanchton, Erasmus,</HI> &amp; others, either shortly set downe,
or plainly poynted at in them; I haue omitted likewise
to mētion particularly; not any way to wrong or detract
from them, but partly for that I did not note the places
at my reading of them; and moreouer for that I thought
that labour more troublesome then profitable to the
Reader.</P>
<P><PB N="25" REF="20"/>
Neither take I vpon me any way to prescribe to the
meanest,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Prescribeth not to anie.</NOTE> knowing my self so far inferiour to the greatest
part, but do begin to thinke more and more, of this
weightie calling, as <HI>Paul</HI> did of the sacred Ministerie, and
to breake out into that his admiration, <HI>who is sufficient
for these things?</HI> who is meete to haue the treasure both
of Church and Common-wealth, with the hopes of all
posteritie committed vnto him, and much more to pre∣scribe
perpetuall rules in this behalfe? Much lesse do I
pre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ume to teach them of most excellent gifts; but as
a poore fellow labourer for the common good, and a
willing learner of all, I do humbly desire the iudgement
and helpe of all the chiefe learned, both for their cause
who wish this, and for the vniuersall benefit of the pre∣sent
age, and of all posteritie. That I may see still both
what they approue in the courses set downe, also what
they disallow, and likewise vpon what grounds; what
may be bettered, what is yet wanting, and what is super∣fluous.</P>
<P>Thus is my hearts desire, to trauel in it still, according
as I haue begun, vntill the Lord shall accomplish the
whole worke, which although it should be seuen yeares
more, yea many moe before; yet the Lord prolonging
my dayes, I shall euer increase in reioycing in my vn∣doubted
assurance of the rich blessing, which God will
giue vnto it, &amp; thinke all my labour most happily spent.
But herein let not any man expect from me great mat∣ters,
in a lofty kind of verse or prose, or eminency in de∣clamations,
orations, or the like, this I leaue to our wor∣thy
renowned schooles of Westminster, Eaton, Win∣chester,
and the rest both in London &amp; elsewhere, and to
our Schoolemaisters of chiefe fame, whose breeding &amp;
imployment in schooles hath bin accordingly; and who
<PB N="26" REF="21"/>
haue ancient scholars long exercised in these kinds. Cō∣cerning
whom I am so far off frō enuying any excellent
learning in them, that I wish all others partakers of the
like in their kind. And for my selfe I content me with
this mercie from the Lord, and blesse him for it, that I
haue trauelled chiefly for our meaner &amp; ruder schooles;
and that he hath vouchsafed me this fauour, to bring my
worke so farre forward, as to helpe to direct hitherto,
according to the things mentioned in the Contents.
Yet this I humbly desire of all such of principall note,
for education, gifts and experience, to further vs with
their better directions in all these exercises and the rest;
&amp; now God hauing so accomplished my desire for the
first foundation, and let me see his blessing vpon the lit∣tle
ons, I will labour to follow them in what I am too
short, as fast as his goodnesse shall enable, vntill I shall
likewise find by experience, wherein that excellency and
comfort of theirs doth consist, and come as neare vnto
them as I can. Though therein, <HI>Cum in primis non liceat;
in secundis tertijsve consistere pulchrum erit.</HI></P>
<P>For the length of the worke in the Grammar schoole,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Reasons for the length of the worke.</NOTE>
I haue in many things contracted very much in this edi∣tion.
And for those things wherein I may seeme ouer
tedious, as namely in the first entrance of children, in
teaching Accidence and Grammar, also for construing,
parsing, and making Latine, I would haue all consider
how therein I haue contended to direct the carefull
Maister, to incite both himselfe, and his little ones, as by
play, to make the least to loue the Schoole and learning;
and for that those things being well performed, all the
difficulty is past. Yea in all such places I would wish you
euer still to remember this, that I wrote not for the great
learned, but chiefly for the simplest, &amp; yong beginners,
<PB N="27" REF="21"/>
both teachers and learners, with whom I cannot be too
plaine; although I haue and do still striue to abridge
whatsoeuer can be, so as I may be well conceiued of
all, for whom I labour; and in the end of euery chap∣ter
haue vsually repeated briefly the sum thereof. And
knowe withall, that I haue thought it my dutie to set
downe whatsoeuer I haue found to be profitable, that
out of them all, the best may bee setled, being confir∣med
by the trials of many. In which respects some of
great learning, who perused the work formerly, haue not
seene how it could well be any shorter, nor what might
well be spared, especially being thus offered to the pub∣lique
censure. Consider moreouer what great volumes
haue bene written of some one of these points alone,
whereas my indeuour hath bene to go thorowe them
all, shewing in euery one, what I take to be principally
necessary or behooffull. And finally remember that
which <HI>Martiall</HI> wittily and truly affirmeth:
<Q><L>Non sunt longa quibus nihil est quod demere possis.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Martial. Epig.</NOTE></L></Q>
<Q><L>Things are not long, wherin there is not ought to
spare.</L></Q></P>
<P>Those for whom it hath bene labored in, who wil not
vouchsafe it the reading because of the length, would
much lesse haue taken the paines, or haue bene at the
cost, to haue trauelled, searched, and tried to haue
found it out. Although this I dare constantly auow, and
keepe within my bounds, that it had counteruailed
vnto me both the labour of an hundredth times rea∣ding
it ouer, and as manie times the charges, if I had
knowne but the things from my first entrance into teach∣ing,
which God hath now thus made knowne to all; be∣sides
the freeing both of my body and minde from much
toyle and griefe. Notwithstanding that I then both read
<PB N="28" REF="22"/>
all whom I could get in this argument of teaching, and
also had from the beginning for sundry years the aduice
and direction of<NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Master <HI>Iohn Ireton</HI> of <HI>Keg∣worth,</HI> men∣tioned be∣fore.</NOTE> one in whose house I liued, who was
well knowne to be inferiour to few in all excellent lear∣ning,
and euen in this kinde amongst other. Neither do I
doubt, but that whosoeuer he be that would do good in
this function, especially of the new beginners, and shall
peruse the worke with desire to make his benefit of it,
shall meete with some one thing alone or other in it,
(which if he will practise it aright) he will freely ac∣knowledge
to be worth all his labour, as I haue done
sundry of them at the receiuing and triall of them, and
much more shall he do the same for all the rest.</P>
<P>Yet for those who would not reade ouer the whole
treatise at large,<NOTE PLACE="marg">The vse of it to the lear∣ned, who would not reade the whole.</NOTE> they may see the sum briefly in the mar∣gents,
&amp; so in the table in the end, to reade what they de∣sire,
to passe ouer the rest. But for them for whom I haue
trauelled, I had much rather to be ouerlong, to the end
that I may omit nothing which concerneth their helpe,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Better for the learners that the worke should be o∣uerlarge then too short.</NOTE>
&amp; may be vnderstood of all, then by being ouer-short, to
omit many things, or not to be vnderstood of the grea∣test
part: as it falleth out in most <HI>Compendiums.</HI> For as I
once heard a great learned and holy man say publikely
in the Vniuersitie concerning <HI>Compendiums,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</NOTE> that they
brought ordinarily but a compendiarie knowledge; so it
will be found certainly true, amongst all learners of
them in matters of any difficulty, vnlesse they haue the
help of good readers, or of most familiar Commentaries
and expositions, to make them plain. Because cōmonly
the learners do imagine that they haue gotten that lear∣ning
by them which indeed they are ignorant of, and so
ceasse from searching further; although for those who
vnderstand them fully, or haue meanes to haue them
<PB N="29" REF="22"/>
plainly opened, they are of most singular vse, for the
easie remembring and practise of the things contained
in them.</P>
<P>Moreouer howsoeuer I should not be able to at∣taine
to each point aymed at here, and wished, nor to
any one of them in the absolute perfection,<NOTE PLACE="marg">This trauell happily em∣ploied, if but to effect these things fol∣lowing.</NOTE> yet I euer
thought from the beginning that my trauell should be
most happily employed, if I might effect but only these
things following, or some of them, as namely:</P>
<P>If I might but set others on work,<NOTE PLACE="marg">1. If but to set others on work hereby.</NOTE> to search yet further,
or to make trial of these experiments or better, for the ful
assurance of all sorts, to finde out at length, that which is
desired.</P>
<P>Or secondly,<NOTE PLACE="marg">2. Or to gain moe experi∣ments, which men are so hardly drawn to commu∣nicate.</NOTE> if it were but to gaine the experiments
of some others who haue most happily trauelled herein.
And the rather, for that sundry of chiefe experience in
this kinde, are so hardly drawne to impart that which
they know; either for lacke of opportunities, or lest they
should be thought to presume ouer much, or suspecting
the censures of others, or for some like by respects, wher∣by
both Church and Common-wealth are depriued of
their due; to wit, of such singular helpes as might excee∣dingly
tend to the benefit of them both.</P>
<P>Or thirdly,<NOTE PLACE="marg">3. Or to make known sundrie most profitable bookes and helpes.</NOTE> if I might but make known amongst alsorts,
sundry most profitable bookes and helpes which God
hath to this end prouided, both for Maisters and Scho∣lars,
which haue formerly bene hid, and are vtterly vn∣knowne
to the greatest part.</P>
<P>Or fourthly,<NOTE PLACE="marg">4. To helpe all desirous to doe good, and yet toyle without fruit.</NOTE> if I may but only help such of my brethren
as toile without fruit or comfort, wearying themselues in
an earnest study to do good, and do mourne and sigh,
wishing better directions. And much more those, who
neuer knew any good proceedings, and liue as burdens
<PB N="30" REF="23"/>
to the publike hurt, for lacke of direction in this behalfe.
That so not any one, who maketh conscience of his cal∣ling,
and will inquire, should be vnprofitable.</P>
<P>Yea fiftly,<NOTE PLACE="marg">If but to gain one yeare.</NOTE> if I might but helpe the common sort,
how to gaine but one yeare only in the getting of lear∣ning,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Thogh there may be hope of almost double sound learning, to that which hath bene in manie rude places.</NOTE>
&amp; lessening of charges, chiefly for the poorer. Al∣beit
that my vndoubted hope is, that by these courses
alone almost double sound and good learning may be
gained, in regard of that which hath bene and is in many
country Schooles, for vnderstanding, speedinesse, cer∣tainty
and delight. That little children being rightly
trained vp, may do more at nine or ten yeares old, then
in many places at fourteene or fifteene, as Master <HI>Askam</HI>
saith, concerning the Northern parts in his time; when
they went to the schoole little children, and came away
great lubbers; alwaies learning, little profiting, learning
without booke euery thing, and vnderstanding within
booke little or nothing, as he rightly affirmeth. And for
the further euidence hereof, that so much more good
may bee done hereby, it is very apparent in this. That
a great deale may be gained by three or foure of these
helpes alone,<NOTE PLACE="marg">For that so much may be gained by three or foure of these helps alone.</NOTE> which either are not knowne, or not practi∣sed
in the ordinary Schooles.</P>
<P>As first, by winning a yeare or two in the beginning,
by <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>etting them to schoole so soone as they are able to
learne.</P>
<P>Secondly, by causing all things in Schools to be done
with vnderstanding. Of the benefite whereof see <HI>Chap.
5.</HI> of the Grammar Schoole.</P>
<P>Thirdly, by making the Scholars very perfect, first in
their grounds, viz Accidence, chiefly in Nounes and
Verbes, after the maner which is shewed there; and after
likewise in the Grammar it selfe, for the perfect vse, vn∣derstanding
<PB N="31" REF="23"/>
and applying of the rules. This will gaine
much in time, and more in ease and certainty then can be
imagined.</P>
<P>Fourthly, by making them very perfect in their au∣thors,
as they proceed.</P>
<P>Fiftly, by the knowledge and practise of the rule of
construing, and of translations formed according vnto
the same, for all the lower sort.</P>
<P>Sixtly, by hauing in all things the most easie, sure, and
excellent patternes to follow; which, they being kept
vnto constantly, must needes come in time to expresse
very liuely, or at least come neere vnto them. To omit
the benefit of increasing in our owne toung as in the
Latin; and all things for going certainly without stagge∣ring
or doubting, and much more by their growing in
their writing, together with their other learning, &amp; that
by one and the same labour.</P>
<P>Now if by these few so much may be gained, and
much more by all the rest together, being constantly
practised: then let euery man iudge what we might cer∣tainly
expect, if many moe learned well-willers, would
adde still but each his seuerall experiment.</P>
<P>These same, amongst others, haue bene the seuerall
ends, whereat I haue aimed, and thought my labours
should be happily emploied, if I might in any sort at∣taine
vnto them. Wherein how farre the Lord hath
vouchsafed to fulfill my desire, I refer it to euery one
who hath or shall duely make triall of that which I haue
written.</P>
<P>That I do in this worke so much account of Gram∣maticall
translations,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Reason of the high ac∣count of grā∣matical trans∣lations.</NOTE> which I so oft mention in the
Grammar schoole, as namely Chap. 8. where I shew the
manner, vse and benefit of them, I hope that this wil be
<PB N="32" REF="24"/>
found true by experience, that after children haue bene
well trained vp in their Accidence, and a litle entred and
acquainted with them, following the courses directed for
thē, they will go ouer their whole Authors so translated,
by the help of thē, before they could haue gone through
one third part of them without. And also that they will
learne their authors far more perfectly for each good vse,
and keepe them much more surely, with lesse labour or
trouble; besides that they shall continually learne by
them to make Latine truly and purely, and to get matter
and phrase, aswell as to construe and parse. And further∣more
because in all the formes which shall vse them,
chiefly in the higher, they wil be found for the most part
to be in stead of the Maisters or Vshers labour, and euer
certaine, teaching English as wel as Latine, without any
of the inconueniences vsually imagined; so that there be
a wise direction and ouersight, as in all other things, that
they be vsed aright.</P>
<P>Besides experience, the reasons are most euident, as
I haue shewed in their place;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Chap. 8.</NOTE> especially by making all
their authors to be so easily and soone vnderstood,
and then for the continuall practise by them of the
Grammar <HI>Analysis</HI> and <HI>Genesis:</HI> and finally that by them
may be such a daily vse of translating both into English
&amp; Latin: all which are so highly commended by the lear∣ned,
for the speedy getting of any tongue. And here∣unto
the two first leaues of <HI>Master Askams</HI> Schoolmaster
whom I principally esteeme and propound,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Master <HI>A∣skams</HI> testi∣monie of the practise of translating.</NOTE> do giue
sufficient testimony. Hee in the very entrance of his
booke, sharply reproouing the common order of ma∣king
Latins practised in Schooles; and hauing shewed
how by that (as it is comonly said) children are vtterly
marred, and also hauing giuen most manifest reasons of
<PB N="41" REF="24"/>
the hurt which comes thereof, for the feare that children
are driuen into: affirming moreouer, that nothing hath
more dulled the wits, or taken away the wils of children
from learning, then that: and lastly how they learne
euill choise of words, wrong placing, and ill framing of
sentences, and that which they must vnlearne againe;
he afterwards speakes thus, concerning this kinde of
translating, and the benifits of it.</P>
<P>There is a way (saith he) touched in the first booke
of <HI>Cicero de Oratore,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">This is well worthie the marking of all.</NOTE> which wisely brought into
Schooles, truly taught, and constantly vsed, would not
onely take away that butcherly feare of making Latines,
but also with ease and pleasure, and in short time, as I
know by good experience, worke a true choise, and
placing of words, a right ordering of sentences, an easie
vnderstanding of the tongue, or readinesse to speake,
facilitie to write, a true iudgment both of his owne and
other mens doings; what toung soeuer he doth vse.
Then he setteth downe the manner, how the child
should be taught to translate a peece of <HI>Tully,</HI> or a like
Author thus plainly, &amp; afterwards out of his translation
to turne it into the Latin of the Author againe; and then
by comparing with the Author to see how neere he
came, and where he missed; so to amend it, still striuing
vntill he come to expresse his Author truly. By this he
saith, the maister may teach all those things which are
most tedious and difficult without any errour, and the
scholar may learne without any great paine, the Maister
being led by so sure a guide, &amp; the scholar brought into
so plaine and easie a way. This is the summe of <HI>Maister
Askams</HI> speech.</P>
<P>Now these Grammaticall translations of our lowest
Schoole Authors, do performe the same things for
<PB N="34" REF="25"/>
all young scholars farre more surely and speedily.</P>
<P>More surely, because the scholar translating into En∣glish
of himselfe, vnlesse the Maister vse maruellous dili∣gence,
before in making him very perfect in the true con∣struing
of it, and as much after in perusing &amp; amending
euery thing which is faulty, the child wil misse in transla∣ting;
and if he translate falsly into English, or misse of the
Grammaticall order, he can not translate into the same
Latine againe, vpon sure grounds and reason, vnlesse
he go by rote, as we say. Moreouer that labour for so
perusing the translations, of euery one of each forme
thorough a Schoole, would be endlesse in the greater
schooles, and much more when they haue turned it into
Latine, for comparing all with the Author, and reducing
each thing into the right order; whereas these being so
translated vnto their hands, do first guide them certainly
how to construe or to translate, to reade all things which
they learne by them, into a true translation, and conse∣quently
to turne them perfectly into the Latine of the
Authour againe.</P>
<P>These do it also more speedily,<NOTE PLACE="marg">More spee∣dily.</NOTE> in as much as they may
reade ouer many lines turning them into English or La∣tine
before that they can write one. Although that kind
of translating by pen of themselues, both into English
and Latine, hath also her due place and singular vse,
for some speciall benefits thereof, as writing true Or∣thographie,
and the like, as I shall shew in the handling
of it.</P>
<P>Furthermore,<NOTE PLACE="marg">This verie course in ef∣fect practised by Maister <HI>Askam.</HI></NOTE> this very course of translating peeces of
<HI>Tully</HI> or the like good Author, into plaine naturall En∣glish,
by the Maister himselfe, and giuing them to the
Scholar to turne into Latine, to trie how neere he can
come to the Author, and then comparing it with the
<PB N="35" REF="25"/>
Author, he sets downe in the beginning of his second
booke, page 2.</P>
<P>By this meanes he saw that experience which might
seeme almost incredible,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Experience of the singu∣lar benefit of it in Maister Iohn Whitne<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</NOTE> in that hopefull young Gentle∣man
(whose death he so much bewaileth) Maister <HI>Iohn
VVhitney,</HI> in Sir <HI>Anthony Dennies</HI> house, where the
Ladie <HI>Elizabeth</HI> did lye, when he came to serue her; that
within lesse then the space of a yeare, he had so profited
in writing pure Latine, that (as he saith) some in seuen
yeares in the Grammar Schooles, yea some in the Vni∣uersities,
could not do halfe so well. So afterwards he
saw the like in his happiest Schollar that euer England
had bred, our late Queene, who made vs all happie;
who, as hee saith, did so farre surpasse all of her yeares
in excellencie of Learning,<NOTE PLACE="marg">This way of translating the chiefe &amp; sure meanes to attaine speedily to any tongue. Maister <HI>Askams</HI> Schoolema∣ster. Lib. 2. p. 33.</NOTE> and knowledge of diuers
Tongues, that verie fewe of the rarest wits in the Vni∣uersities
could any way reach vnto her. And this see∣meth
euidently to haue bene the chiefe meanes; like
as he prooueth at large, by the authoritie of many great
learned, this way of translating, to be either the onely,
or at least the chiefe, readie, and sure meanes to attaine
speedily to any tongue.</P>
<P>And that I may adde but one other testimonie of a
rare and knowne experience in this kind.<NOTE PLACE="marg">A late known and worthie experience in a young No∣ble-man of rare hope.</NOTE> At the Com∣mencement
of that right noble, and memorable Gen∣tleman,
Sir <HI>Iohn Harington,</HI> (who now rests and reignes
with the Lord) hauing speech with Maister <HI>Touey,</HI> who
had bene a Schoolmaister, equall (as he was indged) to
most of the chiefe in that kind; but was then wholly em∣ployed
for the attendance and tuition of that young
Noble-man (with whom he also liues now in heauen,)
I desired to know this of him: that whereas I had writ
vnto him formerly, to haue taken some paines, in setting
<PB N="44" REF="26"/>
downe the shortest and best way of teaching, according
to his experience; and now there was a rare fame, that
God had giuen an extraordinarie blessing to his ende∣uours
with that young Noble-man, so that he did of a
sodaine go farre beyond most others of his time, (aboue
all former expectation:) that he would vouchsafe to
impart vnto me, in a word or two, what were the prin∣cipall
meanes he had vsed thereto. He acknowled∣ging
thankfully, that he had indeed seene much experi∣ence
of Gods mercie therein, told mee, that this was
the principall and summe of his course: That he had
bene enforced to begin againe, euen from the verie Ac∣cidence,
causing him to get the perfect vnderstanding
of the Rules, for the meaning and vse, though he could
not the words in so short a time; and after that, he had
caused him to practise continual translating into Latine,
after this manner. That he himselfe had chosen easie
places of <HI>Tully,</HI> and other familiar Authors, which the
Gentleman knew not, and caused him to turne them in∣to
Latine, and after brought him to the Author, to com∣pare
that which he had written, to the same, iust accor∣ding
to this last manner mentioned out of Maister <HI>As∣kam.</HI>
After, rounding me in the eare, he said; But shall
I tell you, <HI>It was by Prayer,</HI> quoth he. Hereupon, after
my returne, I set my selfe to put all these in practise, yet
more seriously then formerly I had done. But for this
kinde of translating, finding the toyle and impossibilitie
of it, first to translate peeces fit for euerie Forme, and
after to examine euerie ones exercise, how he had tran∣slated,
and to correct them; I wholly bent my selfe to
trie how this might be done, thorow the seuerall lower
Formes, that they might haue most practise of it.</P>
<P>Thus trying sundrie waies, which were ouer-long to
<PB N="45" REF="26"/>
recite, and amongst others, hauing seene in a chiefe
Schoole in <HI>London,</HI> good vse of verball translations; a∣mongst
some other things, I began to thinke, that by
the meanes of translations of the first Authors which
Scholars learne, this translating might be practised in
each lower Forme continually. But there were yet two
maine difficulties, which had formerly hindred me from
any such vse of them. First, that our vsuall translations
did direct the young Scholars vncertainly, and some∣times
amisse, being oft rather to expresse the sense, then
the words in anie right order of Grammar; and that
the learners must go by memorie, and as it were by rote,
more then by anie certaintie of Rule, vnlesse they were
of better iudgement. And secondly, that for this and
other inconueniences, translations were generally in
disgrace in Schooles. Therefore, this then I thought
necessarie to be my first labour, to finde out some cer∣taine
rule to follow, according to which to frame these
translations, and which might be the guide of all.</P>
<P>And herein I,<NOTE PLACE="marg">To whom the finding out of the rule, and of translations thereby is acknowled∣ged.</NOTE> vnder Iesus Christ, acknowledge my
selfe be holden for the rule of construing and translating,
in the beginning of my Schoole labours, now aboue
30. yeares ago, first to Maister <HI>Crusius:</HI> since to the reue∣rend
and ancient Schoole-maister, Maister <HI>Leech.</HI> Third∣ly,
after them to that painefull, Maister <HI>Coote,</HI> of <HI>Hunsden</HI>
in <HI>Essex,</HI> now with the Lord. And fourthly, to that lear∣ned
<HI>Go<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>leuius,</HI> and to some other of my acquaintance,
who had likewise taken paines in this rule, which they
willingly imparted vnto me.</P>
<P>And so from that time vntil this day,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Labour to find out the rule▪ and to frame the translations accordingly.</NOTE> I haue still bene
labouring to find out the rule more exactly, &amp; to frame
the translations according to the same. Secondly, this
hath bene my next studie, to seeke out the right vses and
<PB N="38" REF="27"/>
benefits of these translations,<NOTE PLACE="marg">And also the right vses &amp; benefits of them.</NOTE> and so in all things to set
them downe, as they might be a certaine direction, wher∣by
most easily and surely to reape the fruite of them.
Lastly I haue trauelled herein specially to haue full triall
&amp; assurance in euerie thing,<NOTE PLACE="marg">And finally, to haue <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ull assurance of euery thing.</NOTE> that as I had gathered these
amongst other experiments, for the vse of all schooles, so
vpon certaine proofe by my selfe, and other of better
iudgement, I might at length commend them to all lear∣ners,
and so helpe to bring in that excellent vse of them
(which <HI>Maister Askam</HI> aduised) euen into the Schooles,
in which they had bene so formerly distasted, as that it
was thought a Paradox, but to name the vse of transla∣tions
i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> them.</P>
<P>Now vpon this rule,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Vpon what things all the chiefe bene∣fits of these translations depend.</NOTE> and the expressing euerie thing
in the translations, both in proprietie, and also according
to the sence and meaning of the author, with varietie of
other English phrases, and supplying what is wanting,
to make vp the construction, with the other things ob∣serued
therein, especially vpon the rule, depend all the
chiefe benefits, for a certaine <HI>Analysis</HI> and <HI>Genesis;</HI> both
for construing, parsing, making and tying Latin surely,
and sundrie of the rest,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Chap. 8.</NOTE> as is shewed at large in the eight
Chapter of the Grammar Schoole.</P>
<P>By the right practise of these translations, so framed,
as I am fully assured,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Certaine be∣nefits of these translations rightly vsed.</NOTE> by long experience, through the
Lords mercie and goodnesse, an increase will be found
in learning, farre more then can be well conceiued, be∣fore
due triall made, and that with much lesse trouble to
the Maister then otherwise: and with farre more delight,
certaintie, ease, and cheerfull emulation to the scholar.
I haue therefore thought it my dutie, after my vnfallible
experience of them, rightly vsed, so as I haue plainely
set downe the maner in this second edition of my Gram∣mar
<PB N="39" REF="27"/>
Schoole, and after my so long and painfull trauell,
to find out the Rule most certainly, with the best, and
most profitable vses thereof, to commend them more
confidently vnto all our Schooles, and to all desirous to
recouer speedily the knowledge of their Latin tongue,
or to increase therein. In a certaine affiance, that all who
shall vse them aright, shall see a rich blessing, without in∣conuenience:
yet lest in anie thing I should be thought
too peremptorie, I intreate the learned first to make
proofe, then to iudge hereof according as they find.</P>
<P>For anie further apologie therefore for my bold at∣tempt,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Further Apo∣logie need∣lesse, except, 1. The Au∣thors desire to do all this good.</NOTE>
in these endeuours, I trust that some few of the
reasons lightly touched before, may be defence suffi∣cient.
And first my vnfained studie to do all this good to
all sorts, without the least iniurie to anie one, so farre
forth as I shall know it, or without inuerting anie ap∣proued
course. And that howsoeuer I haue bene the vn∣fittest
of manie of my brethren, to enter vpon so hard a
taske, yet the weaker, the more meete haue I bene, to
haue a compassionate feeling of the wants of others; and
more like to applie my selfe to the capacitie of the mea∣nest
and most ignorant: whereas the great learned and
acute do oft times thinke, that what they themselues vn∣derstand,
all others should presently conceiue, though
the most of the simple comprehend litle or nothing of it
fully, as they should.</P>
<P>Secondly,<NOTE PLACE="marg">2. The ha∣uing all these experiments gathered to our hands.</NOTE> for that in these my poore labours, euerie
one may haue the wearie trauels, and comfortable expe∣riments,
of manie learned thus gathered into one, and
brought therby vnto his hands without labor or charge,
which otherwise might haue cost them manie miles tra∣uelling,
and some yeares triall, as well as my selfe, and
yet they might haue failed of manie things, which here
<PB N="48" REF="28"/>
they may find, and more hereafter, as God shall vouch∣safe
moe supplies vnto it.</P>
<P>Thirdly,<NOTE PLACE="marg">3. Assurance of each mans affection, to haue his child so brought vp as is here de∣sired.</NOTE> because there is no man, hauing the nature
of a wise father, who would not haue his child to haue
some learning, howsoeuer he purpose to employ him
afterward, and who to that end would not haue him so
instructed, as whereby to get the best learning, in the
shortest time, and with the least seueritie, or who will
not giue almost double, if he may be assured to haue his
child so trained vp.</P>
<P>Fourthly,<NOTE PLACE="marg">4. For the te∣stimonie of his cō<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cience to be vpright &amp; faithfull <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> all his worke.</NOTE> for that I haue him who searcheth &amp; trieth
the hearts, and whose good hand hath bene with me in
goodnesse, in all this worke, to beare witnesse vnto my
conscience, that I haue not either in this, or anie other
my trauels, aimed at vaine praise or commendation (for
that our holy God would turne into shame) or at anie
other sinister end; but that I haue striuen with all my
heart, so farre as in my weaknesse I haue bene able, to
aime at those verie ends alone, which our blessed Saui∣our
hath taught me, in that diuine patterne of heauenly
prayer, which hath bene in all my labours my principall
direction. And namely, to manifest my dutie &amp; thank∣fulnesse
to my heauenly father, like as for all other his
mercies chiefly in heauenly things in Christ, and for in∣numerable
temporall fauors, in his fatherly prouidence,
protection and direction vouchsafed vnto me;<NOTE PLACE="marg">1. Anno 1588</NOTE> so more
especially for those three great deliuerances (to be had
in euerlasting remembrance) not onely of our Church
and nation,<NOTE PLACE="marg">2. The death of Queene E∣lizabeth, and peaceable bringing in our Soue∣raigne.</NOTE> &amp; of all other the Churches of Christ with
them, but euen of my selfe particularly in euerie one of
them. And this I haue desired to do, by seeking first to
honour him,<NOTE PLACE="marg">3. Powder <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>reason.</NOTE> and secondly to aduance and enlarge his
kingdome, and to these ends searching to know and ac∣complish
<PB N="41" REF="28"/>
all his holy will, tending thereunto, and so all
the other subordinate ends, as he hath directed me. Thus
haue I endeuoured to rely vpon that his gracious pro∣mise,
that thus seeking first the kingdome of God, and
his righteousnesse, all these other things should be ad∣ded
vnto me, (as an ouer-measure) so farre as should be
good. And herein indeed I haue felt no breach of pro∣mise
from his Maiestie, but found him faithfully and
true; yea, exceeding bountifull, aboue all that I could
conceiue, in all things wherein his goodnesse hath ena∣bled
me so to seeke him. Vpon all these grounds I can
nothing doubt, but through the mercie of the Lord, this
labour being intended to these verie ends, and prooued
to be answerable thereunto, without inconueniences in
the right vse of it, as my assured confidence is; I cannot
but fully hope, that it will in due time be most welcome,
and acceptable to all, that euer shal make triall by them∣selues
or others.</P>
<P>Lastly,<NOTE PLACE="marg">5. For willing sub<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ission of al<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> things to the publike cen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ure.</NOTE> for that I willingly submit it, with all my la∣bours,
to the louing censure of all the learned, who tru∣ly
loue Christs Gospell, being readie to be taught of the
meanest, who shall in anie thing shew me my error, or
giue me clearer light. And though the defects should
still be verie many (as in so difficult a worke it is no great
maruell;) yet sith I am most desirous to be continually
reforming, euerie ingenuous well-willer vnto good lear∣ning,
will (I trust) louingly pardon them, and thankful∣ly
accept of that which God of his goodnesse hath gran∣ted.
Thus I put forth each first Copie of translations
or others,<NOTE PLACE="marg">And desire to be still lear∣ning of all.</NOTE> as not set forth, but to go more generally to
all my louing friends, and well-vvishers to this worke, to
craue of them further helpe, as I sayd before.</P>
<P>To this end, I do still humbly request, euerie true fa∣uourer
<PB N="42" REF="29"/>
of good learning, to lay to his hand, that so I
may be continually learning, amending, and perfecting,
so long as the Lord shall lengthen my daies.</P>
<P>If in anie thing,<NOTE PLACE="marg">The cause of the confi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nt reioycing in it.</NOTE> I haue or shall seeme to reioice ouer∣much,
yet consider first, that in my generall work, in my
Grammar-Schoole, I haue thought the forme of a Dia∣logue
most fit; wherein more libertie is granted to incite
and incourage others. Secondly, that I haue not, nor
will speake anie more, then either what I haue seene ex∣perience
of, or whereof vpon good grounds, I am fully
assured, and which I take my selfe bound to relate, onely
to the praise of our God, &amp; the good of others, to make
all others partakers of the comforts, which to that end
he hath vouchsafed vnto me, following so neare as I can,
that direction mentioned before, in the Preface before
our common Grammar. Thirdly remember that report
of <HI>Maister Askam,</HI> cōcerning <HI>Maister Iohn Whitney,</HI> farre
greater then all mine are together: and then I doubt not
(these things being rightly weighed) but all who are
wise hearted, will easily beare with me, in my confident
reioycing, trusting moreouer that God will verifie all
things, to euerie one who shall duly make triall. And in
this affiance, and testimonie of my conscience, before
his sacred Maiestie, I wholly relie my selfe.</P>
<P>Therefore,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Exhortation &amp; encourage∣ment to the weaker tea∣chers.</NOTE> before I conclude, giue me leaue a lit∣tle
to turne my speech to you, (my deare fellow la∣bourers,)
and namely to all you of the weaker sort, for
whom I haue and do still chiefly trauell, whose hearts
are set as mine to do all the good you can, in your se∣uerall
places, all your dayes. To you all I wish, that as
we haue bene sometimes companions, in fruitlesse toile,
and vexation; so we may be now in reioycing at, and
admiring the new fruites of our labours. What a griefe
<PB N="43" REF="29"/>
may this iustly be vnto vs,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Griefe to all honest hear∣ted maisters, for com∣plaints and murmurings against thē.</NOTE> when one shall come, and crie
out of vs, to our faces: My sonne hath bene vnder you
six or seuen yeares, and yet is not able so much as to
reade English well; much lesse to construe or vnderstand
a peece of Latin, or to write true Latin, or to speake
in Latin in any tolerable sort,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Complaints of parents for the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> chil∣dren not pro∣fiting.</NOTE> which he might haue
bene well able to haue performed, if that you had taken
that course and those good paines with him which you
might haue done; for in such a schoole others much
yonger then mine are able to do it. Another shall com∣plaine;
My sonne comes on neuer a whit in his writing.
Besides that his hand is such,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Murmurings of Townes for charges ill bestowed and children spoiled.</NOTE> that it can hardly be read;
he also writes so false English, that he is neither fit for
trade, nor any employment wherein to vse his pen.
When all in a towne generally, shall murmure a∣gainst
vs, in this or the like manner, that their children
do no good vnder vs, but lose their time, and spend
their friends mony, being brought vp idlely, made fit
for nothing, and therefore what should a schoole do a∣mongst
them? That it were much better to turne the
maintenance giuen to the schoole, to beare the charges
of the towne for other duties and seruices, then so vn∣profitably
to employ it.</P>
<P>Moreouer how must this needs trouble vs,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Some to crie out against our seueritie.</NOTE> when ma∣nie
shall crie out of our seueritie: some shall wish, I
would my child had neuer knowne him. If he had not
dealt so cruelly with my child, he had bene a scholar,
wheras now he is vndone. Or when our scholars coming
to mans estate, shall curse vs, for that by our blowes
they were made dunses or deafe (though this oftentimes
vniustly) or to hate all learning.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Scholars comming to mans estate to bewaile losse of their time.</NOTE> Or shall generally be∣waile
the losse of their time vnder vs, complaining as the
vsuall maner is, My Maister neuer taught me anie vnder∣standing,
<PB N="44" REF="30"/>
or right vse of good learning, that though I
was with sundrie, yet I was neuer the better. I got more
sence, and saw more light for the vse and excellency
of learning, and also felt more sweetnesse therein, in one
halfe yeare in the end, with one who directed me in a
better order, then in all my time, with all others. The
rest deceiued my parents, and were my vndoing. Or
when they shall thus complaine: Our Maister had not
anie care of our gouernment and manners.<NOTE PLACE="marg">That they were not taught any religiou.</NOTE> He neuer
taught vs the feare of the Lord, nor made the least con∣science
to plant anie Religion or grace in vs.</P>
<P>Finally,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Terrour for for lacke of growth of Gods religion.</NOTE> what a terrour shall this be vnto vs, and
what a wounding to our consciences, when we shall but
thinke, how the Lord and all good men, may most iust∣ly
lay this vnto our charge, that the cause hath bene
chiefely in vs, that Gods religion, hath not thriuen any
better in our Land, in so long a time; but that Popery,
ignorance, Atheisme, and all irreligiousnesse, haue
farre more growne vp in many places? If we had bene
as carefull to season our youth, in the truth of Christ,
and to settle them in the grounds of his holy religion,
truly professed amongst vs, to their saluation, as the Po∣pish
schoolemaisters are to corrupt them with Idolatry,
and superstition, vnto perdition, the knowledge and
loue of Gods true worship, and pietie, had flourished
amongst vs, euery where long ago, all Popery and A∣theisme
rooted out. And what answer can we thinke to
make to God, for his religion, and people, for so many
who haue bene lost, chiefly through our lacke of care?
How should these things touch euery one of vs, euen
to the very hearts, and cause vs to bethinke our selues
at length, of this our weighty function, to the end to
take away all this reproch, and to begin to recouer the
<PB N="45" REF="30"/>
credit of our worthy profession.</P>
<P>You know well,<NOTE PLACE="marg">The charge committed to vs.</NOTE> that we are they to whose charge
that rich treasure, both of Church and Cōmon wealth
is committed in trust, (as was said) and the hope of a
more happy age hereafter yet to come. We are they
who helpe either to make or marre all; for that all the
flower of our Nation, and those who become the lea∣ders
of all the rest, are committed to our education, and
instruction: that if we bring them vp aright, there is great
hope, that they shall prooue goodly lights, and marks
to all the rest of the Land, especially, to the townes and
countries where they are; and cleane contrarily, most
wofull ensamples (as are euery where to be seene) if
they be spoiled through vs, or for lacke of our better
care. So that we must needs do the greatest good or
the greatest euill. As we are before them, so we may ex∣pect,
that they shall prooue for the most part after vs.
We are therefore the men, vpon whom the flourishing
of this our Canaan, doth very much depend. We can∣not
then but know, that as our worke aud charge are
so weighty, and in course of education next vnto the
worke and charge of the holy Ministery, which we
also are to helpe to furnish: so our account must be ac∣cording
to that which our God hath trusted vs withall,
and our reward answerable; dreadfull, if we haue bene
negligent; glorious, if we haue bene faithfull.</P>
<P>We cannot be ignorant, how our enemies the <HI>Iesuits,</HI>
not onely in their Semina<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ies, but also in their lesser
schooles, do bend their wits, to go beyond vs in this ve∣rie
kind. Giue me leaue to put you in mind of that which
was written vnto me, from an ancient acquaintance in
the Vniuersitie, now sundrie yeares ago, and which I do
gladly acknowledge, to the praise of God, that it hath
<PB N="46" REF="31"/>
from the first relation put more life vnto me in this busi∣nesse.
The summe of it was this.</P>
<P>The Iesuites,<NOTE PLACE="marg">The combi∣nations of the Iesuites ought to pro∣uoke vs. October, 28. 1608.</NOTE> the Popish schoolemaisters beyond the seas,
do combine themselues together, and all, or at least manie
schooles do reade the same bookes at one time, and the same
places, and do change euery quarter, and set vpon the schoole
dores, the Authors, place, lectures, exercises, euerie quarter,
newly printed, and for this they haue great suite made vnto
them by the Printers. This haue I lately learned of certaine
whom I vsed beyond the seas to this end. <HI>Thus farre my lo∣uing
friend. Whether this report was true in each parti∣cular,
I cannot certainly affirme, yet for the generall, we
all who vnderstand anie thing, do know that it is most
certaine.</HI></P>
<P>Now who are these who thus combine? are they not
the principall plotters of the ruine of all the Churches of
Christ, and of Common-wealths, as they are cried out
of, euen in the Popish countries themselues; the arch e∣nemies
of Christ and his Gospell, and the chiefe vphol∣ders
of the throne of the Beast, to make him king of
kings, and Lord of Lords. And what is their purpose in
seeking out the most excellent courses of getting most
speedily all good learning as they would pretend? Sure∣ly
their purpose is nothing else, as all the world may
plainely see, but by that their learning to ou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>-counte∣nance
the heauēly learning, the sacred truth of that euer∣lasting
Gospell, and all the learned, who professe Christ
Iesus throughout the earth: to gaine all the flowre of the
Nobility, and Gentrie, yea of all the youth in all places
where they come, to bewitch all with an opinion of
their learning, the more easily when their time serues to
cut the throats of all, who truly and sincerely professe
Christs Gospell, and to possesse their places. Yea if it
<PB N="47" REF="31"/>
were in their power, or possible, to destroy all the
Churches of Christ, to extinguish vtterly all true lear∣ning,
to bring in againe all their old learning, as (they
call it) their palpable delusions, and abhominable I∣dolatry.<NOTE PLACE="marg">What our state was al∣most by them.</NOTE>
We all saw, how nea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e we were to be consu∣med
by their fornace. We with our royall King, our
Prince, our Nobles, and Rulers, the Church of Christ,
with the glory thereof. Now our God hauing so mira∣culously
plucked vs out, and we all being in a speciall
manner (next vnto our Gracious Soueraigne, and his
royall Progeny, together with these our Nobles and
Rulers, the holy ministery and noted professors) desig∣ned
in their hearts, as flesh for their caldron; let vs shew
our selues thankfull, euery one in our places and callings:
and in token of our thankfulnesse,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Our miracu∣lous preser∣uations, and their deadly malice, ought to put new life into eue∣ry one of vs.</NOTE> to our most merci∣full
and blessed God (whose name is for this aboue all
other outward deliuerances, to be extolled for euer∣more;)
first for our liues, and then for our Religion the
life of our liues; let vs all be prouoked to bend our stu∣dies,
and euen to spend and end our liues, for our Christ,
and for our dread Soueraigne, vnder him. By whose
hand <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e so (euen miraculously) deliuered vs, the second
time, like as formerly he had in a most wonderfull
manner, at his first comming to the Regall Crowne,
and his entring in amongst vs; whereby all their long
hopes, and bloudie designes against vs were dashed in
a moment, and that heauenly light continued to vs, and
to our posteritie (I trust till Christ shall come) which
they certainly accounted at both those times, to haue
put out for euer.</P>
<P>Let vs now contrariwise stirre vp our selues, more
then euer heretofore, that the light of all good know∣ledge
may breake forth, and be as the morning bright∣nesse
<PB N="48" REF="32"/>
before the Sunne rising, to prepare the way to that
glorious appearing, and kingdome, when we with all
the children of the light shall shine eternally in the hea∣uens:
and when all those who haue sought deuices to
bring in againe darknesse vpon all, or but to hinder the
glorious light of truth, shall without their vnfained re∣pentance
liue perpetually in their place of vtter dark∣nesse.<NOTE PLACE="marg">We haue no cause to fea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e our bloud-thirstie aduer∣saries, if we will but sticke vnto our Christ.</NOTE>
Oh that these enemies could thinke of this, and
be warned in time, to turne their thoughts another way,
euen for the King of Kings, that they might haue bold∣nesse
at his appearing. But to leaue them, praying for
them, that so many of them as belong to Gods eternall
election, may haue their eyes open to see their miserie,
and be conuerted and saued; and to returne to our
selues. There is no cause at all for vs, why we should
feare or doubt of a glorious triumph and crowne here∣by;
if that we will but cheerfully ioyne hearts and hands;
prouoked by the combinations of these our bloud-thirtie
aduersaries, and all sticke close vnto our Lord and
Sauiour, our Captaine and teacher. With them is but
an arme of flesh, the spirit of man, of Sathan, and Anti∣christ:<NOTE PLACE="marg">Our confi∣dence in our Captaine.</NOTE>
but with vs our Christ, commanding and assu∣ring
vs. He who is King of Kings and Lord of Lo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ds.
With vs is he who must reigne, vntill he haue vtterly
ouerthrowne,<NOTE PLACE="marg">2. Thes. 2. 4.</NOTE> and abolished that man of sinne, (though
now exalting himselfe aboue all that is called God, or
worshipped) and all those his souldiers with him. He
will be with vs, and guide vs, he will direct and blesse vs.
He can make the meanest of his to do more seruice
for the vphoding and furthering of his owne king∣dome,<NOTE PLACE="marg">The power of our Christ, with vs, &amp; cer∣tainety of victorie of his side.</NOTE>
which must come with power and glory, and
endure for euer; then all their combinations shall do to
the contrary. And much more when we shall louingly
<PB N="49" REF="32"/>
and faithfully, as of one heart and soule, vnite all our for∣ces,
and labours in one, to this so happy and blessed a
worke, wherein we are sure to preuaile, if we will but
go on manfully, and stand fast to our Captaine, and
great Commander. The victorie is his, he hath got∣ten
it already;<NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></NOTE> he rideth on the white horse, conquering
till he haue accomplished all his worke.</P>
<P>If we of the weaker so it can for the presen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></NOTE> but at∣taine
neare vnto those things mentioned in the Con∣tents
of the Grammar Schoole, <HI>viz.</HI> what may be done
for sp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>edy &amp; certaine attaining to learning in schooles,
which are also hereunto adioyned; our labour shalbe
most pleasing to our God, profitable to all, sweete and
comfortable to our owne hearts. Euen we shall helpe
to restore learning againe to her ancient reputation and
honour, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ee our selues from all reproch, being able
to liue with credit in our places. And that we may come
vnto them all,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Assurance that we may come vnto them.</NOTE> make ye no doubt. My selfe and many
others, haue seene so much experience, in as weake
meanes, as most of vs haue, as whereby to assure vs,
that by our constant labour and diligence, but in the
courses set downe in the Grammar-schoole, we shall
through the helpe of our good God finde them in such
sort, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></P>
<P>Let vs therefore double our diligence,<NOTE PLACE="marg">An <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> to double <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> diligence</NOTE> and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
we have made triall, in these, or in better, item God
haue or shall vouchsa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e them vnto vs. You see how
much through his mercifull goodnesse I haue <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
herein (though the vnablest of very <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>) and
how farre the worke is proceeded in; to the end hereby
to prouoke and encourage you. You who haue not
better, proue these, which God hereby offereth vnto
<PB N="50" REF="33"/>
you; or at least so many of them, as you shall most like
of, and as your leisure and opportunitie well serue; yet
not ouerloading your selues or your children. That we
may approue, what is best, reforme what is amisse, and
draw euery thing still more shortly, euer receiuing bet∣ter,
as his goodnesse shall affoord them. And so in time
by our ioynt consent, we may confirme all the surest,
both vnto our selues, and to all other whosoeuer shall
succeed. You that haue more excellent in any kinde,
communicate them with vs, as we haue presumed here∣in,
in duty to tender thus much vnto you.</P>
<P>But let none of vs be discouraged though we do not
find our desires at the first;<NOTE PLACE="marg">None to be discouraged, if he see not his desire at the first.</NOTE> set to it cheerfully, and in due
time our eyes shall behold it.</P>
<P>Thus also our brethren, who are of the most excel∣lent
gifts, I meane the Maisters of all the principall
schooles of our nation, and all other sound hearted
fauourers of good learning, seeing our louing con∣tention,
shalbe enforced to ioyne hearts, and hands,
and to affoord vs likewise their vttermost helpe and
countenance; which, in the name of our Lord Iesus
Christ, and by our appearing before him, as they tender
his glory, the good of our Church &amp; their natiue coun∣trey,
I againe humbly intreat at their hands: especially
their directions for the best performance of these chie∣fest
and most necessarie excercises mentioned, and what∣soeuer
else they find vs too short in, for the full adorning
of the Grammar Schoole. By this means, shall the
worke of God prosper in our hands, going forward
happily, that we shall vndoubtedly find the desires of
our s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>les, and wherein the excellency of the speedy at∣taining
to all good learning doth consist, to the endlesse
glory of our most holy and onely wise God, the lasting
<PB N="51" REF="33"/>
honour of our Nation, &amp; of the Church of Christ, the
safe preseruation of our liues and religion, with the hap∣pinesse
of posteritie, euen to match &amp; go beyond our ad∣uersaries.
Thus finally all true learning shall be had in
lasting honour, and all vnfained fauourers and furthe∣rers
of the same, shall triumph eternally. Which that it
may, let me onely adjoyne that worthy incourage∣ment,
wherewith <HI>Christophorus Hegendorphinus</HI> inci∣ted
one of his scholars, now many yeares ago.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Christoph. Hegendor∣phinus L. E. discipulo suo,</NOTE></P>
<P><HI>Tu verò in liter as &amp; Graecas &amp; Latinas, vt soles gna∣uiter
incumbe. Nec te deterreat, quod in hoc seculo, tam
literae quam literati contemptui sint; redibit, crede mihi,
redibit suus honor, &amp; literis &amp; literatis: nam omnium re∣rum
vicissitudo est.</HI> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, <HI>inquit Sophocles.</HI> But applie you your
selfe cheerfully vnto Greeke and Latin studies, as you
are wont. Neither let this terrifie you, that in this age,
as well learning as learned men are in such contempt.
There will returne (beleeue me) there will returne, their
due honour, both to learning and to learned men: for
there is an intercourse of all things. For vnto them that
shall liue in the last age, pleasant things shall be made
bitter, and yet pleasant and beloued afterwards againe,
as saith <HI>Sophocles</HI> that ancient Greeke Poet.</P>
<P>Thus farre <HI>Hegendorphinus,</HI> as foretelling (truly I trust)
the glorie of this last succeeding age, whereto let all
heartie friends of good learning euer say, Amen.</P>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<PB N="52" REF="34"/>
<HEAD>CONTENTS IN GE∣NERALL
OF SVCH THINGS AS
may (by Gods blessing) be easily effected in
our ordinarie Grammar schooles▪</HEAD>
<P>1. TO teach schol<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rs how to be able to reade well, and
write true or orthographie in a short time.</P>
<P>2. To make them ready, in all points of their Accidence
and Grammar, to answer anie necessarie question therein.</P>
<P>3. To <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> without booke all the vsuall and necessarie
Rules, to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> their Grammar rules; to giue the meaning,
vse, and order of the rules, to shew the examples, and to ap∣ply
them: which being well performed, will make all other
learning easie and pleasant.</P>
<P>4. In the seuerall <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> and Authors to construe truly,
and in proprietie of wor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s and sense, and also in pure phrase;
to parse of themselues, and to giue a right reason of euerie
word, why it must be so and not otherwise; and to deliuer
the English of the Lectures perfectly out of the Latine.</P>
<P>5. Out of an English Grammaticall translation of their
Authors, to make and to construe anie part of the Latine
which they haue learned, or do presently learne; to proue
that it must be so, and so to reade the Latine out of the En∣glish,
first in the plaine Grammaticall order; after as the
wo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ds are placed in the Author, or in other good composition.
Also to p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rse in Latine, looking onely vpon the translation;
and to all their Poets which they so learne: to do all this with∣out
booke, which is farre the surest, viz. to repeate, construe,
and parse with their booke vnder their arme.</P>
<P><PB N="53" REF="34"/>
6. To take their Lectures of themselues, except in the
verie lowest Formes, and first entrers into construction; or
to do it with verie little helpe, in some more difficult things.</P>
<P>7. To enter surely in making Latine, without danger of
making false Latine, or vsing anie barbarous phrase.</P>
<P>8. To <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> true Latine, and pure <HI>Tullies</HI> phrase, and to
proue it to be true and pure.</P>
<P>9. To <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, imitating <HI>Tully</HI> and the best A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣thors
in that kind, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and pithie, in pure Latine, and fa∣miliar.</P>
<P>10. To translate into English, according to proprietie
both of words and sense▪ and out of the English to reade
the Latine againe, to proue it, and giue a reason of euerie
thing.</P>
<P>11. To take a peece of <HI>Tully,</HI> or of anie other familiar ea∣sie
Authour, Grammatically translated, and in proprietie of
words, and to turne or reade the same, out of the Translati∣on
into good Latine, and verie neere vnto the words of the
Author; so as in most, you shall hardly discerne, whether it
be the Authors Latine or the Scholars.</P>
<P>12. To correct their faults of themsel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es, when they are
but noted out vnto them, or a question is asked of them.</P>
<P>13. To be able in each Forme (at anie time whensoeuer
they shall be apposed of a sodaine, in any part of their Au∣thors,
which they haue lately learned) to construe, parse,
reade into English, and in those Authors, whereof they
haue translations; forth of the translation, to construe and
to reade into the Latine of their Author. First into the na∣turall
order, then into the order of the Author, or neare vn∣to
it, and in their Poëts to do all this without booke, as was
sayd before, and so to giue an account, at each quarters <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd,
what they haue learned in that quarter; so from quarter to
quarter to do the like.</P>
<P><PB N="54" REF="35"/>
14. In <HI>Virgil, Horace,</HI> and other the chiefe and most
approued Schoole Authors in Poëtrie and Prose, to resolue
any peece, for all these points of learning, and to do it in
good Latine:
<LIST>
<HEAD>In</HEAD>
<ITEM>Construing, to giue propriety of words and sense, and
also to expound in good phrase.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Scanning the Verses, and giuing a reason thereof.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Shewing the difficulties of Grammar.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Obseruing the Elegances of Rhetoricke in Tropes
and Figures.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Noting Phrases and Epithets, with other princi∣pall
obseruations.</ITEM>
</LIST></P>
<P>15. So to reade ouer so much of the chiefe Latine Poëts,
as <HI>Virgil, Horace,</HI> &amp;c. and of other the best Authors, as
shall be thought necessary, by that time, that by reason of
their yeares they be in any measure thought fit, for their dis∣cretion,
to go vnto the Vniuersity; and to be able to go tho∣rough
the rest of themselues, by ordinary helpes.</P>
<P>16. In Greeke to take their Lectures of themselues, to
construe perfectly, and parse as in the Latine; to reade the
Greeke backe againe, out of a translation, Latine, or English;
also to construe, parse, and to prooue it out of the same.</P>
<P>17. In the Hebrew to be able to construe perfectly, and to
resolue so farre as is necessary for the Grammar-schoole; and
to reade the Hebrew also out of the translation; which pra∣ctise
of daily reading somewhat out of the translations into
the Originals, must needs make them, both very cunning in
the Tongues, and also perfect in the Texts of the Originals
themselues, if it be obserued constantly; like as it is in the
daily reading Latine out of the translation.</P>
<P>18. To answer most of the difficulties in all classicall
Schoole-Authors; as in <HI>Terence, Virgil, Horace, Persius,
Iuvenal.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="55" REF="35"/>
19. To oppose scholar-like in Latine of any Grammar que∣stion
necessary, in a good forme of words; both what may be
objected against <HI>Lillies</HI> rules, and how to defend them.</P>
<P>20. To write Theames full of good matter, in pure La∣tin
and with iudgement, and how to inuent matter of them∣selues.</P>
<P>21. To enter to make a verse with delight, without any
bodging at all; and to furnish with copie of Poëticall phrase,
out of the best Poëts.</P>
<P>22. So to imitate and expresse <HI>Ouid</HI> or <HI>Virgil,</HI> as you
shall hardly discerne, vnlesse you know the places, whether
the verses be the Authors or the Scholars: and to write
verses ex tempore of any ordinarie theame.</P>
<P>23. To translate forth of English or Latin into Greeke.
Also to write theames or verses in Greeke.</P>
<P>24. To pronounce naturally and sweetly, without vaine
affectation; and to begin to do it from the lowest fourmes.</P>
<P>25. To make right vse of the matter of their Authors,
besides the Latin, euen from the first beginners: as of <HI>Sen∣tentiae,</HI>
and <HI>Confabulatiunculae Pueriles, Cato, Aesops
fables, Tullies <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pistles, Ouids Metamorphosis,</HI> and so on
to the highest. To helpe to furnish them with varietie of the
best morall matter, and with vnderstanding, wisdome, and
precepts of vertue, as they grow; and withall, to imprint
the Latin so in their minds therby, as hardly to be forgottē.</P>
<P>26. To answer concerning the matter contained in
their Lectures, in the Latin of their Authors, from the
lowest fourmes and so vpward.</P>
<P>27. To construe anie ordinarie Author ex tempore.</P>
<P>28. To come to that facilitie and ripenesse, as not onely
to translate leisurely and with some meditation, both into
English and Latin, as before in the sections 10. and 11. but
more also, to reade anie easie Author forth of Latin into
<PB N="54" REF="36"/>
English, and out of English to reade it into Latin againe, as
<HI>Corderius, Terence, Tullies Offices,</HI> &amp;c. To do this in
Authors and places which they are not acquainted with, and
almost as fast as they are able, to reade the Author alone.</P>
<P>29. To write fa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re, in Secretarie, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, Gre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke, He∣brue;
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>.</P>
<P>30. To <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aue all the principall <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> La∣tin,
Greek and Hebrue, with the etymologies both Latin and
Greek: <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
worthie helpes and meanes to be had in the Vniuersities.</P>
<P>31. To be acquainted with the grounds of Religion, and
to haue the summe, and all the chiefe Histories of the Bible.
To take all the substance of the Sermons, if they be plainly
and orderly deliuered: and to set them downe afterwards in
a good Latin style, or to reade them extempore into Latin out
of the English. To conceiue and answer the seuerall points of
the Sermons, and how to make a briefe repetition of the
whole Sermon without booke.</P>
<P>32. To be set in the high way to attaine to the puritie and
perfection of the Latine tongue by their further labour aud
practise in the Vniuersitie: hauing both the rules &amp; grounds
thereof, and also varietie of the best phrase meete and ne∣cessarie
for them.</P>
<P>33 To grow in our owne English tongue, according to
their ages, and growths in other learning: to vtter their
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> in the same, both in propriety, and purity; and so to
be fitted for diuinity, law, or what other calling or faculty
soeuer they shalbe after employed in.</P>
<P>34 Finally, thus to proceed together with the tongs; in
the vnderstanding and knowledge of the learning, or mat∣ter
contained in the same, to become alike expert, in all good
learning, meete for their yeares and studies; that so procee∣ding
<PB N="57" REF="36"/>
still, after they are gone from the Grammar Schooles,
they may become most exquisite in all kinds of good learning,
to which they shall be applied.</P>
<P>These things may be effected in good sort, through Gods
blessing, in the seuerall fourmes, as the scholars proceed, by
so manie in each fourme as are apt and industrious, onely by
the directions in the Grammar schoole constantly obserued.
If the Maisters being of any competent sufficiencie will take
meete paines: and the Scholars being set to schoole, so soone
as they shall be meete, be kept to learning daily, without
loitering, hauing bookes and other necessarie helpes and en∣couragements:
and by their par<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nts care caused to do their
exercises at home, and be euer kept in meete awe, and sub∣mission
to their Maisters. But out of these I will extract
onely those which I take most necessarie and profitable for
schooles (not to trouble with ouer manie) and set them
downe briefly in the Grammar Schoole. That so all scholars
of anie towardnesse and diligence, may be made good Gram∣marians
and euerie way fit for the Vniuersitie by fifteene
years of age, or at least by that time that they shall be meete
by discretion and gouernment, which is commonly sixteene
or seuenteene. And all this to be done with delight aud cer∣taintie,
both to Maisters and Scholars; with strife and con∣tention
amongest the Scholars themselues, without that v∣suall
terrour and crueltie, which hath bene practised in
manie plaees, and without so much as seueritie amongst
good natures.</P>
<P>How greatly all this must needs tend to the furtherance
of the publike good, euerie one may iudge; which it will d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
still, so much the more as the Lord vouchsafeth a further
supply, to the seuerall meanes and courses after set downe,
by adjoining daily moe helpes and experiments, especially of
the learned. Of whom my hope is stil, according to my earnest
<PB N="58" REF="37"/>
desire, that they will lend their helping hands, to the full
perfecting of so profitable a worke.</P>
<P>For the vndoubted certaintie hereof, and of each parti∣cular,
first reade and consider of the meanes aright, then
try according to the directions in their seuerall places in the
Grammar Schoole, and so giue sentence.</P>
<P>For mine owne selfe, I trust (God assisting) to be euer
able to make such plaine demonstration of euerie thing, as
to giue full satisfaction to any one indifferently affected, that
by labour and diligence all may be in good sort accomplished,
so farre as shall be requisite. Or wherein I shall be found too
short, I am resolued (God willing) neuer to giue ouer, du∣ring
life, vntill I shall therein likewise see the de∣sire
of my soule, vnto his glorie, and
the generall good of all.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<PB N="59" REF="37"/>
<HEAD>❧ Helps for attaining to those
things mentioned in the
Contents.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>Hese helps God hath prouided for our
Grammar-schooles, more then in former
times, or at least more then are common∣ly
knowne and vsed in them: whereof
experience teacheth, that there may be
excellent furtherance in a right vse of them, for all the
seuerall parts of good learning in Schooles, for obtai∣ning
the same more speedily, easily, surely &amp; profitably:
and namely for thus running through all our ordinary
classicall-schoole authors, and attaining to the best ex∣ercises
and faculties in Schooles, as any one shall haue
occasion to vse them.</P>
<P>First, for the more speedy and right reading of En∣glish,
and so leading the childe as by the hand to the
Grammar schoole, as a preparatiue thereto.</P>
<P><HI>The English-schoolemaister,</HI> of that honest and painfull
Maister <HI>Coote.</HI></P>
<P>There is also a little Briefe, of a sheet of paper named,
<HI>A Plaine Method for speedy learning to reade,</HI> by <HI>Iohn
Merest:</HI> of whose directions there might be very good
vse, if his Rules and style were amended by some Scho∣lar,
and brought to perfection.</P>
<P>Other directions and helps for teaching to reade, see
in the Grammar-schoole, chap. 3. For further growth
of young Scholars in our English tongue, to expresse
<PB N="60" REF="38"/>
their mindes in proprietie and puritie, for their procee∣ding
therein, as they proceede in Latine: and also for
them who would teach strangers our language, or
learne it. See after.</P>
<P>Secondly, for better learning the Accidence and first
grounds of Grammar (whereas children are vsually very
long in getting their Accidence, and oft, when they
haue done it, are little the better for it, especially for the
vnderstanding and right vse of it) to the end that the
learner may get it sooner &amp; more profitably: for a right
vnderstanding and vse thereof, and for answering any
necessary question belonging to it, and for better kee∣ping
all in memory, to be able thereby to proceed most
speedily, pleasantly and certainely in their construction,
is prouided the Booke called</P>
<P>The posing of the Parts. <HI>as also</HI></P>
<P>M. <HI>Leeches</HI> questions of Accidence and Grammar.</P>
<P>Other helps, especially for directing the Maisters, see
in the Grammar-schoole, Chap. 6.</P>
<P>Thirdly, for more speedy construing the Latin Gram∣mar,
to saue much labour therein, and for keeping the
same with ease, which is otherwise very hard to the
children, and ouer troublesome to the Maister, <HI>Lillies</HI>
rules construed.</P>
<P>Fourthly, for better conceiuing, vnderstanding, apply∣ing,
and making vse of all our Grammar rules.</P>
<P>The Grammar of this last Impression hauing the
summes of the Rules in the margents more perfectly and
fully then formerly, and in the <HI>Syntax,</HI> the words no∣ted
wherein the force of each ensample lieth. In the first
Impression of them many things were mistaken and
corrupted in the printing.</P>
<P>Fiftly,<NOTE PLACE="marg">2. For the speedy and profitable learning all our first and lowest school authors, Gram. tran∣slations.</NOTE> For speedy and profitable learning of all our
<PB N="61" REF="38"/>
first and lowest Schoole-bookes and Authors, (whereas
children are commonly very long in learning some little
peece of them, as of <HI>Sententiae pueriles, Coufabulatiun∣culae,
Cato, &amp;c.</HI> and so the rest; and when they haue lear∣ned
them through with much toyle to themselues and
their Maisters, they are commonly little the better for
them, for any good vse, and doe after presently forget
them, for the most part;) to the end that they may soone
runne thorow all of them, or so much as shalbe thought
good, and that for construing, parsing, vnderstanding,
reading them forth of Latine into English, or forth of
English into Latine; for making the same Latine, and
prouing it; and finally, for leading the learner by the
hand with delight, vntill hee be able to go of himselfe
by ordinary helpes,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Books gram∣matically translated.</NOTE> with much lesse trouble to the
Maister, are prouided Grammaticall translations of
them, as namely; first, of <HI>Sententiae pueriles: Confabu∣latiunculae
pueriles: Corderius dialogues</HI> chiefly for the
ready helpe of speaking Latin of ordinary matters in a
very good and pure phrase.</P>
<P><HI>Catoes morall Disticks,</HI> with the Sentences adioyned,
and also <HI>Isocrates ad Daemonicum,</HI> translated into latine
by <HI>Rodolphus Agricola:</HI> part of <HI>Esops Fables:</HI> the first
booke of <HI>Tullies Offices:</HI> part of <HI>Ouids Metamorphosis:
Virgils Eclog<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es,</HI> with that excellent booke <HI>De Aptbus,</HI>
of the gouernement and ordering of Bees.</P>
<P>All these are made so plaine,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Plainnesse &amp; readinesse of these tran∣slations.</NOTE> as that children, if they
be any thing studious, and well trained vp in the first
grounds of <HI>Grammar,</HI> by the former helpes, may with a
little direction, euer prepare their lectures afore-hand
at home ouer-night: such peeces (I meane) as they are
to learne in lectures; and that, as was said, fo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> euerie
good vse, without neede of other Commentaries in
<PB N="62" REF="39"/>
any of them, or so much helpe of the Maister as is
vsuall. So that they will, by the helpe of them, fall to
their priuate studies of themselues. And for things to be
learned without booke, namely their Authors in verse
so translated, they will be able thereby so to keep them,
as by the meanes thereof, and their other helpes, from
quarter to quarter, to say them without booke, construe,
and to giue all the chiefe difficulties of them, with a ve∣ry
little priuate labour, thus to keep them better in me∣morie,
and haue vse of them continually.</P>
<P>Hereof I might giue you instances of experiments,
according to which you might iudge of them; but I
passe them ouer, standing vpon so euident grounds of
reason, as hath bene shewed before, and as I shall more
fully manifest (God willing) in the Grammar-Schoole,
chap. 8. where I shall set downe the vse of them, with th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
benefit in a right practise.</P>
<P>If you desire a praxis of all or most of the chiefe rules
of the <HI>Syntax</HI> or construction shortly comprized, take
Maister <HI>Leeches</HI> Dialogues,<NOTE PLACE="marg">For a practise of the chiefe rules of con∣struction, Maister <HI>Lee∣ches Dialogues</HI></NOTE> set downe in the end of his
Grammar-questions: which Dialogues are so contriued
of purpose for children to that end: and so likewise
translated into English, as they may be gone through
for each good vse so soone as any of the former.</P>
<P>By that time that children haue gone through these
bookes so translated, and haue by this practise attained
vnto the knowledge and right vse of their Grammar
rules, especially that golden rule of Construing: for
construing, parsing, &amp;c. they will be able, easily, with
much lesse toyle of the Maister, to go through all other
classicall-Schoole-Authors, by such helpes and meanes
as God hath further prouided.</P>
<P>For speedy running ouer the rest of the lower schoole<NOTE PLACE="marg">For the rest of the lower Schoole-au∣thors, other translations.</NOTE>
<PB N="63" REF="39"/>
bookes, which are not so translated grammatically:
first, the other translations of them may be of very good
vse thus farre foorth. As namely, first to giue the lear∣ners
some light for the right vnderstanding &amp; meaning
of the Authors (which vnderstanding of the matter is a
maine foundation for the speedy attaining to any such
learning, especially for getting the Languages, as I haue
shewed elsewhere) as also for resoluing the Authors,
and affoording some good English phrase, with varietie
thereof to expresse their minds. And withall, that by the
right vse of such translations, they may the more easily
learne the manner of our vsuall translating of Authors,
or anie other worke, respecting onely the matter and
intent of the Author, whereof our commonest vse is:
and so for reading forth of Latin into our owne tongue,
to expresse the sense onely, not directly, <HI>verbatim,</HI> or
grammatically, but obseruing perfect sense, good phrase,
and purity of our tongue, and so back againe out of the
English into a good Latine style in like manner. For the
right learning of these Authors doth not so much con∣sist
in the construing and parsing of them, as in getting
by them the matter, phrase and style of the Author, and
to these ends and purposes amongst others, as I take it,
they haue bene translated, and are many of them vn∣knowne
to most.</P>
<DIV3 TYPE="section">
<HEAD>The Translations are these.</HEAD>
<P>1. For the rest of <HI>Tullies Offices,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">For the rest of <HI>Tullies</HI> Of∣fices not tran∣slated gram∣matically, M. <HI>Grimmalds</HI> translation.</NOTE> which are not tran∣slated
grammatically; as namely the two latter bookes,
Maister <HI>Grimmald</HI> his translation, which yet would be
much more profitable to this end, to them who would
make vse of it, if the English were separated from the
Latine, set in a booke by it selfe, as the Grammaticall
and other translations vsually are.</P>
<P><PB N="64" REF="40"/>
2. <HI>For</HI> Tullie De Amicitia, Senectute, &amp;c. Thomas
Newtous <HI>translation.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">For the other parts adioy∣ned to the Offices, <HI>Tho. Newtons</HI> tran∣slation.</NOTE></P>
<P>3. For the rest of <HI>Ouids Metamorphosis, Arthur Gol∣dings</HI>
translation in very good English meeter.</P>
<P>4. For <HI>Ouid de Tristibus,</HI> the translation hereof in
English meeter.<NOTE PLACE="marg">For the rest of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></NOTE></P>
<P>5. <HI>Ouids Epistles,</HI> the like.</P>
<P>6. For the rest of <HI>Virgils Georgickes,</HI> not translated
grammatically, Maister <HI>Abraham Flemmings</HI> transla∣tion
in English meeter, comming next to the Gram∣maticall
translations.</P>
<P>7. For <HI>Virgils Aeneidos,</HI> Maister <HI>Phaer</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Virg. a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>neid <HI>Maister</HI> Pha∣er.</NOTE> in English
meeter.</P>
<P>8. For <HI>Terence,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">For <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>erence</HI> Maister <HI>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r∣nards</HI> transla∣tion.</NOTE> if you thinke good, and especially to
furnish with English phrase to answer the Latine, and
by reading out of the English into Latin, to helpe more
speedily to obtaine the Latin phrase and style, Maister
<HI>Barnards</HI> translation.</P>
<P>Prouided alwayes,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Caution to be vsed in this and other authors.</NOTE> that this be with great caution,
for auoyding all danger of corrupting their manners by
lasciuiousnesse or otherwise; considering the prone∣nesse
of our nature, like to tinder or gunpowder, if neuer
so little a sparke fall into the same. The like caution is to
be had for other, as <HI>Horace, Iuvenal, Persius, Martial, &amp;c.</HI></P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="section">
<HEAD>For higher Authors.</HEAD>
<P>For the more profitable,<NOTE PLACE="marg">For higher Authors, as <HI>Caesars Com∣mentaries,</HI> Sir <HI>Clement Ed∣munds</HI> his translation. This author, with those which follow next, are worthy workes for Noble Gentlemen and all other, who would doe seruice to the Church of God; and their natiue Countrey, to bestow some of their trauels and idle houres in.</NOTE> easie, and speedy reading o∣uer
<HI>Caesars</HI> Commentaries (concerning the <HI>Roman</HI> warre
a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>chiued chiefly by <HI>Caesar)</HI> to the end not onely to giue
light: first, for the true vnderstanding of the Author, but
also to expresse the same in the best and fittest words in
<PB N="65" REF="40"/>
a pure English phrase; and likewise for notable obserua∣tions
for warre, gathered all along out of it, which is one
principall vse of the booke.</P>
<P>The translation of it by Sir <HI>Clement Edmunds,</HI> Clarke
of the Councell.</P>
<P>This booke, as it is wel knowne to be the purest style,
and an excellent history for matter of warre and martiall
affaires, and therefore most necessary for our dayes,
for the better helping to preserue the Church of God
and our natiue countrey; so it is difficult for children, in
regard of the subiect, <HI>viz.</HI> matter of warre, which they
are not acquainted with. Yet by the Translation rightly
vsed, it is made so plaine &amp; easie, that children of twelue
or thirteene yeares of age, rightly trained vp, may be a∣ble
to go through it for all the vses mentioned in short
space, and much more others of riper iudgement. So
that it were great pitty, in regard of the benefit that may
come by it to all sorts, that so worthy a worke should
lie hid as it were, being vnknowne to the greatest part.</P>
<P>The like we may say for these following. For <HI>Lucans
Pharsalia</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>For</HI> Lucans Pharsalia <HI>Sir</HI> Arthur Gorge.</NOTE> of the like argument in verse, <HI>viz.</HI> of the warre
betweene <HI>Caesar</HI> and <HI>Pompey,</HI> Sir <HI>Arthur Gorge</HI> in English
meeter.</P>
<P>For <HI>Liuy</HI> his Roman history, D. <HI>Hollands</HI> translation.<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>For</HI> Liuy D. Hollands <HI>tran∣slation.</HI></NOTE></P>
<P>For that excellent part of the Roman history by <HI>Cor∣nelius
Tacitus</HI> his foure Bookes,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>For</HI> Cornelius Tacitus, <HI>Sir</HI> H. Sauill.</NOTE> translated by that wor∣thy
fauourer and rare promoter of all good learning, Sir
<HI>Henry Sauill.</HI></P>
<P>For <HI>Florus</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Florus.</NOTE> his Roman history, from the foundation
of <HI>Rome</HI> to <HI>Tratanus,</HI> the translation of it, dedicated to
the Lord Marquesse of <HI>Buckingham.</HI></P>
<P>For <HI>Seneca,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Seneca.</NOTE> that admirable Moralist and sweete La∣tinist,
the translation of it by Maister <HI>Lodge.</HI></P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="section">
<PB N="66" REF="41"/>
<HEAD>Commentaries.</HEAD>
<P>Besides these Translations for the ordinary schoole-authors,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Comments▪ on all <HI>O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>id.</HI> For the <HI>Me∣tamorphosis Sabine.</HI></NOTE>
there are also Commentaries for them who
desire their helpe; as, for all <HI>Ouid,</HI> not onely that large
Commentary of sundry together, but more particularly,
For <HI>Ouids Metamorphosis, Sabins</HI> Morals briefly.</P>
<P>Also <HI>Raphael Regius,</HI> a large Commentary.</P>
<P>For <HI>Virgil,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>On</HI> Virgil, Seruius Do∣nate, &amp;c.</NOTE> besides the large Commentary of <HI>Seruius</HI>
and <HI>Donate,</HI> with the Annotations of sundry other, set
out by <HI>Frabricius:</HI> see,</P>
<P>The Analysis of <HI>Ramus</HI> on the <HI>Eclogues</HI> and <HI>Georgicks</HI>
for the Logicke and Rhetoricke thereof.<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ramus,</HI> on the Eclogues and Georgickes.</NOTE></P>
<P>A very sweete paraphrase of <HI>Friskiline</HI> on the <HI>Eclogues</HI>
and <HI>Georgickes.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Friskilines</HI> paraphrase.</NOTE></P>
<P><HI>Meins</HI> Annotations on <HI>Virgil.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Meins.</NOTE> So for the vse of the
Maisters, and all of riper yeares and vnderstanding:</P>
<P><HI>Taubman</HI> on <HI>Virgil,</HI> a very profitable worke.</P>
<P>Moreouer,<NOTE PLACE="marg">For the rest of the anci∣ent Poets short and pi¦thy commen∣taries.</NOTE> for the speedy and more profitable rea∣ding
of all the rest of the chiefe ancient Poets, are pro∣uided
short and pithy Commentaries, or Annotations,
containing the substance and whatsoeuer is of worth in
all the ancient and large Commentaries, and the same
made so plaine, as that very children, rightly trained
vp, may be able, by them, to reade their Lectures of
themselues, or with very little helpe: whereas formerly
they were ouer crabbed and obscure for the Maisters in
many places to vnderstand; as namely,</P>
<P>Maister <HI>Bonds</HI> Commentarie on <HI>Horace</HI> and <HI>Persius.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Maister <HI>Bonds▪</HI></NOTE></P>
<LIST>
<HEAD>Maister Farnabee on<NOTE PLACE="marg">Maister Farn.</NOTE></HEAD>
<ITEM>Iuvenal,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Persius,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Lucan,</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Senecaes</HI> tragedies.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Martiall.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<P><PB N="67" REF="41"/>
Also,<NOTE PLACE="marg">For the Ro∣man histories and antiqui∣ties Maister <HI>Goodwin</HI> his <HI>Anthologia.</HI></NOTE> for the more cleare and full vnderstanding of
these and of all the Romane historie and Antiquities;
<HI>Romanae historiae Anthologia, viz.</HI> a short and very plaine
Exposition in English, of the Romane Antiquities, by
Maister <HI>Goodwine</HI> of <HI>Oxford,</HI> for the vse of <HI>Abingdons</HI>
Schoole.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="section">
<HEAD>Theames.</HEAD>
<P>For helpes for Theames both for matter and maner,
besides the vnderstanding of <HI>Aphthonius</HI> common Pla∣ces,<NOTE PLACE="marg">For Theams M. <HI>Vicars</HI> his <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> for in∣uention and manner.</NOTE>
and the chiefe heads of Inuention by <HI>Ramus</HI> and
others, see Maister <HI>Vicars</HI> his <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, or <HI>Manudu∣ctio,</HI>
leading the scholar (as by the hand) to the vse of
Rhetoricke; especially for making Theames, Declama∣tions,
or Orations.</P>
<P>For matter, <HI>viz.</HI> for short, witty, and easie Sentences
for the yonger sort,<NOTE PLACE="marg">For matter, <HI>Bibliotheca scholastica.</HI></NOTE> Maister <HI>Drax</HI> his <HI>Bibliotheca schola∣stica.
Flores Senecae.</HI></P>
<P>Epitome sentent. Stobaei.</P>
<P>For store of the best examples for Theams both Ro∣man
and forren of most morall matters,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Exampls,</HI> Va∣lerius Max.</NOTE> in stead of new,
they may vse <HI>Valerius Maximus.</HI></P>
<P>This is made plain for the better help of the teachers
where need is, by two ancient Commentaries together,
the one of them by <HI>Oliuerus Arzignanensis,</HI> the other
by <HI>Badius Ascensius,</HI> expounding euery thing clearely,
and almost grammatically, besides the Annotations of
others.</P>
<P>For further help of Theames,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Stobaei An∣thologia.</NOTE> both Latin and Greek,
<HI>Stobaeus</HI> sentences, or his <HI>Anthologia</HI> of the largest: a most
excellent worke, gathered &amp; digested by him Common
place-wise, in Greeke, out of all the famous Greeke
Authors, translated into Latin by <HI>Gesnere</HI> that learned
Phisitian, hauing the Latin set ouer-against the Greek,
and may be singular for acquainting the higher and bet∣ter
<PB N="68" REF="42"/>
sort of scholars, with the best morall matter of sundry
kindes.</P>
<P>For phrases in generall,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Phrases for Theames.</NOTE> Maister <HI>Drax</HI> his <HI>Cilliepeia.</HI></P>
<P>For Epithets, <HI>Ciceroniana Epitheta.</HI></P>
<P>For some select Phrases to this purpose,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Drax</HI> his <HI>Cal∣liepeia,</HI> Mai∣ster <HI>Farnabees</HI> Phrases.</NOTE> and the like,
Maister <HI>Farnabees phrases.</HI></P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="section">
<HEAD>Epistles and Letters.</HEAD>
<P>For patterns of short Epistles and pithy letters of all
sorts of matter;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Patterns for Epistles, <HI>Laconicae Epi∣stolae.</HI></NOTE> see the Laconicall Epistles, to wit, the
shortest and pithiest gathered out of <HI>Tullie, Manutius,
Politian, Erasmus,</HI> and many others, comprized by <HI>Bu∣chlerus</HI>
in a little volume of purpose to this end.</P>
<P>For examples,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Examples for imitation of Epistles of all sorts, <HI>Flores &amp; Sententiae scribendin{que} formulae illu∣stres.</HI></NOTE> seruing and directing for imitation
of sundry kindes of Epistles, both Consolatory, Gratu∣latory,
and also Hortatory, with all the rest of the kinds
of Examples: see <HI>Flores &amp; Sententiae scribendi{que} formulae
illustres.</HI></P>
<P>For pure phrases more peculiarly belonging to Epi∣stles,
see <HI>Manutius</HI> phrases.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="section">
<HEAD>Orations.</HEAD>
<P>For Orations:<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Orations,</HI> Melchior Iu∣nius.</NOTE> The Orations of sundry, and those of
diuers kindes of Morall matters, and vpon sundry occa∣sions,
gathered and set forth by <HI>Melchior Iunius.</HI></P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="section">
<HEAD>Examining of Phrases in Prose.</HEAD>
<P>For helpe in examining of phrases,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Examining phrases in prose.</NOTE> and so for ob∣seruing
propriety and purity therein.</P>
<P>1. <HI>Godscalcus</HI> his obseruations of the Latin tongue
digested alphabetically.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Godscalcus.</NOTE></P>
<P>2. <HI>Schorus</HI> phrases,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Schorus.</NOTE> shewing also the manner how to
obserue phrases in the reading of Authors.</P>
<P>3. <HI>Erasmus</HI> his Epitome of <HI>Vallaes</HI> elegancies,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Erasmus</HI> Epit. of <HI>Vallaes</HI> e∣legancies, <HI>Popma.</HI></NOTE> of the
last Edition.</P>
<P>4. Popma de Differentijs verborum.</P>
<P><PB N="69" REF="42"/>
For flourishing and amplifying in Prose, <HI>see Cicero∣niana
Epitheta, Antitheta &amp; Adiuncta.</HI></P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="section">
<HEAD>Poetrie.</HEAD>
<P>Besides <HI>Textoris Epitheta,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>In Poetry.</HI> Text. Epith. Buchleri The∣saurus poëti∣cus.</NOTE> See <HI>Buchleri Thesaurus poë∣ticus,</HI>
a booke of notable vse for each scholar: for helpes
of Epithets and Poeticall phrases: and also for his dire∣ction
of the right manner of making a pure verse, with
other things belonging thereto.</P>
<P>For quantities of Syllables,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Smetius.</NOTE> <HI>Smetius</HI> his <HI>Prosodia.</HI></P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="section">
<HEAD>Dictionaries.</HEAD>
<P>For both English and Latine,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Dictionaries.</NOTE> especially for finding
out the fittest Latin words to the English, and most na∣turall;
and according to propriety first, together with
the Etymologies or notations of the Latine words,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Rider.</NOTE> <HI>Ri∣ders</HI>
dictionarie of the last.</P>
<P>For giuing the Greeke to the Latine, and for supply
of sundry of the best Latin phrases expounded,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Thomas Tho∣masius.</NOTE> and the
vse shewed, <HI>Thomas</HI> Dictionarie of the last.</P>
<P>For a short comprising of most Latine Primitiues in
Sentences (except those which belong to the seuerall
Arts and Trades &amp;c.) and so to furnish with most words
of all sorts,<NOTE PLACE="marg">For a short comprising of the Latine Primitiues, <HI>Ianua lingua∣rum.</HI></NOTE> for reading of any ordinary author belon∣ging
to the grammar schoole, or otherwise, <HI>Ianua lingua∣rum,</HI>
a booke in twelue hundred sentences containing
the most of the ordinary words, to be euen as a Dictio∣narie
in the childrens heads, translated into English, to
the end it may be more easily and speedily gotten.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="section">
<HEAD>Analysis or resoluing of Authors.</HEAD>
<P>For a plaine and easie resolution of the matter of Au∣thors
meete for young scholars,<NOTE PLACE="marg">For resoluing authors, Gram. trans. of &amp;c.</NOTE> see the grammaticall
translation of the first booke of <HI>Tullies</HI> Offices.</P>
<P>Also of the first booke of <HI>Ouids Metamorphosis.</HI></P>
<P>And withall, the like translation of the first and last
<PB N="70" REF="43"/>
Eclogue of <HI>Vìrgil,</HI> and of his fourth booke of the <HI>Geor∣gickes
De Apibus,</HI> some of these in the inmost colums,
others in the outmost.</P>
<P>For a more learned <HI>Analysis</HI> in Latine, both Logicall
and Rhetoricall, see <HI>Ramus</HI> Commentaries on the <HI>Ec∣logues</HI>
and <HI>Georgickes,</HI> and also vpon all the Orations of
<HI>Tully,</HI> on which he hath commented. Also <HI>Piscators A∣nalysis</HI>
of <HI>Tullies</HI> Offices.</P>
<P>For a short and methodicall <HI>Analysis</HI> of the seuerall
bookes of the Scripture, and of each chapter therein, see
<HI>Gemma Fabri.</HI></P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="section">
<HEAD>Disputing scholar-like of Grammar Questions, and to pre∣pare
for more learned Disputations in
the Vniuersities.</HEAD>
<P>1. In English,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Disputation of Grammar questions, in English; Posing of the Parts.</NOTE> by way of Questions and Answers to
make children perfect in the Accidence and Grammar;
The Posing of the Parts.</P>
<P>2. In Latine,<NOTE PLACE="marg">In Latine, M. <HI>Stockwoods</HI> disput.</NOTE> for the better scholars in a more large
and scholar-like dispute, Maister <HI>Stockwoods</HI> disputati∣ons
of Grammar.</P>
<P>3. For the like dispute in <HI>Tullies</HI> Offices by Questi∣ons
and Answers,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Disputing of morall que∣stions, master <HI>Brasbridge</HI> questions of <HI>Tullies</HI> Off.</NOTE> the better to vnderstand the rare and
almost diuine matter, for direction of manners, in that
booke, Maister <HI>Brasbridge</HI> his Questions of <HI>Tullies</HI> Of∣fices.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="section">
<HEAD>Proper words for seuerall Arts and Sciences.</HEAD>
<P>To be able to get and remember words appertaining
to Arts,<NOTE PLACE="marg">For words belonging to Historie, Trades, &amp;c. <HI>Stanbridg. vo∣cabula.</HI></NOTE> Trades, Sciences, histories of diuers kinds, and
the like, as any one desireth them; first Maister <HI>Stan∣bridge</HI>
his <HI>Vocabula</HI> in verse. These verses are some of
them amended already; the rest so purposed.</P>
<P><PB N="71" REF="43"/>
After him, where he ends, others may be adioyned,
in the end of <HI>Hunters</HI> Cosmographie, in verse like∣wise.</P>
<P>For words belonging to <HI>Astronomy</HI> and <HI>Cosmography:</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Hunters Cos∣mographie.</NOTE>
and also the ancient proper names of places, as Coun∣tries,
Cities, and Riuers, &amp;c. <HI>Hunters</HI> Cosmographie
in verse.</P>
<P>If the names of the places,<NOTE PLACE="marg">How this might be more profi∣table.</NOTE> riuers, &amp;c. as they are ter∣med
at this day, were set directly ouer the heads of each
of the ancient names there, after the manner of <HI>Stan∣bridges
Vocabula,</HI> it might be of most excellent vse, and
soone gotten, or set on the opposite page directly a∣gainst
them.</P>
<P>All other words of like nature, belonging to the se∣uerall
histories, or whatsoeuer else, might be thus com∣prised
in verse, after the manner of <HI>Stanbridge</HI> or <HI>Hun∣ter,</HI>
or otherwise, they might be set downe in a short
narration, in forme of a Dialogue grammatically tran∣slated,
after the manner of <HI>Corderius</HI> Dialogues, where∣in
he sets out, to the like purpose, a very sumptuous
banquet in an historicall narration, in the 22. Dialogue
of his fourth booke.</P>
<P>Such a booke might easily be compiled by a iudici∣ous
scholar,<NOTE PLACE="marg">How such a worke might be easily compiled.</NOTE> of a pregnant wit, hauing meete leisure, by
the helpe of <HI>Hadrianus Iunius</HI> his <HI>Nomenclator;</HI> and the
speciall Dictionaries for seuerall vses, and so any such
words be very readily gotten, by studying and reading
them oft forth of English into Latin: as experience tea∣cheth
in the like.</P>
<P>But all these would be gotten much sooner,<NOTE PLACE="marg">How best learned.</NOTE> if being
thus verbally translated into English, the English were
set by it selfe, so to study it out of them, like as the <HI>Gram∣mar</HI>
translations are.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="section">
<PB N="72" REF="44"/>
<HEAD>Greeke.</HEAD>
<P>Whereas there is nothing in any tongue for the per∣fect
obtaining of it,<NOTE PLACE="marg">For speedy attaining to the Greeke.</NOTE> but Grammar, words, and pra∣ctise
of them in a right composing and setting them to∣gether:
I meane, first, the knowledge of the Grammar
rules, belonging to that tongue; words to expresse the
minde, and practise of both in reading Authors, and in
writing; for most easie and speedy attaining to the <HI>Greek</HI>
tongue, which hath bene wont to be so difficult and te∣dious:
God hath prouided these readie helpes.</P>
<P>1. For the Grammar,<NOTE PLACE="marg">For the Grammar Maister <HI>Cam∣dens</HI> most profitable for vs.</NOTE> Maister <HI>Camdens</HI> is of all o∣ther
most easie and profitable (as I take it) like as for
<HI>Westminster,</HI> so for all our schooles; for that it followes
the order of our Latine Grammar most directly, chiefly
in the <HI>Syntax,</HI> wherein many of the rules are the very
same, or neare vnto them. The Anomalies in the Verbs
being set alphabetically, so as they may be found very
readily; and the Dialects set directly after the order of
the Declensions and Coniugations, that by it alone
well studied, most difficulties may be easily vnderstood
and answered.</P>
<P>For all other difficulties,<NOTE PLACE="marg">For other difficulties concerning Grammar, <HI>Cleonards</HI> Gram with Ant<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sign.</NOTE> and wherein it seemes to
faile; see <HI>Cleonards</HI> Greeke Grammar, with <HI>Antesigna∣nus,</HI>
set foorth by <HI>Sylburgius,</HI> wherein by the help of the
large <HI>Index,</HI> you may be resolued of most doubts.</P>
<P>Hereunto adioyne,<NOTE PLACE="marg">The short a∣bridgement in the eud of Scapula.</NOTE> if need be to enquire further, the
Anomalies, Dialects and other difficulties set downe al∣phabetically
in the end of <HI>Scapulaes</HI> Dictionary.</P>
<P>Secondly,<NOTE PLACE="marg">For speedy attaining the greeke Pri∣mitiues.</NOTE> for attaining very speedily to all the Greek
Primitiues or Radices; which being had, all the rest
are easily and plainely learned, as deriued from them,
God hath prouided,</P>
<P>1. The <HI>Clauis linguae Graecae,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Clauis <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Graecae.</NOTE> by <HI>Lubine.</HI> In which litle
<PB N="73" REF="44"/>
briefe, all, or most of the Greeke Radices are included
in some seuen hundred little sentences, in imitation of
<HI>Ianua linguarum,</HI> with a double <HI>Index</HI> adioyned, <HI>viz.</HI>
both Latine before the Greeke, and Greeke before the
Latine; whereby they may be soone gotten, and easily
kept, or recouered being forgotten.</P>
<P>2. For the more full vnderstanding of the tongue,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>For a more full know∣ledge of thē,</HI> Fundamētum linguae Graecae, siue Epitome Lexici &amp; Ety∣mologici graeci proschola Br<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣mensi.</NOTE> for
propriety and right significations, Notations or Ety∣mologies,
Deriuations, and the like, see <HI>Fundamentum
linguae Graecae;</HI> a little Epytome gathered briefly of pur∣pose,
according to the order of <HI>Scapula.</HI> For the larger
explication of the same, with phrases and vse of words;
see <HI>Scapula.</HI></P>
<P>For practise in reading some vsuall Authors.<NOTE PLACE="marg">Authors in verse, <HI>Theog∣nis, &amp;c.</HI> with <HI>Sylburgius.</HI></NOTE> The fit∣test
for yong scholars (so faire as I can iudge) after they
haue runne through their <HI>Clauis,</HI> if you will begin with
Poetry, that they may learne to make a verse in Greek, is</P>
<P><HI>Theognis</HI> his sentences with the other Poets ioyned
with him; as namely <HI>Phocilides, Pythagoras, &amp;c.</HI> with the
Latine translation and annotations thereof, set forth by
<HI>Silburgius.</HI> Some whereof being learned without booke
perfectly, is a speciall helpe that scholars may haue
quantities, phrase, and apt morall matter for verse.</P>
<P>2. If you please to reade <HI>Hesiode</HI> his <HI>Opera &amp; Dies,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Hesiode <HI>with</HI> Ceporine &amp; Melancth.</NOTE>
you may vse <HI>Ceporine</HI> and <HI>Melancthons</HI> Commentaries
set foorth by <HI>Iohannes Frisius Tigurinus;</HI> and the new
translation of it by <HI>Erasmus Schemidt</HI> professor at <HI>Wit∣tenberg.</HI></P>
<P>Or if you desire to reade <HI>Homer,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">For <HI>Homer.</HI></NOTE> which is most ge∣nerally
approued of all, as the most excellent Poet: be∣sides
the Latine Translations, especially that which ex∣poundeth
it most neerly and properly.</P>
<P>For the better vnderstanding and expressing of it in
<PB N="74" REF="45"/>
English,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Maister <HI>Chap∣man</HI> in En∣glish meeter.</NOTE> Maister <HI>Chapmans</HI> translation in English mee∣ter;
whom we may rightly call, the English <HI>Homer.</HI></P>
<P>To these you may adde,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Eustathius.</NOTE> if you will, <HI>Eustathius,</HI> and
the large Commentarie of <HI>Spondanus.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Spondanus.</NOTE></P>
<P>For the best and fittest Authors in Prose to be read in
Schooles,<NOTE PLACE="marg">For prose▪ <HI>Isocrates</HI> tran∣slated by <HI>VVolphius. Schorus</HI> his translation with annotat.</NOTE> as namely <HI>Isocrates ad Daemonicum,</HI> are the
translations of <HI>Wolphius:</HI> and also of <HI>Rodolphus Agricola:</HI>
and like wise the translation of <HI>Antonius Scorus,</HI> with his
annotations adioyned to his booke <HI>De ratione discendi▪
linguae Graecae.</HI></P>
<P>2. For <HI>Zenophon,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Zenophons Cy∣ropaideia.</NOTE> the translation of his 3. first bookes
<HI>de Cyri vita &amp; disciplina.</HI></P>
<P>For more speedy reading the Greeke Testament,<NOTE PLACE="marg">For the Greek Testament, <HI>Pasors</HI> dictio∣narie.</NOTE> <HI>Pa∣sors</HI>
Dictionary gathered of purpose to that end. What
is defectiue may be supplied by the <HI>Fundamentum, Pis∣cator</HI>
and others.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="section">
<HEAD>VVriting in Greeke.</HEAD>
<P>For writing exercises in Greeke,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>For writing in Greeke,</HI> Clauis, Thomas<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s, Garthius. Poselij Calligr. Elegantiae graecae.</NOTE> or translating into
Greeke: besides, the <HI>Clauis linguae Graecae</HI> for words, and
also <HI>Thomas</HI> his Dictionarie, for phrase you may vse
<HI>Garthius</HI> his Lexicon: and withall for prose <HI>Poselii Calli∣graphia:
Elegantiae Graecae</HI> by <HI>Vollandus.</HI></P>
<P>In verse for Epithets and Authorities,<NOTE PLACE="marg">In verse for Epithets and authorities, <HI>Dinnerus.</HI></NOTE> <HI>Dinnerus</HI> his
Greeke Epithets.</P>
<P>For morall matter in Greeke,<NOTE PLACE="marg">For morall matter out <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> best Greeke Au∣thors, <HI>Stobaei Anthologia, Cornucopia.</HI></NOTE> with excellent senten∣ces
and discourses out of all the ancient and best Greeke
Authors, for the vse of Translations, Theames, Verses,
Declamations or Orations.</P>
<P><HI>Stobaei sententiae,</HI> called <HI>Anthologia;</HI> or <HI>Cornucopia</HI> of
the largest.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="section">
<HEAD>Speaking Greeke.</HEAD>
<P>For speaking of ordinarie matters in Greeke,<NOTE PLACE="marg">For speaking Greeke, Po∣selius.</NOTE> <HI>Poselius</HI>
his Dialogues.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="section">
<PB N="75" REF="45"/>
<HEAD>Hebrue.</HEAD>
<P>For a most speedy attaining to the Hebrue.</P>
<P>1. For the Grammar,<NOTE PLACE="marg">For Hebrue Grammar.</NOTE> though euery one may take
for his owne vse what Grammar he hath learned, or is
most familiarly acquainted with, and supply out of o∣thers
what is wanting therein; yet for him that is newly
to beginne, or desires most easily to teach or direct o∣thers<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Martinius</HI> printed by <HI>R<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣phalengius</HI> at <HI>Berne.</HI></NOTE>
I take (vnder better iudgement) <HI>Martinius</HI> to be
the best. My reasons are,</P>
<P>1. For that it is most methodicall,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Reason of it.</NOTE> proceeding ac∣cording
to the right order of Nature and rules of Art.</P>
<P>2. For that it hath answering vnto it, Maister <HI>Vdals</HI>
Hebrue Grammar in English, being in effect a meere
translation of <HI>Martinius,</HI> onely leauing out some things
which he thought lesse necessary, and making most
things in <HI>Martinius</HI> very plaine, in stead of a Commen∣tary,
as the translations do the Authors.</P>
<P>3. For that the <HI>Martinius</HI> Grammar printed by <HI>Ra∣phalengius</HI>
and by <HI>Abrahamus VVeerlinus</HI> at <HI>Berne,</HI> haue
a <HI>Praxis</HI> adioyned, for the parsing of three <HI>Psalmes, viz.</HI>
the 1. 25. and 68, like as Maister <HI>Vdals</HI> hath in English:
which <HI>Praxis</HI> is so orderly for the right examining or a¦nalysing
of euery word according to the order of na∣ture
and art, and according as all things are set downe
in the Grammar in order of the Chapters, that they
leade the learner directly, as by the hand, to the plaine
parsing and resoluing of those three <HI>Psalmes;</HI> and by
them, auy other part of the Hebrue Bible.</P>
<P>And lastly, for that Maister <HI>Vdals</HI> Grammar, (which
I commend as a short Commentarie to it) hath also a
briefe Epitome of the Hebrue Lexicon adioyned, for
the more speedy finding out any word, and so attai∣ning
the tongue.</P>
<P><PB N="76" REF="46"/>
Or in stead of <HI>Martinius,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Maister <HI>Vdals</HI> Grammar.</NOTE> Maister <HI>Vdals</HI> Grammar it
selfe, which I finde to be farre more easie for the lear∣ner,
and much sooner gotten, for the vse of it, and also
may be readily deliuered and vttered in Latine, at least
by comparing with <HI>Martinius.</HI></P>
<P>For the best Lexicon or Dictionarie,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Lexicon <HI>Buxtorphius.</HI></NOTE> <HI>Buxtorphius</HI>
his Epitome for continuall vse: and also his <HI>Thesaurus</HI>
for more exquisite knowledge: or,</P>
<P>For giuing the Hebrue words to the Latine; <HI>Lexi∣con
Latino-Hebraicum,</HI> in the end of the Epitome of <HI>Pag∣nine</HI>
by <HI>Raphalengius.</HI></P>
<P>For helpe for construing, and so reading priuately,
and knowing the <HI>Radices.</HI></P>
<P>The Interlineal Bible, by <HI>Arias Montanus.</HI></P>
<P>For the <HI>Psalmes,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Tossanus.</NOTE> <HI>Tossanus</HI> may affoord some helpe.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="section">
<HEAD>English.</HEAD>
<P>Concerning our owne language,<NOTE PLACE="marg">For our owne tongue to grow in pro∣prietie and puritie.</NOTE> whereas some great
learned, haue much and long complained, that in most
Schooles there hath bene litle care, to teach Scholars to
expresse their mindes readily in proprietie and puritie
of speech, so to helpe to adorne our owne tongue;
whereof wee haue continuall practise, to the end that
they may grow herein with the Latine and other lear∣ned
tongues, God hath prouided these helpes.</P>
<P>1. The vse of the grammaticall translations (hauing
to that end,<NOTE PLACE="marg">1. Grāmatical translations for all the first begin∣ners.</NOTE> both proprietie and also varietie of words
and phrase to expresse the minde) may be a good en∣trance
for the yonger sort.</P>
<P>2. After them,<NOTE PLACE="marg">2 Other tran∣slations.</NOTE> all the other translations, vsed onely
in such sort, as hath bene and shall be further shewed
in the Grammar schoole; so to ascend to those who
haue written most exquisitely in that kinde of Tran∣slation.</P>
<P><PB N="77" REF="46"/>
3. Dictionaries,<NOTE PLACE="marg">3. Dictiona∣ries.</NOTE> where fit words are wanting, to make
choise of those English words in them which best agree
to the matter in hand.</P>
<P>4. Adioyne to these,<NOTE PLACE="marg">4. Best authors in each kinde for English.</NOTE> for them who would grow to
more exquisite perfection, the bookes of such as haue
written the purest style in English in each faculty, which
they purpose to exercise themselues in.</P>
<P>For strangers,<NOTE PLACE="marg">For strangers.</NOTE> who vnderstand the Latine tongue,
at least in some sort, and would learne our tongue them∣selues,
or would teach it vnto others publiquely or pri∣uately,
besides the former helpes for reading English.</P>
<P>1. The English Grammar,<NOTE PLACE="marg">The English Grammar.</NOTE> called <HI>Grammatica Angli∣cana,</HI>
a little Epitome written according to the rules of
Art, by <HI>P. Gr.</HI> printed at <HI>Cambridge Anno</HI> 1594.</P>
<P>2. <HI>Logonomia Anglica,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Logonomia Anglica.</NOTE> by Maister <HI>Gill</HI> Schoole-mai∣ster
of <HI>Paules.</HI></P>
<P>3. Translations, first grammaticall; which leade the
Scholar directly to learne our tongue; after other tran∣slations,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Translations.</NOTE>
and so the best English Authors and Dictio∣naries
as before.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="section">
<HEAD>Rhetoricke.</HEAD>
<P>For Rhetoricke,<NOTE PLACE="marg">For Tropes and Figures briefly in vse, Maister <HI>Fa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣nabees</HI> tropes and figures.</NOTE> so farre as shall be necessary for the
Grammar-schoole.</P>
<P>1. For Tropes and Figures of Rhetoricke, and so for
other figures of Grammar, Maister <HI>Farnabees</HI> Tropes
and figures, so shortly comprized in verse, as that they
may be most easily gotten in a very little time, and so
likewise kept in memorie, to serue for euery good vse.</P>
<P>2. For a more full vnderstanding of that little booke,<NOTE PLACE="marg">For a more methodicall tractate▪ M. <HI>Butlers</HI> Rhe∣toricke.</NOTE>
and of all other matters belonging to Rhetoricke, as for
a methodicall handling, and short comprizing of the
whole Art, by precepts, illustrations by examples, and
the like.</P>
<P><PB N="78" REF="47"/>
M. <HI>Butlers</HI> Rhetorick of <HI>Magd.</HI> colledge in <HI>Oxf.</HI> with
a short commentary adioyned, now the 4. time printed.</P>
<P>3. For the vse of Rhetoricke,<NOTE PLACE="marg">3. For the vse of Rhetorick, Maister <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, Ma∣nuductio ad artem Rheto∣ricum.</NOTE> <HI>viz.</HI> for the practise
thereef in Theames, Declamatious, Orations, &amp;c.</P>
<P>The <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, or <HI>Manuductio ad artem Rhetoricam,</HI> by
Maister <HI>Vicars</HI> of Queenes Colledge in <HI>Oxford.</HI></P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="section">
<HEAD>Religion.</HEAD>
<P>Concerning Religion;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Religion, for laying surely the grounds <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</NOTE> for laying surely the first
grounds of our holy Religion in Schooles, according
to our good lawes; and for seasoning the first and ten∣der
yeares of our children therewith: (wherein the Ie∣suites
shall rise in iudgement against vs, being farre more
vigilant and industrious to destroy, then we to saue; to
ouerthrow the Gospell, then wee to propagate and
spreade it.)</P>
<P>1. To the end that Scholars may speedily get and e∣uer
keepe in fresh memorie with ease and delight,<NOTE PLACE="marg">For know∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>edge of the historie of the Bible, Bibliorum summula.</NOTE> the
whole summe of the sacred story, <HI>viz.</HI> the holie Bible,
(being the sole foundation of our Religion,) and so the
summe of euery Chapter therein; wherby they may be∣come
sound Christians, and in time (through the Lords
blessing) admirable Diuines, God hath prouided a litle
Booke called <HI>Bibliorum summula,</HI> which comprizeth
the arguments or sums of euery Chapter of the whole
Bible in Disticks, <HI>viz.</HI> each Chapter in two verses, be∣ginning
alphabetically, that they may be more happily
committed to memorie, and recalled more easily
when they are forgotten.</P>
<P>This booke is most painefully and profitably compo∣sed
in a familiar and easie verse, by Maister <HI>Shaw,</HI> ac∣cording
to the contents of the seuerall Chapters.<NOTE PLACE="marg">A more brief abridgement <HI>Memoriale, Biblicu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></NOTE></P>
<P>Hereunto is adioyned in the end, for further helpe of
memorie, the same contriued farre more briefly, <HI>viz.</HI>
<PB N="79" REF="47"/>
in a very few verses: as namely <HI>Genesis</HI> hauing fiftie Di∣sticks
in the <HI>Summula,</HI> according to the fifty Chapters, is
comprized in ten verses, euery verse whereof compre∣hends
fiue Chapters, &amp; almost euery word notes a seue∣rall
Chapter; thus notably deuised by <HI>Math. Martinius.</HI></P>
<P>2. For the first principles or iudiments in Religion,<NOTE PLACE="marg">For the p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>in∣ciples besides those by law appointed, Maister Per∣kins <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ixe Prin∣ciples ex∣pounded.</NOTE>
to be taught in Catechizing; and for building soundly
vpon the sacred Scriptures, according to the doctrine
of our Church: besides our ordinary Catechismes by
Law established, for a further vnfolding and demon∣strating
of the principles out of the expresse texts of the
Word, Maister <HI>Perkins</HI> six Principles expounded, with
many other, and chiefly such briefe ones, as by their
oftest printing do testifie the greatest liking, and most
generall approbation of the godly learned.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="section">
<HEAD>VVriting.</HEAD>
<P>For faire writing in our owne,<NOTE PLACE="marg">For faire wri∣ting, Copie bookes for Secretarie, Romane, Greeke, He∣brue.</NOTE> and all the chiefe lear∣ned
tongues.</P>
<P>Copie bookes, prepared of purpose for the Gram∣mar-schooles,
as in Secretarie for our English, so for
the Latine, Greeke and Hebrew, together with dire∣ctions
for writing in the beginning of them, printed by
Maister <HI>Thomas Man;</HI> whereby all Scholars, well entred
and practized from their beginning, euery day a little,
may come to write commendably, and many of them
verie faire euery of these hands, without hindering their
learning, as is proued by experience.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="section">
<HEAD>Memorie.</HEAD>
<P>For the helpe of Memorie,<NOTE PLACE="marg">For Memory.</NOTE> besides all directions for
briefe summes of euery matter, as are set downe in their
places in the Grammar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>schoole and others; and besides
diuers good rules and precepts for memorie in a little
booke called <HI>The Castle of Memorie,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Maister</HI> Wil∣lies Mnemo∣nica.</NOTE> Chap. 6.</P>
<P>Maister <HI>VVillies</HI> his booke of Memorie, called <HI>Mne∣monica
<PB N="80" REF="48"/>
siue Reminiscendi,</HI> are gathered out of the best
who haue written thereof: out of which the most profi∣table
things may be selected and vsed by them who are
judicious.</P>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>Other Bookes and helps,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Bookes pre∣pared for the Presse.</NOTE> some of
them readie for the Presse, others in good
forwardnesse to be soone prepared, if they shall
be generally desired, and the desire signified to
the Stationers, as necessarie or profitable
for the ends for which they haue bene
trauelled in, as namely;</HEAD>
<P>1 <SEG REND="decorInit">F</SEG>Or furnishing with fit matter for Theams
in Prose or Verse,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Helpe for matter for Theames.</NOTE> Latine and Greeke,
which so troubleth young scholars, and
discourageth them,<NOTE PLACE="marg">An <HI>Index</HI> ga¦thered out of the fittest Schoole-authors and others, with references to the places.</NOTE> for that they know
not where to finde such fit matter for them, and must
needes be very difficult before a great deale of reading
and practise; there is an <HI>Index</HI> or booke of References,
gathered out of their Schoole-authors and others, onely
pointing at the places where to finde them.</P>
<P>2. For patterns for Theames,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Tullies</HI> para∣doxes transla∣ted gramma∣tically for patternes for Theames. The Laconi∣call Epistles translated.</NOTE> <HI>Tullies</HI> Paradoxes tran∣slated
grammatically, with a short Analysis in the mar∣gent,
whereby they may be learned more perfectly, and
vnderstood more fully to that end.</P>
<P>3. For direction and patterns for writing pithy and
short letters in English, which is amongst vs, both most
<PB N="81" REF="48"/>
commendable, and of principall and daily vse. The La∣conicall
Epistles, translated into a good English style,
with the Grammar order and propriety in the margents.</P>
<P>4. For the more speedy and profitable learning the
<HI>Ianua linguarum</HI> for euery good vse;<NOTE PLACE="marg">4. For the more speedie &amp; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> learning <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> it is pre∣pared to be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, printed as to supply what is wanting or Grammar order, pro∣p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>etie, de∣clining, quan∣tities, and E∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ymologies.</NOTE> whereas now, the
English, in many places keepeth onely the sense, but va∣rieth
both from the verball and Grammar order, and
also from the propriety of the words in the Latin, wher∣by
the learners are oft exceedingly puzled and carried
amisse: there <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s prouided a grammaticall translation to
be set in the margen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s in the English, to carry the lear∣ner
aright, both for proprietie and Grammar. And also
in the <HI>Index</HI> or Table, are set downe the declining of the
Nownes and Verbs, with the Genders of the Nownes,
to serue in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of a Dictionarie for all of them: and
withall, both the doubtfull quantities, and likewise
the Etymologies or notations of the words briefly, be∣ing
examined by comparing the best Authors in that
kinde, and conference with other learned.</P>
<P>So that the learner may soone runne through it, to
get both English by the Latine, and Latine by the En∣glish,
with certainty, and for the other vses mentioned.</P>
<P>For furnishing with <HI>Terence</HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>phrase, with the best
matter, <HI>Terentianus Christianus,</HI> translated grammati∣cally.</P>
<DIV3 TYPE="section">
<HEAD>For the Greeke.</HEAD>
<P>1. For getting speedily the Greeke Radices or Pri∣mitiues,<NOTE PLACE="marg">For speedie getting the Greeke Pri∣mitiues, <HI>Cla∣uis linguae Graeca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> made much more plaine.</NOTE>
the <HI>Clauis linguae Graece</HI> is made much more
plaine, easie and profitable; first, by the Latine set in
the margent, according to the Greeke, answering word
for word in such places where it now differs, and the
whole Latine sentences to be placed in the page oppo∣site
to the Greeke, to leade the learner rightly by the
<PB N="82" REF="49"/>
hand to the knowledge of the Greeke, whereas now
many of the Sentences in Latine do onely expresse the
sense, and so set the learner at a stand, or carry him quite
amisse.</P>
<P>2. By the principall Etymologies set in the margent
of the Greeke Sentences, directed with letters to know
them speedily.</P>
<P>3. By a grammaticall construction of the same in
English, answering the Greeke so neare as may be, ad∣ioyned
in the end of the <HI>Clauis,</HI> with proprietie and va∣rietie
of the sense in the margents. By the h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lpe where∣of
(as experience will soone shew) all the Sentences
may be gotten in a very little time, both for Latine and
Greeke, by studying them out of the English, onely hel∣ped
by looking vpon the Greeke and Latin, as need re∣quireth;
to be able thereby to giue the Greeke and La∣tine
words to the English, and contrarily, so to serue
for any good vse thereof: and euer easily by this means
to keepe all perfectly, without any trouble or charge
of memorie, through the help of the perfect vnderstan∣ding
of it by this translation.</P>
<P>Also for the easier entrance of the young Scholar to
runne cheerefully and speedily through the best Greeke
Authors in prose,<NOTE PLACE="marg">For entrance in the speedie the running tho∣rough the best Greeke Authors in prose, Grammatical translations of <HI>Isocrates ad Daemonicum.</HI></NOTE> as well as in verse, is prepared <HI>Isocra∣tes
ad Daemonicum,</HI> translated both in Latine gramma∣tically;
and also with another translation in a more pure
Latine style.</P>
<P>So likewise the first booke of <HI>Zenophons Cyropaideia</HI>
in like manner.</P>
<P>Which three bookes being well gone through,<NOTE PLACE="marg">The first <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <HI>Z<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣nophons Cyro∣paideia.</HI></NOTE> scho∣lars
will easily and speedily run through all other Greek
Authors, by the ordinarie helpes of translations, and
the like meanes which God hath so bountifully proui∣ded
<PB N="83" REF="49"/>
for this last Age, especially if they haue said a good
foundation in the Grammar first.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="section">
<HEAD>Hebrue.</HEAD>
<P>For laying speedily a sure foundation;<NOTE PLACE="marg">For the spee∣dy and sure attaining all the Hebrue Radiees, are preparing a <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>word</HI> and a <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> there∣unto like <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> and Greeke.</NOTE> first, for the
right knowledge of all the Hebrue Primitiues in their
first and proper signification; secondly, by what Tropes
their significations are changed into other senses: and
so thirdly, by what reasons or notations all their deri∣uatiues
and issue come thereof: and finally, for getting
speedily all the Hebrue Primitiues without booke; and
with the getting of them, to learne also so much of the
Hebrue Bible in most profitable matters and sentences,
there hath bene long thought of, and is now in prepa∣ring.</P>
<P>First, a briefe Hebrue Lexicon, after the manner of
the <HI>Fundamentum linguae Graecae.</HI></P>
<P>And secondly, another little booke after the manner
of <HI>Clauis linguae Graecae,</HI> wherein all, or most of the He∣brue
Primitiues are to be comprized, in certaine choise
sentences of the sacred Scriptures, of sundry kindes of
matt<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</P>
<P>This may be called fi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ly <HI>Ianua linguae Hebraicae;</HI> the
other, the <HI>Clauis</HI> vnto it.</P>
<P>As these two may be of notable vse, to make speedily
perfect Hebricians, and likewise to helpe to prepare the
way to the calling of the Iewes thereby, so they re∣quire
the cunningest workemen for the more curious
framing and finishing of them: whom God hath also
prouided, if some noble minded fauourers of good
learning, and of the Church of Christ, will but a little
lay to their helping hands, for defraying the charges of
their maintenance, till they shall be able to go through
the worke, to bring them to perfection, for the full ac∣complishment
<PB N="84" REF="50"/>
of all the good therein desired.</P>
<P>For all these bookes and helpes more particularly,<NOTE PLACE="marg">For all these helpes more particularly, and the right vse of them: the Grammar schoole in this last Edi∣tion.</NOTE>
and for the right vse of euery of them, and how to auoid
all the abuses and other in conueniences; and so for at∣taining
all those parts or learning mentioned in the
Contents, see the Booke called <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, or the
Grammar-schoole in this second Edition: where, in a
familiar Dialogue betweene two Schoole-maisters all
these things are full discussed and set foorth, and yet
the booke in many things abridged, and made lesse then
before.</P>
<P>For matter of charges to prouide so many helpes,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Matter of charge, and all objections there answe∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>▪</NOTE> the
gaining of one yeares learning will plentifully recom∣pence,
if we vse onely the necessarie: and all the other
benefits be a sufficient ouerplus.</P>
<P>For all other obiections, I referre you likewise to the
Grammar-schoole, where (I hope) you shall see your
selfe well satisfied in all. And what is still wanting, I trust
the same good hand of our God will, in his due time,
f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ly supply.</P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="afterword">
<PB REF="50"/>
<HEAD>❧ The Examiners Censure:
<DATE>March. 16. 1620.</DATE></HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">W</SEG>Here as this Author, still desirous to com∣municate
all the new comforts, which
God hath vouchs<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>fed him in his long
and painefull trauels, for the generall
good, and specially for our Grammar-schooles; and
fearing lest in anie matter he should deceiue himselfe
or others, hath intreated vs to make some further
triall of the things which he hath written h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rein, for
the better confirmation of himselfe and of all others;
we could not denie his so honest a request. There∣fore
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Labours in this kinde, by <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
of <HI>Worcester,</HI> at the first <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
of his Gramm<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r-schoole, as appeares in the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
Preface before it, and by other <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
since; yet now that it is to come foorth <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>,
much more compleate and perfect after so much
long trauell and experience) we haue her<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>upon made
new and further triall accordingly. In which we haue
<PB REF="51"/>
found so much content in euery forme, from the lowest
to the highest, for the time which we then had, as
perswaded vs of the trueth of whatsoeuer he hath
written concerning the same; and giues vs withall
much assurance of a very great blessing to be hoped
for, both to Church and Common-wealth in all places
for which he hath trauelled, by these his happie La∣bours
rightly put in practise: which all well-willers
to Religion and Learning are to wish to their Coun∣trey,
and by all meanes to promote, for the good of
the present and of all succeeding ages.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>IAMES VSSHER Doctour and Professor
of Diuinitie in the Vniuersitie of <HI>Dublin.</HI></SIGNED>
<SIGNED>DANIEL FEATLY Doctour of Diuinity,
and Chaplin in house to his Grace of
<HI>Canterburie.</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
<PB REF="51"/>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

