<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Virginia's God be thanked, or A sermon of thanksgiving for the happie successe of the affayres in Virginia this last yeare. Preached by Patrick Copland at Bow-Church in Cheapside, before the Honorable Virginia Company, on Thursday, the 18. of Aprill 1622. And now published by the commandement of the said honorable Company. Hereunto are adjoyned some epistles, written first in Latine (and now Englished) in the East Indies by Peter Pope, an Indian youth, borne in the bay of Bengala, who was first taught and converted by the said P.C. And after baptized by Master Iohn Wood, Dr in Divinitie, in a famous assembly before the Right Worshipfull, the East India Company, at S. Denis in Fan-Church streete in London, December 22. 1616</TITLE><AUTHOR>Copland, Patrick, ca. 1570-ca. 1655.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A19313</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">STC 5727</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC S105066</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99840796</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99840796</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">5330</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A19313)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5330)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1133:06)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Virginia's God be thanked, or A sermon of thanksgiving for the happie successe of the affayres in Virginia this last yeare. Preached by Patrick Copland at Bow-Church in Cheapside, before the Honorable Virginia Company, on Thursday, the 18. of Aprill 1622. And now published by the commandement of the said honorable Company. Hereunto are adjoyned some epistles, written first in Latine (and now Englished) in the East Indies by Peter Pope, an Indian youth, borne in the bay of Bengala, who was first taught and converted by the said P.C. And after baptized by Master Iohn Wood, Dr in Divinitie, in a famous assembly before the Right Worshipfull, the East India Company, at S. Denis in Fan-Church streete in London, December 22. 1616</TITLE><AUTHOR>Copland, Patrick, ca. 1570-ca. 1655.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Pope, Peter, fl. 1622.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[6], 36, [8] p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed by I[ohn] D[awson] for William Sheffard and Iohn Bellamie, and are to be sold at his shop at the two Grey-hounds in Corne-hill, neere the Royall Exchange,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1622.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Printer's name from STC.</NOTE><NOTE>The epistles by Peter Pope, with caption title "To the most illustrious knight, Sir Thomas Smith ..", have separate register. They include the Latin originals.</NOTE><NOTE>The last leaf is blank.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Sermons, English.</TERM><TERM>Virginia --  History --  Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775 --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2000-00</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2001-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>SPi Global</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2002-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP Staff (Oxford)</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2002-05</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Emma (Leeson) Huber</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2002-06</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A19313">
<STC T="S">5727</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99840796</BIBNO>
<VID>5330</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT>
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<P><PB REF="1"/>VIRGINIA'S God be Thanked, OR A SERMON OF THANKSGIVING FOR THE HAPPIE successe of the affayres in VIRGINIA this last yeare. Preached by PATRICK COPLAND at <HI>Bow</HI>-Church in <HI>Cheapside,</HI> before the Honorable VIRGINIA COMPANY, on Thursday, the 18. of <HI>Aprill</HI> 1622. And now published by <HI>the Commandement of the said hono∣rable</HI> COMPANY. Hereunto are adjoyned some Epistles, written first in Latine (and now Englished) in the East Indies by <HI>Peter Pope,</HI> an Indian youth, borne in the bay of <HI>Bengala,</HI> who was first taught and converted by the said <HI>P. C.</HI> And after bap∣tized by Master <HI>Iohn Wood,</HI> D<SUP>r</SUP> in Divinitie, <HI>in a famous Assembly before the Right Worshipfull, the East India Company,</HI> at S. <HI>Denis</HI> in Fan-Church streete in <HI>London,</HI> December 22. 1616.</P>
<P><HI>LONDON</HI> Printed by <HI>I. D.</HI> for <HI>William Sheffard</HI> and <HI>Iohn Bellamie,</HI> and are to be sold at his shop at the two Grey∣hounds in Corne-hill, neere the <HI>Royall Exchange.</HI> 1622.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>TO THE RIGHT NOBLE AND HO∣NORABLE EARLES, BARONS, And Lords; And to the right worshipfull <HI>Knights, Marchants,</HI> and <HI>Gentlemen,</HI> Adven∣turers for the Plantation in VIRGINIA; all happinesse, externall, internall, and eternall in Christ Iesus our blessed SAVIOVR.</HEAD>
<P>AFter I had discharged the charge laid vp∣on me by your Ho∣nourable and Wor∣shipfull Court; and was presently after, sollicited by some of your Honourable Societie, to present to the eye, what I had deliuered to the eare.
<PB REF="3"/>
Though at first, I was indeed very vnwil∣ling, at their intreatie: yet, being com∣manded by your Honourable Court to publish what before you had intreated mee to Preach; and weighing well with my selfe, that words spoken, are soone come, soone gone; but that written withall, they make a deeper impre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ion: for, by striking as well the Eye of the Reader, as the Eare of the Hearer, they peirce his heart the better, and saue his soule the sooner. Hereupon, that I might testifie how much I honour your lawful Commandements; and withall, that I might confirme with my Pen that grace, which it pleased God to worke by my Voyce; I haue now yeelded to all of your Requests, making that common to all, which then was imparted but to some: onely in desire some way to witnesse my dutifull respect <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o your Honourable Court, and loue to your Noble Plantati∣on. For, seeing many of your Noble and worthy Company haue spent a great part of their painefully gained estates vp∣on this honourable Action; and reioyce
<PB REF="3"/>
in nothing more then in this, that God hath giuen them a price in their hand, and a heart to vse it for the furthering of this glorious Worke; How could I, at so ear∣nest intreatie, refuse to adventure this Mite of mine, among so many worthie Adventures of theirs? How could I (I say) refuse to make their publique <HI>Bountie,</HI> and your publique <HI>Thankesgiuing,</HI> yet more publique?</P>
<P>If your Honours will be pleased to take in good part what now I impart; it may proue a spurre vnto me, to vndertake some bet<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er piece of seruice for the good of your noble Plantation; at least, if it lie in my poore power to bring it to passe. Thus intreating your Honours fauoura∣ble acceptance, I rest</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE>London <DATE>this 22 of <HI>May.</HI> 1622.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><HI>In all humble dutie to be commanded</HI> P. C.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="4"/>
<PB N="1" REF="4"/>
<HEAD>Virginia's God be thanked.</HEAD>
<Q><LG>
<HEAD><BIBL>Psalme, 107. verse. 23.</BIBL></HEAD>
<L>They that goe downe to the Sea in Ships, and occupie in the great waters;</L>
<L N="24">24. They see the workes of the Lord, and his wonders in the deepe:</L>
<L N="25">25. For hee commandeth, and raiseth the stormie winde, and it lifteth vp the waues thereof.</L>
<L N="26">26. They mount vp to the heaven, and descend to the deepe; so that their soule melteth for trouble:</L>
<L N="27">27 They are tossed too and fro, and stagger like a drunken man, and all their cunning is gone.</L>
<L N="28">28. Then they cry vnto the Lord in their trouble; and hee bringeth them out of their distresse.</L>
<L N="29">29. He turneth the storme to a calme, so that the waues thereof are still.</L>
<L N="30">30. When they are quieted they are glad; and he brin∣geth them to the haven where they would be.</L>
<L N="31">31. Let them therefore confesse before the Lord, his loving kindnesse; and his wonderfull workes be∣fore the sonnes of men.</L>
<L N="32">32. And let them exalt him in the Congregation of the people, &amp; prayse him in the Assembly of the Elders.</L>
</LG></Q>
<P>THE occasion of our present mee∣ting (Right Honorable, Right Worshipfull, and dearely belo∣ved in our Lord Iesus Christ) is to celebrate the goodnes of our
<PB N="2" REF="5"/>
good and gracious God, &amp; to giue him publique and solemne prayses for the sa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e arriving of your Fleete of 9. Sayle of Ships in <HI>Virginia,</HI> in <HI>Novem∣ber,</HI> and <HI>December</HI> last: And for the happie (yea, and in a maner miraculous) landing o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> 800. peo∣ple M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n, Women, and children, all in health: As also for the hopeful and good successe, where∣with Almightie God hath crowned your Colo∣ny in that Heathen-now Christian Kingdome.</P>
<P>This Taske being layd vpon me (the vnwor∣thi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st of many, who could and would haue per∣formed it better) I haue endevoured to discharge, according to the scantling of time, and measure of grace vouchsafed vnto mee.</P>
<P>The Prophet in this Psalme, magnifying the Providence of God, against all prophane Epi∣cures, and carnall Worldlings (who ascribe all <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hings, either to blinde Fortune; or their owne Industrie) setteth downe foure kindes of men, which are most indebted vnto God for delive∣rance from Dangers: The first is of those, who in their Iourney by land haue escaped a Dearth, from the first verse to the tenth. The Second, is of Prisoners inlarged and set at libertie, from the tenth verse, to the seaventeenth. The Third, is of such, as are freed from a desperate and mor∣tall Sicknesse, from the 17. verse to the 23. The Last, is of Mariners, Saylers, and Sea-faring men; who haue escaped a storme, and haue got into the wished haven, from the 23. verse to the 33.</P>
<P>This last part, being the Text appoynted for my present discourse; I haue for my better pro∣ceeding
<PB N="3" REF="5"/>
in it; and your Memories sake, reduced to these three heads, A <HI>Danger,</HI> A <HI>Deliverance,</HI> A <HI>Dutie.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>Danger</HI> is set downe verse, 25.26.27. (for the other two verses, are but as it were, an Intro∣duction into it) <HI>for hee commaundeth, and raiseth the stormie winds &amp;c.</HI> The <HI>Deliv<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rance</HI> from the Danger is set forth by the <HI>Meanes</HI> that these Sea-faring men vse to bee freed from it, viz. faith<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ull and fervent Prayer vnto God, verse 28.29. 30. <HI>Then they cry vnto the Lord in their trouble &amp;c.</HI> The <HI>Dutie,</HI> is delivered verse 31. 32. <HI>Let them therefore confesse before the Lord his louing kindnesse &amp;c.</HI> To speake of these in order; the first thing wee haue to note is this, that <HI>Great is the Danger of Sea-faring men.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">D. Great is the danger of Sea-faring men.</NOTE> A liuely Image of their vncer∣taine and variable liues is heere set downe by the Prophet. And if we marke wel the comparison; It is next to famine, Imprisonment, and a dead∣ly Disease to be a Sea-man:<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Pittacus.</HI></NOTE> for as one sayth <HI>Na∣vigantes ne{que} inter vivos, ne{que} inter mortuous. Saylers are neither amongst the living, nor yet amongst the dead:</HI> as having but a few inches of planke be∣tweene them and Death, they hang betweene both; ready to offer vp their Soules to every flaw of wind, and billow of water wherein they are tossed. The immoveable rocks, and the mu∣table windes; the ouerflowing waters, and swal∣lowing sands; the tempestuous stormes, &amp; spoy∣ling Pyrats haue their liues at their mercy and commaund. Mariners living in the Sea, almost as fishes, hauing the waters as their necessariest
<PB N="4" REF="6"/>
Element: are commonly men voyd of feare, ven∣trous and contemners of dangers: yet when God on a sudden commandeth a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>orme, and sitteth himselfe in the mouth of the tempest: when their Ship is foundred with water vnder them; when Life and Soule are readie to shake hands, and de∣part this present world; then, euen these nought-fearing fellowes, these high stomaked men trem∣ble for feare like faint-hearted women that shrink at euery stirre in a wherrie on the River of <HI>Thames</HI> in a rough and boysterous Tyde: or like vnto a yong Souldier, which starteth at the shooting off of a Gun.</P>
<P>I remember what <HI>Aeschi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es</HI> spak of <HI>Demosthenes</HI> at <HI>Rhodes</HI> when he read the Defence that <HI>Demost∣henes</HI> had framed to his Accusation; the people wondring at the strength and validitie of it. <HI>Quid si ipsam andissetis bestiam sua verba pronu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cia<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tem<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> What would you haue tho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ght</HI> (sayd he) <HI>if you had heard the Beast</HI> (for so hee speaketh disgracefully of <HI>Demosthenes</HI>) <HI>pronouncing it with his owne mouth?</HI></P>
<P>You wonder at the hearing of the dangerous storme, described here by the Prophet; but what would you say, if you had seene it your selues with your owne eyes? <HI>Ionah,</HI> a Sea-faring man, when he writeth of the storme wherein he was; his pen wrote nothing so effectually, as his heart felt: and being the Scribe and Orator onely, hee is nothing so fluent and copious as when he is the Patient. The stile of his history is simple &amp; plaine <HI>Ionah prayed v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>to the Lord his God out of the belly of the fish.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Ionah 1. 1.</NOTE> What one word therein is loftie and mag∣nificent,
<PB N="5" REF="6"/>
and lifted aboue the common course of speech? But the stile of <HI>Ionah</HI> himselfe speaking from a sense and feeling of his owne woes, is full of Ornament and Maiestie, full of tr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nslated and varied phrases, as if a sentence of ordinarie termes were not sufficient to expresse his extraordinarie woes: for being in Affliction, and in the danger it selfe;<NOTE PLACE="marg">verse 2.</NOTE> it is not sayd as before that he <HI>prayed,</HI> but that he <HI>cryed, praying</HI> is turned into <HI>crying</HI>; not from the <HI>belly of the fish,</HI> but fro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the <HI>belly of hell:</HI> a maru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ilous transformation: And the trouble he speaketh of,<NOTE PLACE="marg">verse 3.</NOTE> is said to be <HI>a casting of him into the bottome of the midst of the Sea</HI>; and <HI>a compassing of him about with flouds, surges &amp; waues,</HI> which went ouer and ouer his head: Nay,<NOTE PLACE="marg">verse 5.</NOTE> <HI>a compassing about of his soule,</HI> and a <HI>very melting of it for tro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ble,</HI> as heere in this Psal. verse 26. and <HI>a wrapping about of his head with weedes,</HI> and <HI>a going downe vnto the bottome of the Mountaines.</HI> Let the Scriptures bee throughly searched againe and againe, from the beginning of <HI>Genesis,</HI> to the end of the <HI>Revelation</HI>; and wee shall hardly meete with the like descrip∣tion of Misery, so emphatically and pathetically set out as this of Sea-faring men, set downe both in that second Chapter of <HI>Ionah,</HI> and in this 107. Psalme.</P>
<P>The miseries of <HI>Iob,</HI> you all know how vehe∣ment they were, and he neuer more kind<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ly ex∣pressed them then by this translation. <HI>Am I a Sea, or a Whale-fish that thou keepest me in ward?</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Iob 7.12.</NOTE></P>
<P>Will you yet see the great danger of Sea men, I will leade you along to weigh it by an experi∣ence
<PB N="6" REF="7"/>
and tryal of mine own, In a <HI>Typhoon,</HI> or cruel tempest that I met with off of the Islands of <HI>Mac∣qa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> adioyning to the Continent of <HI>Chyna.</HI> In this <HI>Typhoon</HI> or storme, our goodly <HI>Vnicorne</HI> (a ship of 800<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nne) was cast away vpon the Continent of <HI>Chyna;</HI> but all the people (blessed be God) saued; and though at their first landing vpon the <HI>Chyna</HI> shore, they were rifled by some of the baser <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ort of the <HI>Chynae<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>;</HI> yet vpon the comming of the <HI>Mandarins,</HI> or Governours, they had good entertainement of dyet &amp; house-roome for their mony, and were very kindly vsed by those of bet∣ter note. In this Tempest wee lost also our <HI>Pin∣nace,</HI> with 24 or 30 men in her which we had sent before vs to <HI>Firando</HI> (an Island adioyning to <HI>Ia∣pan</HI>) to giue notice of our comming, of whom we never heard newes: wee cut off our long Boate, and let her goe; we sunke our Shallop with two men in her, who were swallowed vp by the waues. Such was this Storme, as if <HI>Ionah</HI> had been flying vnto <HI>Tharshish.</HI> The ayre was beclouded, the hea∣vens were obscured, and made an Egyptian night of fiue or sixe dayes perpetuall horror: The ex∣perience of our Sea-men was amased; the skil of our Mariners was confounded; our <HI>Royal Iames</HI> most violently and dangerously leaked; &amp; those which pumped to keepe others from drowning, were halfe drowned themselues with continuall pumping. But God that heard <HI>Ionah</HI> crying out of the belly of Hell; and who, heere is sayd <HI>to turne a storme into a calme</HI>; hee pitied the distres∣ses of his servants; hee hushed the Tempest, and
<PB N="7" REF="7"/>
brought vs safely to <HI>Firando,</HI> our wished Haven. O that the Tempest of <HI>Macqau</HI> may never out of my minde, but that this wonderfull Delive∣rance and al other Gods mercies, may stil be iog∣ging mee at the elbow, and putting me in minde to <HI>confesse before the Lord his loving kindnesse, and his wonderfull workes before the Sonnes of men</HI>; that I may <HI>exalt him in the congregation of the people, and prayse him in the Assemblie of the Elders.</HI></P>
<P>But you will say, what needeth all this Dis∣course, touching the Danger of Sea-men; we are met together for another purpose, to giue thanks vnto God?</P>
<P>Beloued, I doe confesse indeed it is so, that the end of our present meeting is for <HI>Thankesgiuing.</HI> But how can wee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er be feelingly thankfull, as we should in word and deed, if wee know not the Danger wherein wee are, and the Deliverance vouchsafed vnto vs? Will not the true knowledge and deepe consideration of these, make vs put so many the more thankes into our Sacrifice of Prayse?</P>
<P>Wherefore I beseech you to take to heart, first, the Danger of your people in their passages both to <HI>Virginia,</HI> and after their landing. Secondly, the Danger of your whole Colony there. Thirdly, The Danger of your selues here at home. And left others, that are not of your Honourable Company, may thinke this point impertinent to them; Let all of vs consider the Dangers wherein we were, and still are; and the many Deliverances vouchsafed vnto vs (for I must intreat you to giue
<PB N="8" REF="8"/>
me leaue to joyne Danger and Deliverance toge∣ther, for the better stirring of you vp vnto your dutie.) And then I doubt not, but all of vs shall haue cause to <HI>confesse before the Lord his louing kindnesse, and his wonderfull workes before the sonnes of men.</HI></P>
<P>And first, to touch the Danger of your people, both in their passage to <HI>Virginia,</HI> and after their landing there, may I not say in the words of <HI>Iob,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Iob 16.3.4.</NOTE> <HI>Will yee giue the words of him that is afflicted to the winde?</HI> As if he had said, when affliction it selfe, and the inmost sorrowes of my heart tell my tale, will you not regard it? <HI>O that your soules were in my soules stead,</HI> that you felt as much sorrow as I doe: <HI>L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>quor in angustia mea; quer<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r in amaritudine animae mea,</HI> I speake that that I speake from a world of trouble; I make my complaint in the bitternesse of my soule. Surely, if some hundreds of those that mis-carried in the infancie, and at the first beginning of your Plantation, (which is excee∣dingly bettered within these 2. yeeres) were now aliue, I thinke they would speake no otherwise than <HI>Iob</HI> spake<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>Wil you giue the words of thē that are afflicted to the winde?</HI> Will ye not beleeue in what Danger we were,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Summer I∣lands.</NOTE> when some of vs made Ship∣wracke vpon the supposed inchanted <HI>Ilands</HI>; when others of vs encountred with bloudie ene∣mies in the West Indies; when many of vs dyed by the way; and when those that were left aliue, some perished a shore, for want of comfortable prouisions, and looking vnto, and others were killed with the Bowes and Arrows of the Savages
<PB N="9" REF="8"/>
vpon our first landing there? I presume, I speake to melting hearts of flesh, as tenderly sensible of your brethrens woe, as heartily thankful for your owne good.</P>
<P>And now, beloued, since the case is altered, that all difficulties are swallowed vp: And seeing, first, there is no danger by the way; neither through encountring of enemy, or Pyrate; nor meeting with rockes, or Sholes (all which to Sea-faring men are very dangerous, and from all which your Ships and people are farre remoued, by reason of their faire and safe passage through the maine Ocean) nor through the tediousnesse of the passage; the fittest season of the yeare for a speedie passage, being now farre better knowne then before; and by that meanes the passage it selfe made almost in so many weekes, as formerly it was wont to be made in moneths; which I con∣ceiue to be, through the blessing of God, the maine cause of the safe arriuall of your last Fleete of nine Sayle of Ships, that not one (but one, in whose roome there was another borne) of eight hundred, which were transported out of <HI>England</HI> and <HI>Ireland</HI> for your Plantation, should miscarry by the way; whereas in your former voyages scarce 80. of a 100. arrived safely in <HI>Virginia.</HI> And secondly, seeing there is no Danger after their landing, either through <HI>warres,</HI> or <HI>famine,</HI> or <HI>want of conuenient lodging, and looking too,</HI> through which many miscarried heretofore; for, blessed be God, there hath beene a long time, and still is a happie league of Peace and Amitie soundly concluded,
<PB N="10" REF="9"/>
and faithfully kept, betweene the <HI>English</HI> and the <HI>Natiues,</HI> that the feare of killing each other is now vanished away. Besides, there is now in your Plantation plentie of good and wholesome pro∣visions for the strength and comfort, not onely of the Colony, but also of all such as after their pas∣sage doe land ashore. There is also convenient lodging, and carefull attendance provided for them, till they can provide for themselues; and a faire Inne for receiuing and harbouring of Strangers, erecting in <HI>Iames</HI> Cittie; to the setting vp of which, both your worshipfull Governour, Sir <HI>Francis Wyat,</HI> and your worthie Treasurer, Master <HI>George Sands</HI> doe write, that they doubt not, but there will be raised betweene fifteene hundred and two thousand pounds; to which euery man contributeth cheerefully and bounti∣fully; they being all free-hearted, and open-han∣ded to all publique good workes. Seing, I say, that now all former difficulties (which much hin∣dered the progresse of your noble Plantation) are removed, and in a maner ouercome: And that your people in your Colony (through Gods mercy) were all in good health, euery one busied in their Vocations, as Bees in their Hiues, at the setting sayle of your Ship the <HI>Concord</HI> from <HI>Vir∣ginia</HI> in March last. O what miracles are these? O what cause haue you and they to <HI>confesse before the Lord his louing kindnesse, and his wonderfull workes before the sonnes of men?</HI></P>
<P>But to passe from the Danger and deliverance of your people, who indangered, yea, lost their
<PB N="11" REF="9"/>
liues in setling of your Plantation, consider, I be∣seech you, in the second place, the Danger where∣in your whole Colony stood, at the time of Sir <HI>Thomas Gates</HI> arriving in <HI>Virginia</HI> from the <HI>Sum∣mer Ilands,</HI> when it was concluded a few dayes af∣ter his landing, by himselfe, Sir <HI>George Summers,</HI> Captaine <HI>Newport,</HI> and the whole Counsell, by the generall approbation of all, to abandon the Colony (because of the want of provisions) and to make for <HI>New-found-land,</HI> and so for <HI>England.</HI> And will not the hopefull setling of your Colo∣ny there, now vnder the Government of a worthy and worshipfull Commander; and a wise and wel-experienced Counsell, stirre you vp to <HI>con∣fesse before the Lord his louing kindnesse, and his won∣derfull workes before the sonnes of men?</HI></P>
<P>But, if neither the Danger of your people; nor the Danger of your whole Colony abroad, and the Deliverance vouchsafed to them both be e∣nough to stirre you vp to confesse before the Lord his louing kindnesse: Then I beseech you, in the third place, to consider the Danger of your owne selues here at home. What masse of money haue you buried in that Plantation? How many of you had it not made to wish that you had ne∣uer put your hand to this Plough? Nay, how ma∣ny of you had it not made to shrinke in your shoulders; and to sinke (as it were) vnder the burden, and to be quite out of hope for euer see∣ing penny of that you had so largely depursed?</P>
<P>And now, Beloued, is not the case altered? Are not your hopes great of seeing; nay, of feeling,
<PB N="12" REF="10"/>
within a few yeares of double, treble; yea, I may say of tensold for one? Doe not all of you know what that Religious and judicious Overs<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er of your Colledge lands there writeth vnto you from thence?<NOTE PLACE="marg">Master <HI>George Thorpe</HI> in his Letter written from <HI>Iames</HI> Citie <HI>May</HI> 17. 1621.</NOTE> <HI>No man</HI> (sayth he) <HI>can iustly say, that this Country is not capable of all those good things, that you in your wisedomes, with your great charge haue pro∣jected, both for her wealth and honour: and also of all other good things, that the most opulent parts of Chri∣stendome doe afford; neither are wee hopelesse, that this Country may also yeeld things of better value then any of those</HI>? And surely, by that which I haue heard and seene abroad in my travailing to <HI>India</HI> and <HI>Iapan,</HI> I am confirmed in the truth of that which he doth write. for <HI>Iapan,</HI> lying in the same latitude that <HI>Virginia</HI> doth; and if there be any ods, <HI>Virginia</HI> hath them, as lying more Southerly then <HI>Iapan</HI> doth: <HI>Iapan</HI> (I say) lying vnder the same latitude that <HI>Virginia</HI> doth, aboundeth with all things for <HI>profit</HI> and <HI>pleasure,</HI> being one of the mightiest and opulentest Empires in the world, hauing in it many rich Mines of Gold and Siluer.</P>
<P>And had you not a taste of some Marchantable Commodities sent vnto you from <HI>Virginia</HI> some yeeres agoe, whilest that worshipfull and worthy Gouernour, Sir <HI>Thomas Dale</HI> sent home vnto you samples of aboue a dossen severall good Com∣modities from thence? Haue you not now great hopes of abundance of Corne, Wine, Oyle, Lem∣mons, Oranges, Pomegranats, and all maner of fruites pleasant to the eye, and wholesome for the belly? And of plentie of Silke, Silke Grasse,
<PB N="13" REF="10"/>
Cotton-wooll, Flax, Hempe &amp;c. for the backe? Are not you already possessed with rich Mines of Copper and Yron, and are not your hopes great of farre richer Minerals?<NOTE PLACE="marg">Master <HI>George Sandes</HI> in his Letter written from <HI>Iames</HI> Citie <HI>March</HI> 3. 1621.</NOTE> Haue you not read what of late your worthie Treasurer doth write vnto you? <HI>If</HI> (sayth hee) <HI>wee ouercome this yeere the Yron-workes, Glasse-workes, Salt-works; take order for the plentifull setting of Corne; restraine the quantitie of Tobacco, and mend it in the qualitie, plant Vines, Mulbery-trees, Fig-trees, Pomegranats, Potatoes, Cotton woolles; and erect a faire Inne in Iames Citie (to the setting vp of which, I doubt not but wee shall raise fifteene hundred or two thousand pounds: for every man giues willingly towards this and other publique workes) you haue enough for this yeere.</HI></P>
<P>And a little after, in the same letter<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Maister <HI>Pory deserues good incouragement for his paineful Discove∣ries to the South-ward, as far as the Choanoack, who although he hath trod on a litle good ground, hath past through great forests of Pynes</HI> 15. <HI>or</HI> 16. <HI>myle broad and aboue</HI> 60. <HI>mile long, which will serue well for Masts for Shipping, and for pitch and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>arre, when we shall come to extend our plantatiōs to those borders. On the other side of the River there is a fruitfull Coun∣trie blessed with aboundance of Corne, reaped twise a yeere: aboue which is the Copper Mines, by all of all places generally affirmed. Hee hath also met with a great deale of silke grasse which growes there monethly</HI> of which Maister <HI>Harriot,</HI> hath affirmed in print many yeeres agoe, that it will make silke Grow-graines<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> and of which and Cotten woll all the
<PB N="14" REF="11"/>
<HI>Cambaya</HI> and <HI>Bengala</HI> stuffes are made in the East Indies.</P>
<P>Heard you not with your owne eares what M. <HI>Iohn Martin</HI> an <HI>Armenian</HI> by birth (that hath lived now 6. or 7. yeeres in <HI>Virginia,</HI> and is but very lately come from thence, and purposeth (as all others that are lately come ouer, who also farre preferre <HI>Virginia</HI> to <HI>England</HI>) to returne thither againe, with this resolution, there to liue and die) said in the audience of your whole Court the 8<SUP>th</SUP> of this Instant? <HI>I haue travailed</HI> (said he) <HI>by Land over eighteene severall kingdomes; and yet all of them in my minde, come farre short of</HI> Virginia, <HI>both for temperature of ayre, and fertilitie of the soyle.</HI> All this throughly considered, O how great cause haue you to <HI>confesse before the Lord his louing kind∣nesse, and his wonderfull workes before the sonnes of men</HI>?</P>
<P>And that all of vs here present may confesse before the Lord his louing kindnesse, and his wonderfull workes before the sonnes of men; Let vs take to heart our private, our publique Dangers and deliverances: from how many Dan∣gers eminent and imminent hath the Lord deli∣vered vs and our whole Land in eightie-eight; and in the <HI>Gun powder-Treason</HI>? Haue wee not then all of vs good cause to <HI>exalt the Lord in the Congregation of the people, and to prayse him in the Assembly of the Elders?</HI> Nay, haue not Elders and Yongers, and all good cause so to doe?</P>
<P>But, alas, I am afraid, that we haue forgotten the louing kindnesse of the Lord, and his won∣derfull
<PB N="15" REF="11"/>
Deliverances bestowed vpon vs. <HI>Beneficij memoria est brevissima</HI>; <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. May not <HI>England</HI> justly be charged with <HI>Is∣raels</HI> sinne, whose Prayers and Prayses ended so soone as they passed the red Sea? Amongst the Tribes, there was one named <HI>Manasse,</HI> which sig∣nifies, Forgetfulnes; I pray God the Tribes, euen the heads of our people forget it not; but that we and the whole Land, may <HI>confesse before the Lord his louing kindnesse, and his wonderfull workes be∣fore the sonnes of men; and se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke to exalt him in the Congregation of the people, and to prayse him in the Assembly of the Elders.</HI></P>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<Q><BIBL>Verse 28.</BIBL> Then they cryed vnto the Lord in their trouble &amp;c.</Q>
<P>THus having spoken of the Danger, I come now to speake a word of the Deliverance, and the meanes which these Sea-faring men vsed to be freed from their trouble, which is faithfull &amp; fervent Prayer, <HI>Then they cryed vnto the Lord, &amp;c.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Faithfull and fervent Prayer vnto God,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">D. There is no daunger so great, out of which faithful and fervent prayer will not helpe a man.</NOTE> <HI>in the name of Iesus Christ, is a sure meanes to procure helpe in trouble, and to free vs from the greatest danger that is, or at least from the evill thereof.</HI> These Ma∣riners going vnto God, not with a cold and care∣lesse devotion; nor with a dombe Spirit: but with as earnest and impatient a voyce, as the af∣fection of their heart, and affliction of their bo∣dy could send forth: they thus crying vnto the
<PB N="16" REF="12"/>
Lord in their trouble; hee brought them out of their distresse, he hushed the storme: he brought them to the haven of their desire, &amp; made them glad at the heart. As <HI>David</HI> gaue charge to his Souldiers that they should not kill <HI>Absolom</HI> his Sonne, though hee sent them against <HI>Absolom</HI> to stay his rebellion: So God forbids his crosses to destroy his children, though he send them a∣gainst his children, to purge out their corrupti∣ons. As <HI>Iohn</HI> after the voyce of Thunder heard the voyce of Harpers; so when the Saints haue heard the noyse of sorrow, they shall heare the sound of ioy. As the viper leapt vpon <HI>Paul,</HI> and leapt off againe: so troubles leape vpon the righ∣teous and leape off againe, as though they had mistaken the partie, and rapt at the wrong doore. One calleth Affliction the <HI>Trance</HI> of the righte∣ous, because they seeme dead for a while, but they wake againe.</P>
<P>Now all this commeth to passe, because the Lord sendeth the Spirit of Prayer into the hearts of his Children, whereby they cry vnto him in the time of their trouble, and there∣fore no marveile, <HI>when they cry vnto the Lord in their trouble,</HI> that <HI>he bringeth them out of their di∣stresse.</HI></P>
<P>The most ef<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ctuall spe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ch to the secret eares of God commeth not from wordes, but from sighes and grones: he that heareth without eares can interpret our prayers without our tongues<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> hee that saw and fancied <HI>Nathaniel</HI> vnder the fig-tree, before he was called, hee that saw and san∣ctified
<PB N="17" REF="12"/>
<HI>Iohn Bap<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ist</HI> in his mothers wombe before hee came forth, he s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eth, and blesseth our prai∣ers fervently conceived in the bosome of our Consciences before they be vttered. But if they be faint and faithlesse,<NOTE PLACE="marg">1 King. 18. 26<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> 27. &amp;c.</NOTE> they shall be answ<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>red of God, as the Prayers of <HI>Baals</HI> Priests were, who though they cried lowd <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rom morning to noone, and to the offering vp of the euening Sacrifice; and cut themselues till the bloud gushed out vp∣on them, yet there was none to heare, nor to re∣gard their roarings.</P>
<P>Giue therefore but thy prayer a voyce to cry: for, it must not be dumbe, nor tong-tied; giue it an eye to seeke: for, it must not be wandring and carelesse; and giue it an hand to knocke: for, it must not feare to molest and disquiet; and not onely shalt thou bee freed from Dangers, but the doores, yea, all the treasures and jew∣els of the kingdome of Heaven shall be open vn∣to it.</P>
<P>But some, it may be, will say, My danger is great; yea, so great that it maketh my heart to ake within me, and my soule to melt for sor∣row.</P>
<P>I answere, the greatnesse of our Danger cannot be a stop to our Deliverance; If we can but call and cry vnto the Lord in our trouble, Hee will bring vs out of our Distresse. The Sea-faring men here described, had their hearts to melt for sor∣row, yet <HI>crying vnto the Lord in their trouble, He brought them out of their distresse?</HI> The word here translated, <HI>Distresse,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Vmimmits∣kothebem.</HI></NOTE> is by <HI>Arias Montanus</HI> tran∣slated
<PB N="18" REF="13"/>
<HI>de coarctationibus</HI>; and by <HI>Iunius</HI> and <HI>Tre∣mellius, ex angustijs.</HI> So that the trouble here spo∣ken of, is not properly trouble, but <HI>narrownes</HI> &amp; <HI>straights.</HI> Be our case then never so desperate, the Lord can helpe it: for, nothing is vnpossible to him. The <HI>Israelites</HI> groaned vnto him in <HI>E∣gypt,</HI> he heard and deliuered them from the ty∣rannie of <HI>Pharaoh</HI>: The yong men in the Fierie Furnace called vpon him, and were deliuered: The cry of <HI>Daniel</HI> stopped the mouth of the roa∣ring Lyons; <HI>Paul</HI> and <HI>Silas</HI> being in bonds, pray∣ed, and their chaynes fell loose from them; the doores opened and gaue them passage. Although wee be plunged never so low, that we know not where to seeke, nor where to finde; although the floods of troubles runne cleane ouer and o∣uer vs; in so much that we seeme to our selues past helpe and recovery; yet are we not indeede past helpe, so long as we are not past desire to be holpen. Men indeed are altogether amazed, and in a maner bereft of wit and vnderstanding, when they feele themselues dangerously tossed too and fro, as here these Sea-faring men did; but <HI>when they cried in their trouble vn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o the Lord, he brought them out of their distresse.</HI> There was neuer af∣fliction so great, but the hand of the Lord hath beene able to master it; There was ne∣uer storme so fierce, but his power hath beene able to allay it. Therefore, if out soules doe e∣uen melt for trouble within vs; wee must not take discomfort at it. The lord sitteth aboue the water-Floods; the Lord commandeth the
<PB N="19" REF="13"/>
Sea, and all that is therein; the Lord that turneth the storme to a calme (blessed be his name, and let the might of his Maiesty receiue honour for euer∣more) hee will neuer forsake his children that crie vnto him; neither in health nor sickenes, light nor darkenesse, stormes nor calmes; in the land of the liuing, nor in the land of forgetfulnes. Therefore, let vs resolue with holy <HI>Dauid,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Psal. 23.4.</NOTE> <HI>Though I should walke thorow the valley of the shadow of death, I will feare no euill.</HI> I will feare <HI>no euill</HI> (saith <HI>Dauid</HI>) neither great nor small: for it is all one with God to deliuer from the greater stormes, aswell as from the lesser. Some difference there is indeed of <HI>Dangers</HI> and <HI>Deliueran∣ces</HI> out of them, but it is only such as in Books prin∣ted on large and lesse letter and paper, the matter not varying at all; for example. Whē God brought some of the ships of your former fleetes to <HI>Virginia</HI> in safty; here Gods prouidence was seen &amp; felt pri∣uately by some; and this was a deliuerance, written (as it were) in <HI>quarto</HI> on a lesser paper &amp; letter. But now, when God brought all of your 9. ships, and al your people in thē in health &amp; safety to <HI>Virginia:</HI> Yea and that ship <HI>Tyger</HI> of yours, which had fallen into the hands of the Turkish men of war, through tempest and contrary windes, she not being able to beare sayle, and by that meanes drouen out of her course some hundreds of miles: for otherwise of it selfe the passage from <HI>England</HI> to <HI>Virginia,</HI> is out of the walke of Turkes, and cleere and safe from all Pyrates, who commonly lurke neere Ilands, and head-lands, and not in the maine Ocean. When this your <HI>Tyger</HI> had falne, by reason of this storme,
<PB N="20" REF="14"/>
and some indiscretion of her M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ster and people, who taking the Turkes to haue beene Flemmings, bound for <HI>Holland</HI> or <HI>England,</HI> bore vp the helme to speake with them: for they needed not if they had listed to haue come neere the Turkes, but haue proceeded safely on their voyage) into the hands of those mercilesse Turkes, who had taken from them most of their victuals, and all of their seruice∣able sayles, tackling and anchors, and had not so much as left them an houre-glasse or compasse to steere their course, thereby vtterly disabling them from going from them, and proceeding on their voyage. When (I say) God had ransomed her out their hands,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Esa. 43.4.</NOTE> as the Prophet speaketh, by another Sayle which they espyed, and brought her likewise safely to <HI>Virginia</HI> with all her people, two English boyes onely excepted, for which the Turkes gaue them two others, a French youth and an Irish. Was not there the presence of God printed, as it were, in <HI>Folio</HI> on Royall Crowne Paper and Capi∣tall Letters, that, as <HI>Habacucke</HI> sayth,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Hab. 2.2.</NOTE> <HI>They that runne and ride post may reade it.</HI> O then how great cause haue you and they, <HI>to confesse before the Lord his lo∣uing kindnesse, and his wonderfull workes before the sonnes of men?</HI></P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="part">
<PB N="21" REF="14"/>
<Q><BIBL>Verse 31.32.</BIBL> Let them therefore confesse before the Lord, &amp;c.</Q>
<P>HItherto of the <HI>Danger</HI> and <HI>D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>liuerance</HI>; now of the <HI>Dutie,</HI> which, in a word, is thanksgiuing.</P>
<P><HI>The greater our danger i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>;</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">D. The more &amp; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>reater Gods blessings are vpō vs, the lar∣ger &amp; heartier ought our prayses and thanksgiuings be vnto God for the same.</NOTE> <HI>the more ioyfull is our de∣liuerance, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he more cheerfully ought wee to confesse before the Lord his louing kindnesse, and his wonder∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ull workes before the sonnes of men. Thanksgiuing is the end of our Deliuerance.</HI> This dutie carefully per∣formed, is a singular exercise of faith, when men standing vpon the shore, and beholding the dan∣gerous and tumultuous Seas which they haue pas∣sed, are stirred vp to sacrifice prayse and glory to him for the s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>me. <HI>Gen.</HI> 8.20. <HI>Exod.</HI> 15.1 <HI>Psal.</HI> 50.15. This seruice is a further worke of faith then peti∣tion: for they which are but illightned <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gainst death may serue in a sort to make some petitions to God; but they neuer bethinke them at-all of the dutie of thanksgiuing, when they haue recei∣ued benefits from him. And for this cause, nine of the ten leapers which Christ cleansed, are defamed to all posteritie by the Holy Ghost in the Gospel.</P>
<P>Let vs labour to purge our selues of such a wic∣kednesse, spending much of our time in songs of thanksgiuing, <HI>Confessing before the Lord his louing kindnesse, and his wonderfull workes before the sonnes of men.</HI> For thanksgiuing is, as it were, the homage or rent-charge, which wee are to returne to God for all his mercies, especially for our right to our inheritance in heauen. And wee know that if men refuse to do their homage, or pay their rent to
<PB N="22" REF="15"/>
their earthly Land-Lord, they shal deserue thereby to be turned out of their farmes, &amp; others to be put in their roome, which shall discharge the duty bet∣ter. So, if we proue vnthankfull to the Lord of hea∣uen, shall wee not iustly deserue to lose our inheri∣tance? Wherefore let vs doe as men, which are bound by bond to make tender of a sum of money vpon great penalty in a certaine place; and, at a cer∣taine time named in the bond, they will be sure to tender the paiment in the place, and at the time ap∣pointed and specified in the bond, lest they incurre the penaltie. Euen so, &amp;c. Let vs beware wee doe not forslow our thankfulnesse vpon light and slight excuses, lest we forfeit Gods louing kindnes, &amp; our owne saluation. Let vs weigh, what God hath done for vs, &amp; lay all Gods benefits together, thereby the be<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ter to sti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re vs vp vnto thankfulnes. <HI>Leah</HI> beareth one son, &amp; calleth his name <HI>Reuben</HI>; a second son, &amp; called his name <HI>Simeon,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Gen. 29.32. 33. &amp;c.</NOTE> and a third, and called him <HI>Leni</HI>; but when aboue exspectation she conceiueth, and beareth the fourth time, she purposely cals his name <HI>Iudah,</HI> &amp; expresly protests that she wil praise the Lord. If one benefit moue you not, many should if many haue not done it, yet this last &amp; late mercy passing all the former. O call it <HI>Iudah,</HI> &amp; now of set purpose praise the Lord, &amp; <HI>confesse before him his lo∣uing kindnesse and his wonderfull workes before the sonnes of men.</HI></P>
<P>Which that you may the better do, giue me leaue I pray you to shew you how your thanksgiuing ought to be qualified, that it may be a sweet sauour vnto God.</P>
<P><PB N="23" REF="15"/>It must be accompanied, 1. with <HI>confessi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.</HI> 2. with <HI>exalt<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tion. Confession</HI> againe, is either of <HI>Gods louing kindnes</HI>; or of his <HI>wonderfull workes.</HI></P>
<P>There are two things in which Gods louing kind∣nesse is to be seene, 1. In <HI>giuing.</HI> 2. In <HI>forgiuing.</HI></P>
<P>Gods louing kindnes in giuing, is to be praised: for is not God a great &amp; good benefactor or ours, and do wee not greatly praise our benefactors? O let vs confesse his louing kindnesse as he is our Be∣nefactor.</P>
<P>Gods louing kindnesse in forgiuing our sinnes is also to be confessed. I shewed you before the dan∣ger of your people sent to <HI>Virgini<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> the danger of your Colony planted there, and the danger of your owne selues here at home. And now if you looke to the Primitiue &amp; original cause of al these your great Dangers, and many dis-asters that haue heretofore befalne to your plantation, I suppose you shall soon find the cause to be sin. The Marriners in the tran∣sportation of <HI>Ionah,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Ionah<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> 1.7.</NOTE> made no question hereof. Let vs with these Marriners cast lots that wee may know for whose cause this euill came vpon your planta∣tion in <HI>Virginia.</HI></P>
<P>Was it for the sin of our land in generall, either because (as it is said of <HI>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></HI>) it came not out to helpe forward this worke of the Lord with their Prayers and Purses;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Iudg. 5.23.</NOTE> or was it because (as the Pro∣phet speaketh<NOTE PLACE="marg">Isay 1.5.</NOTE>,) <HI>The whole head is sicke, and the whole heart is heauy, from the sole of the foote to the crowne of the head, there is nothing whole therein, &amp;c.</HI> Surely, surely, the sinnes of our land are crying sinnes; and is it any wonder if they doe awake the
<PB N="24" REF="16"/>
Iustice of God, and turne the mercies of Heauen into roddes of Indignation? Or was it for the sinne of your owne society at home; because you haue eyther too much affected your gaine? or too too seldome called vpon the name of God in prayer for giuing his blessing to your plantati∣on? or too faintly depended vpon God by faith and patience for the issue? or too much neglected God in thankefulnesse for the successe? I can not excuse nor accuse you; you need not care to bee iudged by mans day:<NOTE PLACE="marg">1. Cor. 4:3<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></NOTE> your consciences can best tell you, whether the lot fall vppon you or not.</P>
<P>Or, was it for the sinne of such as you haue transported to your Plantation, because (most of them at the first, beeing the very scumme of the Land, and great pity it was that no better at that time could be had;) they neglected Gods wor∣ship, liued in idlenesse, plodded conspiracies, resisted the gouernment of Superiours, and ca∣ried themselues dissolutely amongst the heathens. If in any of these they haue offended, was not Gods rod of <HI>Mortalitie</HI> iustly vpon them for their sinnes?</P>
<P>But now (beloued) Almighty God hath graci∣ously looked vpon you and your people, in passing by their and your sins; The Lord hath sayd to the destroying angel,<NOTE PLACE="marg">2. Sam. 24.16.</NOTE> <HI>It is sufficient, hold now <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hy hand</HI>; the mortality of your people is ceased abroad: and the hope of your good returnes is increased at home: O <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>herefore, ought you not to <HI>confesse be∣fore the Lord his louing kindnes, both in giuing of mer∣cies, and forgiuing of sinnes?</HI></P>
<P><PB N="25" REF="16"/>Another confession there must be, of <HI>Gods won∣derfull workes.</HI> And both these confessions are a∣gaine and againe repeated in the amebe, burden or foote of this psalme.</P>
<P>It is most true,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ps<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l. 40.5. &amp; 66.3. &amp; 10 4. 24.</NOTE> that all <HI>Gods workes are wonder∣full</HI> (for he hath made them all in wisedome, in number, weight and measure) and that the Lord declareth himselfe to be great and wonderfull e∣uen in the least of them amongest the sonnes of men. This <HI>Pharaohs</HI> Inchanters did confesse, <HI>This is the finger of God,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Exod. 8.19.</NOTE> in the little lowse. But vnthank∣full man taketh no notice of ordinary fauours, common protection, health, plenty, rest, pleasure, which are vsuall with them, and therefore Gods name is not praised for them: for except Christ worke miracles, they will not beleeue;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Iohn 6.30.</NOTE> <HI>What signe</HI> (sayd the fleshly hearers of Christs word) <HI>shewest thou, that we may see it, and beleeue thee? What dost <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hou worke?</HI> No signe, no faith: yea except God do great things for them,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Psal. 147.20. Marke 2.12.</NOTE> that they may be able to say, that he hath not done so to any, and we neuer saw such a thing; they will not confesse his louing kindnesse, but rather smother both it, and his wonderfull workes.</P>
<P>Let vs therefore consider and weigh well the <HI>Wonderful workes</HI> of the Lord: for, is it not a work of wonder to command the creatures against the course of nature? as to cause the winde to cease with a word, and to quiet the Seas onely with a becke? To stay the fire that it doe not burne; and the hungry Lyons that they doe not deuoure? to mollifie the hearts of Saluages, and to make some
<PB N="26" REF="17"/>
of them voluntarily to remooue from their owne warme and well seated and peopled habitations, to giue place to Strangers, whom they had neuer before seene: as <HI>P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>whatan</HI> at the first plantation of the English, to remoue from his owne station, and now of late the <HI>Mattaw<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mbs</HI> to depart from their cleared and rich grounds; and to make others of them (as <HI>Opachancano</HI>) to sell to the English and their Gouernour sir <HI>George Yeardly</HI> the right and ti∣tle they had to their possessions? Yet all these hath the Lord done, and are they not wonderfull works indeed? O then let vs stir vp our selues and others, and call vpon them, saying,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Psal. 66.16.</NOTE> <HI>Come and hearken all yee that feare God, and I will tell you what the Lord hath done to my soule.</HI> O let vs <HI>confesse before the Lord,</HI> as <HI>his louing kindnesse,</HI> so also <HI>his wonderfull workes before the sonnes of men.</HI></P>
<P>But alas, I am afraid, that it is with vs concer∣ning Gods wonderfull workes, as it was with the people of the Iewes, concerning the wonders of Gods Law, of whom God by his Prophet com∣playneth;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Hosea 8.12.</NOTE> <HI>I haue written to them the great things of my Law, but they were accounted as a strange thing.</HI> God had vouchsafed to teach them the wonders of his word, what greater bounty? They passed by them, as things not worthy to be wondred at and regarded; what greater impiety? O that it were not with vs touching his wonderfull workes, as it was with them concerning the wonders of his law?</P>
<P>Our thankesgiuing, if it be good, must bee ac∣companied with <HI>exalting</HI> of the Lord. Now, to <HI>exalt</HI> the Lord none can properly be said to doe it;
<PB N="27" REF="17"/>
for who can exalt the Highest that exalteth all, and is exalted of none? To exalt the Lord then in the congregation of his people, is nothing else, but as <HI>Dauid</HI> expounds it,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Psal. 122.8.9.</NOTE> to wish prosperity vnto Gods Church, &amp; to procure the wealth of Gods people.</P>
<P>O then (beloued) would you haue God to accept of your thankes, and to giue a blessing to your Colony abroad, and your selues at home; stu∣die to wish well, and to doe well to Gods Church and people.</P>
<P>Labour first, to procure faithfull, honest, and peaceable Preachers, and send them ouer to your people (as you haue sent some already, both of good learning and sanctified life, and many more such may you send,) that they may <HI>Open their eies,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Act<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> 26.18.</NOTE> <HI>that they may turne from darknes to light; and from the power of Satan vnto God; that they may receiue forgiue∣nesse of sinnes, and an inheritance amongst them which are sanctified by faith in Christ.</HI> If you prouide not spiritual foode for your people, aswell as corporall, what better prouision make you, then you doe for your bruite beasts which feede in your pastures? Nay, do you make so good? For, hath not an Oxe therein what he needeth; but a man without this, is hee not left vnprouided of the farre better part, euen his Soule? Yea, and if you haue no care to prouide good Preachers for your people, but send ouer vnto them such as offer themselues hand ouer head; you prouide not well for your selues: for, what assurance can you haue of them, who haue no assurance of themselues? what seruice can you expect from them which perfourme none
<PB N="28" REF="18"/>
vnto Almightie God? will they euer be faithfull vnto you, that are vnfaithfull vnto him? And how can they bee faithfull vnto God, if they haue not faithfull Preachers to bring them vnto him? Surely, the best you can looke from them, is but eie-seruice, which how good this wil be, I leaue it to yourselues well to consider of, who haue felt the smart of it by your slow returnes. Nothing can cast a sure knot vpon the hearts of your people, but the true knowledge and feare of God: so as when you aduance religion, you aduance together with it your owne profit. The neglect of this hath made your hopes in your long looked for Returnes, to this houre to bee frustrate.<NOTE PLACE="marg">1. Sam. 6.11. Deut. 28.5. Hag. 1.19.30.</NOTE> <HI>Obed Ed<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m</HI> prospered the better for the Arke of God. The Iewes had no good harnest whilest they left off to build Gods Temple; and they amended in their estate when they amended that fault, and reformed themselues.</P>
<P>Amongst other of the causes, that it hath not pleased God to be succesfull vnto your Plantation at the beginning thereof, and in the infancy of the same. That worthy ouer-seer of your Colledge Lands before mentioned, giueth this as one; <HI>That you haue not as you ought</HI> (for these bee his very words) <HI>preferred Gods glory by your serious endea∣uo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rs of conuerting the Natiues, who</HI> (as he writeth) <HI>do liue so peaceably amongst vs, and round about vs, as they do euen seeme to groane vnder the burden of the bondage of Satan, and to want nothing but meanes to be deliuered.</HI> And this hee confirmeth by a di∣scourse which he had with <HI>Opachankan<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> their great King, who hath succeeded <HI>Powhatan,</HI> whose daugh∣ter
<PB N="29" REF="18"/>
<HI>Pokah<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ta<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> one maister <HI>Iohn Rolfe,</HI> an English Gentleman of good worth, married: for he found that the sayd <HI>Opachankano</HI> had more notions of religion in him, then could be imagined in so great a blindnesse, since he willingly acknowledged that theirs was not the right way, desiring to be instru∣cted in ours: And confessing that God loued vs more then them; and that he thought the cause of his anger against thē, was their custome of making their children Blacke-boyes, or consecrating them to Sathan. Hee found also that the sayd <HI>Opachan∣kan<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> had some knowledge of many of the fixed S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>arres, and had obserued the North Starre, and the course of the Constellations about it, and cal∣led the great Beare <HI>Manquahanum,</HI> which in their language doth signifie the Sunne.</P>
<P>I might heere speake something touching my owne experience, of the willingnesse of the Hea∣thens in gen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rall in all the Easterne parts of the world, where I haue trauailed, how ready they are to receiue the Gospel, if there were but Preachers amongst them that could and would instruct them by their Doctrine and Life. And of one of them in speciall,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Peter Pope, so named by his Maiestie.</NOTE> which I brought with me out of <HI>India</HI> to <HI>England,</HI> and taught him (I not being able to speak otherwise to him, nor he to mee, but by signes,) to speake, to reade and write the English tongue and hand, both Romane and Secretary, within lesse then the space of a yeare, so that his Maiestie and many of the Nobilitie wondered at his hand; and within the compasse of three yeares, I taught him the grounds of Religion, and to learn most of
<PB N="30" REF="19"/>
Saint <HI>Pa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>les</HI> Epistles by heart, and to giue a pub∣lique confession of his Faith the day hee was bap∣tized in a famous assembly heere in the Cittie, be∣fore the right worshipfull the <HI>East India Company,</HI> and since to write the Latine Epistles heereunto adioyned.</P>
<P>I could heere say much of the double diligence of Iesuites their poysoning with the Coloquin∣tida of Popery many thousand soules in the <HI>E<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dies</HI> and <HI>Iapan,</HI> and other the remotest parts of the world: All which might bee Motiues strong enough to stirre you vp to haue a greater care of the planting of the Gospell in your Plantations.</P>
<P>But Time now calleth vppon mee to excite you, as to labour to procure and send ouer honest and painefull Preachers, so in the second place to haue a care (as I know you haue) to pro∣cure and send ouer skilfull and pianefull Trades∣men and Husbandmen, to follow their trades, and to cultiuate the ground.</P>
<P>Our Countrey aboundeth with people; your Colony wanteth them: you all know that there is nothing more dangerous for the estate of Com∣monwealths, then when the people doe increase to a greater number and multitude, then may iustly parall<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll with the largenesse of the place and coun∣try in which they liue. For, euen as bloud, though it be the best humour in the body, yet if it abound in greater quantitie, then the vessell and state of the body will contayne and beare, doeth indanger the body, and oftentimes destroyes it: so although the honour of a King be in the multitude of people (as
<PB N="31" REF="19"/>
wise King <HI>Salomon</HI> speaketh) yet when this multi∣tude of people increaseth to ouer great a number,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Pro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. 14.28.</NOTE> the common wealth stands subiect to many peril∣lous inconneniences, as famine, pouerty, and sun∣dry other sorts of calamities.</P>
<P>Thus hauing falne into this point of exalting God in the congregation of the people, and the as∣sembly of the Elders, I haue here good occasion offered to mee to blesse God for the <HI>prudence</HI> and <HI>prouidence</HI> of this honourable citie, the honourable <HI>Elders</HI> thereof, the honourable <HI>Lord Maior,</HI> and the right worshipfull the <HI>Aldermen</HI> his brethren; who seeing this Cittie to be mightily increased, and fea∣ring lest the ouer-flowing multitude of inhabitants should, like too much bloud in the body, infect the whole Cittie with <HI>plague</HI> and <HI>pouertie</HI>; haue there∣fore deuised in their great wisdomes a <HI>Remedy</HI> for this <HI>Malady,</HI> to wit, the transporting of their ouer-flowing multitude into <HI>Virginia</HI>; which was first put in practise in the Maioralitie of that worthy &amp; famous Lord Maior Sir <HI>George B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>wl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>,</HI> who se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t o∣uer a hundred persons, the halfe of their charge be∣ing borne by the Citie; the other halfe by the Ho∣nourable <HI>Virginia</HI> Company; which worthy course was afterwards followed by the right worshipfull Sir <HI>William Cockins,</HI> in whose Maioraltie were sent ouer a hundred more in the like nature. And now likewise the right Honourable, the present Lord Maior, with the right worshipfull the Aldermen his brethren, intend to con<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>inue this course, that they may ease the Citie of a many that are ready to starue, and do starue dayly in our streetes (to the
<PB N="32" REF="20"/>
great griefe of all tender-hearted and mercifull men) for want of foode to put into their mouthes. This course, I say, they haue taken already, and meane to prosecute it, as I am informed, to the end they may preserue this famous Cittie in greater <HI>Peace</HI> and <HI>Prosperitie</HI>: Herein wisely imitattng the prudent and prouident <HI>husbandman,</HI> whom they see thus to deale with his grounds, when they are ouercharged with cattle: For, as he by remouing thē from one ground to another, prouideth well both for his cattle and for his ground: so they in their wisedoms, by remouing their super-increasing peo∣ple from the Citty to <HI>Virginia,</HI> haue prouided well both for this Cittie and their people: for, whereas many of those which were sent ouer, were a burden to this Citty, they are now through the good go∣uernment there, and Gods blessing vpon the works their hands) become men able to liue of themselues in good sort and fashion in <HI>Virginia</HI>; being before their sending ouer like to vnconuerted <HI>Onesymus,</HI> vnp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ofitable vnto all;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Philem. ver. 1<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</NOTE> and now by their being there, like vnto the same <HI>Onesymus,</HI> but truely conuer∣ted, profitable to the Plantation, and to the Cit∣tie; to the one by their <HI>paines,</HI> to the other by their <HI>prayers,</HI> blessing God from the bottome of their hearts that they were sent from <HI>London</HI> to <HI>Vir∣ginia</HI>; yea, blessing also the Lord <HI>Maiors,</HI> in whose time they were sent ouer.</P>
<P>I may say of this singular prudence and proui∣dence of this honourable Cittie, what our Sauiour sayd of the fact of <HI>Marie Magdalen</HI> in powring her
<PB N="33" REF="20"/>
costly oyntment on his sacred head (howsoeuer some sonnes of <HI>Beliall</HI> maligne this worthy worke, as <HI>Iudas</HI> the Traitor, and some of hell, maligned <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>at act of <HI>Ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ies</HI> anoynting of Christ, pretending <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e good of the poore, but intending it as much as his owne saluation, which was little or nothing at all,)<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ioh. 12.3.4. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>c Mat. 26.13.</NOTE> <HI>Verily I say vnto you wheresoeuer this Gospell shall bee preached, throughought all the world, there shall also this that she hath done be spoken of, for a me∣moriall of her.</HI> So verily, I say of this honourable City and worthy <HI>Elders</HI> thereof, that so long as there shall continue any English in <HI>Virginia</HI> (and we hope their race shall continue there till the second comming of our blessed Sauiour) transported from this Citie thither, they shall not c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ase to pray for the prosperitie of this famous Citie, and wor∣thy gouernours thereof. Wherefore let me beseech so many of the right. Worshipfull and wor∣thy Gouernours of this famous Cittie, as are present, (and I humbly intreate them, to stirre vppe all such as are absent) to proceede as they haue begunne,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Pro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. 4.18.</HI></NOTE> that their <HI>Way may shine as the light that shineth more and more vnto the per∣fect day</HI>; that what was spoken of <HI>Ruth,</HI> may bee verified in them;<NOTE PLACE="marg">Ruth 3.10.</NOTE> <HI>Thou hast shewed more goodnesse in the latter end, then at the beginning:</HI> and that that may bee their praise, which is recorded to be the commendation of the Church of <HI>Thy<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tir<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>;</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">Re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. 2.19.</NOTE> <HI>I know thy workes, and thy loue and seruice, and faith and patience; and how thy workes are more at the last then as the first.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="34" REF="21"/>Right Worshipfull, yee are plentifull in other good workes, the maintaining of your Ho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pitals, and other publike workes in this famous Cittie, preach your munificence through all the world,<NOTE PLACE="marg">R<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. 8. &amp; 16.19.</NOTE> as the faith and obedience of the <HI>Romans</HI> was publi∣shed abroad among all. O be rich in well doing this way likewise, that it may be sayd of you, <HI>Many haue done worthily for the plantation in Virginia, but the honourable Citty of London surmounteth them all.</HI> Your Cittie (as I sayd) aboundeth in people (and long may it doe so) the Plantation in <HI>Virginia</HI> is ca∣pable enough to receiue them; O take cour<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e to ease your Cittie, and to prouide well for your peo∣ple by sending them ouer thither; that both they of that Colony there, and they of your owne Cittie here, may liue to blesse your prudent and prouident gouernment ouer them. For, I haue heard many of the painfullest labourers of your Cittie, euen with teares bemoane the desolate estate of their poore wiues and children; who though they rise earely, taw and teare their flesh all the day long with hard labour, and goe late to bed, and feede almost all the weeke long vpon browne bread and cheese, yet are scarce able to put bread in their mouthes at the weekes end, and cloathes on their backes at the yeares end; and all because worke is so hard to be come by, and there be so many of the same Trade, that they can not thriue one for another. Right Worshipfull, I beseech you ponder (as I know you doe) the forlorne estate of many of the best members of your Citty, and helpe them, O helpe them out of their misery; what you bestow vppon
<PB REF="21"/>
them in their transportation to VIRGINIA, they will repay it at present with their Prayers, and when they are able with their Purses; and GOD in the meane while, will plentifully re∣ward your liberalitie this way with his blessing vpon your famous Citie, vpon your selues, vpon your posteritie: For doth not your mer∣cifull God, the Lord of Hosts,<NOTE PLACE="marg">Mal. 3. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>0</NOTE> bid you <HI>proue him, if hee will not open the windowes of heauen vnto you, and powre you out a blessing without measure?</HI></P>
<P>And that I may bend my speech vnto all, se∣ing so many of the Lords Worthies haue done worthily in this noble Action: yea, and se∣ing that some of them greatly rejoyce in this (as I haue heard it from their owne mouthes) that GOD hath inabled them to helpe forward this glorious Worke, both with their Prayers and with their Purses, let it be your griefe and sorrow to be exempted from the Company of so many honourable minded men, and from this noble Plantation, tending so highly to the advancement of the Gospell; and to the ho∣nouring of our drad Soveraigne, by inlarging of his Kingdomes, and adding a fifth Crowne vnto his other foure: for, <HI>En dat Virginia quin∣tam,</HI> is the Motto of the Legal Seale of VIR∣GINIA. And let mee, in a word, shut vp all, vnto you all, that hath beene spoken with that exhortation of the Apostle;<NOTE PLACE="marg">1. Cor. 15.5<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</NOTE> <HI>My beloved brethren,
<PB N="36" REF="22"/>
be yee stedfast, vnmoueable, aboundant alwayes in the worke of the Lord: for as much as you know that your labour is not in vaine in the</HI> LORD.</P>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="letter">
<PB REF="22"/>
<HEAD>To the most Illustrious Knight, Sir <HI>Thomas Smith,</HI> the most prudent Gouernour of the East-Indy Company, eternall felicity in the Lord.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>Right Worshipfull,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>IN many respects to be reuerenced by me. May it please your Worship to pardon my boldnesse in visiting you with this rude Epistle, to the end that I may shew my thankefulnesse towards you for your great and many benefits bestowed vpon me: As soone as God shal enable me to make a greater progresse in the Latine tongue, you may expect a longer; yea, perhaps a more elegant and e∣loquent Letter. In the interim I doubt not but your Worship (in regard of your Clemencie to∣wards me) will accept in good part these witnesses of a thankefull mind. The Almightie and all pow∣erfull God preserue you long in health, that you may be (as you are) a grace and ornament to the Companie of Marchants, that you may attaine to high Honour here on earth, and most ample glorie hereafter in Heauen: <HI>Farewell.</HI></P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE>From your Royall <HI>Iames,</HI> <DATE>this 24. of <HI>April</HI> 1620.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED>A Fauorite of your Illustrious dignity. <HI>Peter Pope.</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="letter">
<PB REF="23"/>
<HEAD>To the VVorshipfull and worthy Captaine, <HI>Martin Pring,</HI> Commander of the Sea Nauy of the East-India Com∣pany in <HI>India.</HI></HEAD>
<P>I Shal peraduenture seeme bold (most Illustrious <HI>Mecoenas</HI>) daring to trouble your learned eares with this rude Epistle, but your humanity to∣wards all, and beneuolent loue toward the learned incouraged me, though the least of the learned, yet most desirous of learning, and a louer of learned men, to present vnto you these first fruits of my wit, and first tryall in the latine tongue; to the end I may testifie how much I loue both you and the excellent gifts and graces of God bestowed vpon you. Now if you will bee pleased to take in good part, and haue respect to these vnpolished lines, you may perhaps ore it bee long, expect from the some more learned and better digested Letters. Farewell Worshipfull Sir.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE>From the <HI>Iames</HI> Royall <DATE>.22. Ianuary 1619.</DATE></DATELINE></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="letter">
<PB REF="23"/>
<HEAD>To the same.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>Worshipfull Sir,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>IN regard of late it was your pleasure to witnesse your loue to me by a gift, to the end that here∣after I might account you not onely a speciall friend, but also a worthy supporter of me in lear∣ning; it was most acceptable vnto mee: and as I embrace this pledge of your beneuolence, so inter∣changeably I promise my selfe to be respectiue to∣wards you, according as your piety and liberality deserue. Of both which towards all, especially to∣wards me, this token is a sufficient witnesse. For the present I haue but little, which I may render for your great liberality towards mee (and to re∣turne nothing at all, were altogether a signe of an vngrateful mind) vnlesse it be this small Paper-gift. Now if I may perceiue that any gift of this kind shall be acceptable to you, I will satisfie you either with these or the like euen to the full. Farewell Worshipfull and worthy Sir: The Lord alwayes guid you with his Spirit, and vphold you with his mighty power, and euery day inrich you with the rich graces of his Spirit. </P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE>From the <HI>Iames</HI> Royall, <DATE>the 20. of May. 1620.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED>Your Worships in all dutifull obedience. <HI>Peter Pope.</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="letter">
<PB REF="24"/>
<HEAD>Illustrissimo equiti aurato, Domino Thomae Smit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, societatis Mercato∣rum Indiae orientalis gubernatori pruden∣tissimo, aeternam in Domino felicitatem.</HEAD>
<P>CLarissime Domine, multis nominibus plurimùm mihi colende, libet si licet epistolio te hoc, rudi licet, in<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>isere; quò gratitudinem in te m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>am, ob magna multa{que} tua in me collata beneficia tester. Vbi De∣us maiores in lingua latina dederit progressus, longiores fortassis etiam elegantiores a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> magis disertas, a me ex∣pectabis literulas. Interea non dubito quin cels<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>do vestra, pro ea quae tua in me est <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lementia, ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> grati animi testes, aequi boni{que} consulat. Deus opt. Max. te longè multùm{que} incolumem seru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> quò illustri Mer∣catorum Societati sis decorì ac ornamento eximio, at{que} ita hîc fauorem assequaris ampliorem, &amp; in coelis amplissimum. </P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE>Vale ex Regali vestra Iacobo <DATE>.24. Aprilis 1620.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED>Illustrissima amplitudinis <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>a studio <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iss<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>s. <HI>Petrus Papa.</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="letter">
<PB REF="24"/>
<HEAD>Clarissimo Domino D. Martino Pringo, Nauticae Classis societatis Mercatorum Indiae orientalis, praefecto vigilantissimo, <HI>Petrus Papa. S. P. D.</HI></HEAD>
<P>AVdax fortassis videbor (Mecoen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s Illustrissi∣me) qui a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>deam doctas <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uas aures r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> hoc epi∣stolio interturbare; sod quae tua est in omnes ba∣mani<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s, &amp; in li<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>era<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> ben<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us amor, me (literaru∣rum licet minimum, literarū tamen studio fissim<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>, &amp; literatorum amantissimum) induxit, vt has ingenij mei primitias; &amp; in lingua latina primum specimen tuo <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>∣mini inscriberem, quò testatum faciam quami <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, &amp; exi∣mias in te collatas Dei dotes, colam. Quòd si inexpolit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> has literalas aqu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> boni{que} consulueris, e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iores fort<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ss<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> breui &amp; magis comptas a nobis expectabis. Vale pl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ri∣mùm mihi colende.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE>Ex Regati Iacobo <DATE><HI>22.</HI> Ianuarij <HI>1619</HI></DATE>.</DATELINE></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="letter">
<PB REF="25" MS="y"/>
<HEAD>Eidem.</HEAD>
<P>QVOD <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uper mihi per donum innotescere volu∣isti (Domine plurimùm mihi colende) vt post∣hacte non inter amicos solum, sed &amp; inter beneficos Mecoenates cens<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>am, gratum mihi fuit: ac si∣cuti amplector hanc beneuolentiaetua tesseram, ita vicis∣s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lliceor me beneuolo erga te fore animo, prout &amp; tua pi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tas, &amp; liberalitas merentur; cuius vtrius{que} in om∣nes, me preserti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>, tantis tuis d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nis ill<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> specimen ap∣paret. Inpresentiarum parum est quod protanta tua in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e liberalitate referam (nihil autem referre animi es∣set <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gratissimi) praeter chartaceum hoc mun<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s∣cul<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>. Quòd fih<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sce<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>odi mu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mosyna persp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>xere tibi gr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ta ess<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>is a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> similib<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s te ad satietatem, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> ad fastidium vs{que} satiabo. Vale Domine eximie, &amp; plu∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>imùm mihi ex anim<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> colende. Dominus Spiritu te suo semper gubernet, sustineat inuicta virtute &amp; suis do∣nis indies locupletet.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE>Ex Regali Iacobo <DATE>May <HI>20. 1620.</HI></DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED>Vestra celsitudinis studio fissi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>, Petrus Papa.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

