<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A letter to the Right Honourable Thomas Alyn Lord Mayor of the City of London sent to him from the committee appointed to disperse the general remonstrance and protestation of the 16th of November last, into the several cities and conuties [sic] of England and Wales, to be by him communicated to the aldermen, and Common-Council of the said City.</TITLE></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A88045</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">Wing L1750</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">Thomason 669.f.22[16]</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC R211360</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99870090</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99870090</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">163599</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88045)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 163599)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 247:669f22[16])</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="2">A letter to the Right Honourable Thomas Alyn Lord Mayor of the City of London sent to him from the committee appointed to disperse the general remonstrance and protestation of the 16th of November last, into the several cities and conuties [sic] of England and Wales, to be by him communicated to the aldermen, and Common-Council of the said City.</TITLE><AUTHOR>England and Wales. Parliament. Committee appointed to Disperse the General Remonstrance and Protestation.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed by I.C.,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>[1659]</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Publication date from Wing.</NOTE><NOTE>Annotation on Thomason copy: "xber [i.e. December]. 9. 1659".</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Alleyne, Thomas, --  Sir, fl. 1660.</TERM><TERM>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM>London (England) --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</TERM><TERM>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2010-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2010-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>SPi Global</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2010-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Mona Logarbo</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2010-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Mona Logarbo</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2011-06</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A88045">
<STC T="W">L1750</STC>
<STC T="T">669.f.22[16]</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99870090</BIBNO>
<VID>163599</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="letter">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<HEAD>A Letter to the Right Honourable THOMAS ALYN Lord Mayor of The City of London, sent to him from the Committee appointed To Disperse The General Remonstrance and Protestation of the 16<SUP>th</SUP> of November last, into the Several Cities and Conuties of ENGLAND and WALES, To be by him Communicated to the Aldermen, and Common-Councel of the said City.</HEAD>
<OPENER><DATELINE><DATE>December 6th 1659.</DATE> At the Committee appointed to disperse the General <HI>Remonstrance</HI> and <HI>Protestation,</HI> into the several Cities and Counties of <HI>England</HI> and <HI>Wales.</HI></DATELINE><LB/>
<SALUTE>Right Honourable,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>WE being appointed by lawful Authority, to disperse the General <HI>Remonstrance</HI> and <HI>Protestation</HI> as aforesaid, have thought good hereby, to direct the same here enclosed to your Lordship, desiring you to communicate the same to the rest of your Brethren the Worshipful Aldermen, and together with them, to the Court of Common-Council of the City of <HI>London;</HI> and to do therein, as by the printed Letter herein also enclosed, or as by the Remonstrance it self is directed, or otherwise, as to Your and their Grave wisdoms shall seem most meet. We very well know that your Lordship, and the Aldermen, with the Court of Com∣mon-Council, are really sencible of the great and miserable distractions, and confusion the three Nations are at present almost over∣whelmed with, and of the sudden and great decay of Trade by reason thereof; but especially of that sad and miserable distraction, and confusion which happened in this famous City on <HI>Munday</HI> the 5th instant, and of the several notorious Murders then Committed: all which, we conceive, have been of late cheifly occasioned by the interruption of the Parliament, the <HI>13th</HI> of <HI>Oct.</HI> last; and also, that the &amp; distractiaons &amp; decay of Trade, is like to grow every day worse and worse, unlesse some speedy way &amp; means be found out, to put a stop to the Torrent of the Rampant Sword, that so the Parliament may again return with safety, to the free exercise &amp; discharge of their trust in settling the Government of these Nations, upon true &amp; sure Foundations of a Free State &amp; Common-wealth; by which all the good people of these Nations, both as men and Christians, may enjoy their Common and equal Rights and Freedoms, both in their Persons and Estates, which undoubtedly is, and will be, the only, speediest, and most probable way and means, for a full and free Trade once more to flourish in these Nations, to the encouragement of all Art, labour and industry, the only Glory and Sinews of a good &amp; well or∣dered Common-wealth. And to the end no doubt may remain in your Lordship, whether the said Parliament be the lawful Supream Le∣gislative Authority of these Nations, be pleased for your better information therein, to read the Statute of the 16 <HI>Cor.</HI> 7. whereby it is declared and enacted, That this Parliament shall not be dissolved, prorogued, or adjourned, but by Act of Parliament to be past for that purpose, nor shall at any time or times be adjourned, unless it be by themselves or by their own order; And that all and every thing, and things whatsoever, done or to be done for the adjourning, proroguing or dissolving the said Parliament contrary to the said Act, shall be utterly void, and of no effect; By which, as also by the several reasons and grounds for the making the said Act declared in the preamble thereof, together with the Parliaments answer to the Kings Letter of the third of <HI>March</HI> 43, Printed in the Booke of Collections of publick Orders, and Ordinances, <HI>&amp;c.</HI> fol. 451, by which with the advice and concurent consent of the Com∣missioners of <HI>Scotland,</HI> for the better solution of the said question, the PARLIAMENT told the KING, That they were bound to let him know, that they were called together according to the known FUNDAMENTAL LAWS of the Nation, and their continuance settled and established by a Law, and therefore they were bound in duty, and accordingly did then resolve with their lives and fortunes to preserve and defend the just Rights and Authority of this Parliament, and likewise by severall other arguments and reasons, very fully and learnedly set forth and printed in the same and other books, your Lordship may and will fully and clearly understand, that notwithstanding all or any of the seclutions and interruptions they have or shall at any time meet withall, yet so long as the said Act stands unrepeall'd, and that a <HI>Quorom</HI> according to the antient Custome of <HI>England</HI> of the Members that last sat are living, they are and unavoydably must and will be the Lawfull and Supreame Legislative Authority of these Nations; And therefore not to trouble your Lordship any further, but hoping according to the duty of your place, and the trust re∣posed in you, being Lawfully called to so high and Honourable place and Seat of Authority, your Lordship will speedily use all Lawfull wayes and means for restoring this Parliament to the safe and free exercise, and discharge of their trust for the ends aforesaid, which we judge will undoubtedly be by the assisting hand of Gods providence, the only meanes under Heaven to heale all our breaches, put an end to all our publique distractions, which at present is ready even to swallow us up in a Flood of generall Confusion: Free us from that Bondage and Slavery the people of these Nations for many years past, but especially at prefent are like to undergoe by forceable imprisoning their persons, and violent seizing upon and taking away their Estates contrary unto, and against the known and good Laws of this Commonwealth, and that this poor miserable and devided Nation but once flourishing, and now a scorne and reproach to all Nations, by reason of our distractions and often changes may as formerly againe become a terror to all the Nations round about it, and your Lordship may be confident that no assembly of men in these Nations <HI>Rebus sic Scantibus</HI> can be better confided in, to secure the promises unto us then this Parliament, who have all along been and now are ingaged for the same things; And let not your Lordship and the City of <HI>London</HI> think that they shall be alone in this good work, for all the Counties in <HI>England</HI> and <HI>VVales</HI> are ingaged in the same as by the Remonstrance your Lordship may understand, and within very few dayes will be ready to lend their assistance thereto, so that having Nakedly and plainly laid before your <HI>Lordship</HI> the hearts and spirits of the people ingaged in this Remonstrance, and their good affections to this work, we doubt not but that your Lordship and this City will be ready and willing to do the same, that so this good work may if possible without the expence of blood be soon finished, and all just interests thereby fully satisfied, and all persons have cause to rejoyce that they can once more set down under the wholsome Vines of peace and safety.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Signed in the name, and by the consent and appointment of the Committe. <HI>JOHN FREEMAN,</HI> Clerk to the said Committee.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
<TRAILER>For the Right Honorable <HI>Thomas Allyn,</HI> Lord Mayor of the City of<HI>London.</HI></TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="colophon">
<P>London Printed by <HI>I. C.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

